[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
This is CS50.
这是 CS50。
This is week 2 wherein we will ultimately learn how to use memory,
这是第二周，我们将最终学习如何使用内存，
but we thought we'd first begin with a bit of story time.
但我们认为应该先从讲故事开始。
And in fact, allow me to walk over to our brave volunteers who
事实上，让我走到我们勇敢的志愿者那里，
have joined us already.
他们已经加入了我们。
First here on my left, we have who?
在我左边的第一个，是谁？
AKSHAYA: Hi, I'm Akshaya.
阿克沙娅：嗨，我是阿克沙娅。
I'm a first year in Mathews, and I'm planning
我是一年级生，在马修斯学习，我计划
on concentrating in chemical and physical biology and CS.
专注于化学和物理生物学以及计算机科学。
DAVID MALAN: Wonderful, welcome.
大卫·马兰：太棒了，欢迎。
And let me have you hang on to the microphone
请你拿着麦克风
first because we've asked Akshaya to tell us a short story.
首先，因为我们请阿克沙娅给我们讲个小故事。
So in your envelope, you have the beginnings of a story.
所以，你的信封里有一个故事的开头。
If you wouldn't mind reading it aloud.
如果你不介意的话，请大声读出来。
And as she reads this, allow us to give some thought as to what
当她读的时候，让我们思考一下
level Akshaya reads at, so to speak.
阿克沙娅的阅读水平，这么说吧。
AKSHAYA: All right, it's a long one, get ready.
阿克沙娅：好吧，它很长，准备好。
One fish, two fish, red fish, blue fish.
一条鱼，两条鱼，红鱼，蓝鱼。
DAVID MALAN: All right, very well done.
大卫·马兰：好的，做得很好。
What grade level would you say she reads at if you think back
如果你回忆起中学、小学，你会说她的阅读水平是几年级？
to your middle school, grade school, when
当老师说你达到了这个水平或者那个水平，或者这个水平的时候？
maybe teacher said you read at this level or maybe this level or this one
也许老师说你达到了这个水平，或者那个水平，或者这个水平。
here?
在这里？
So OK, no offense taken yet.
所以，好的，还没人被冒犯。
AUDIENCE: 1st grade.
观众：一年级。
DAVID MALAN: I'm sorry?
大卫·马兰：你说什么？
AUDIENCE: 1st grade.
观众：一年级。
DAVID MALAN: 1st grade.
大卫·马兰：一年级。
OK, so first grade is just about right.
好的，所以一年级差不多是正确的。
And in fact, according to one algorithm, this text here,
事实上，根据一种算法，这篇文章，
one fish, two fish, red fish, blue fish, would indeed
一条鱼，两条鱼，红鱼，蓝鱼，的确
be considered to actually be 1st grade or just before first grade.
被认为是实际上一年级或者刚上一年级之前。
So let's-- and why is that, though?
所以，让我们——为什么是这样的呢？
Why did you say 1st grade?
你为什么说是一年级？
AUDIENCE: It's very basic.
观众：很简单。
DAVID MALAN: It's very basic.
大卫·马兰：很简单。
But what is it about these words that are very basic?
但是，这些词为什么很简单呢？
Do you want to identify yourself?
你想自我介绍吗？
AKSHAYA: Sure.
阿克沙娅：当然。
They're all one syllable and they're very simple like colors and stuff
它们都是单音节的，而且很简单，就像颜色之类的东西
like that.
那样。
DAVID MALAN: Spot-on.
大卫·马兰：完全正确。
So like they're very short words they're very short sentences.
所以，它们都是很短的词，很短的句子。
And you would expect that of a younger person.
你会期望年轻人是这样。
All right, let's go ahead and hand the mic to your next volunteer
好的，让我们把麦克风递给下一个志愿者
here if you'd like to introduce yourself.
如果你想自我介绍的话。
ETHAN: Yes.
伊森：好的。
Hi, I'm Ethan.
嗨，我是伊森。
I'm a first year in Canada, and I'll be concentrating in economics.
我是一名加拿大的一年级学生，我将专注于经济学。
DAVID MALAN: Wonderful.
大卫·马兰：太棒了。
And in your folder, we have another story to share.
在您的文件夹中，我们还有另一个故事要分享。
ETHAN: Congratulations.
伊森：恭喜你。
Today is your day.
今天是你的日子。
You're off to great places.
你将前往伟大的地方。
You're off and away.
你出发了。
DAVID MALAN: So this text might sound familiar, particularly
大卫·马兰：所以这个文本可能听起来很熟悉，尤其是
on the heels of high school, perhaps.
在高中之后，也许。
What grade level might he be reading at?
他可能在哪个年级阅读？
So maybe 5th grade.
所以可能是五年级。
And why 5th grade?
为什么是五年级？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
大卫·马兰：好的。
Yeah.
是的。
So a little more complicated.
所以有点复杂。
Like the words-- we've got some more punctuation, we have an apostrophe,
比如这些词——我们有更多标点符号，有一个撇号，
we have longer sentences.
我们有更长的句子。
And indeed, according to one algorithm, not quite 5th grade,
事实上，根据一种算法，还不完全是五年级，
but we would adjudicate your reading level to be 3rd.
但我们会判定你的阅读水平是三年级。
But let's see if we can't do one final flourish here
但让我们看看我们是否可以在这里做最后的润色
if you'd like to introduce yourself and your story.
如果你想介绍你自己和你的故事。
MIKE: Hi, I'm Mike.
迈克：你好，我是迈克。
I'm also a first year.
我也是一年级。
I'm in Weld, and I'm planning on concentrating
我在韦尔德，我计划专注于
in biomedical engineering.
生物医学工程。
DAVID MALAN: Welcome.
大卫·马兰：欢迎。
And your tale?
你的故事？
MIKE: It was a bright, cold day in April and the clocks were striking 13.
迈克：那是一个明媚寒冷的四月天，钟声敲响了13下。
Winston Smith, his chin nuzzled into his breast in an effort
温斯顿·史密斯，他把下巴埋在胸前，试图
to escape the vile wind, slipped quickly through the glass doors
躲避恶风，迅速地穿过玻璃门
of victory mansions, though not quickly enough
胜利豪宅，尽管不够快
to prevent a swirl of gritty dust from entering along with him.
以至于无法阻止一股沙尘随他一起进入。
DAVID MALAN: All right, so escalated quickly.
大卫·马兰：好的，升级很快。
And someone's guess at this reading level?
有人猜想这个阅读水平是多少？
AUDIENCE: 1984.
观众：1984。
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
大卫·马兰：什么？
Oh, OK, 1984 is indeed the text in question, and in what
哦，好的，1984确实是所讨论的文本，你在什么
grade did you perhaps read that book?
年级读过这本书？
So I'm hearing 8th, I'm hearing 10th.
所以我听到的是八年级，我听到的是十年级。
So indeed, 10th grade is what a certain algorithm would actually
所以事实上，十年级是某种算法实际上
adjudicate that reading level to be at.
判定那个阅读水平应该是在。
And consider now the heuristics.
现在考虑一下启发式方法。
So we started with very small words, very small sentences, very easy words,
所以我们从非常小的词语、非常短的句子、非常简单的词语开始，
and then things sort of escalated into more interesting, more
然后事情逐渐升级，变得更加有趣，更加
sophisticated English, more interesting sentence construction and the like.
复杂的英语，更加有趣的句子结构等等。
So I bet if we could somehow capture those characteristics of text,
所以，我敢说，如果我们能够以某种方式捕捉到这些文本的特征，
the length of the words and the lengths of the sentences
词语的长度和句子的长度
and the position of the punctuation, I daresay,
以及标点符号的位置，我敢说，
even using week 1 material and, today, week 2 material,
即使使用第一周的材料，以及今天第二周的材料，
we'll be able to actually write code and implement an algorithm like that
我们将能够实际编写代码并实现这样的算法
can take these spoken words, put them to paper,
可以将这些口语词语写下来，
and actually analyze roughly what that reading level might be.
并实际分析一下那个阅读水平可能是什么。
So that's just a teaser of what lies ahead.
所以这只是对未来的一些预告。
For now, allow us to thank our volunteers, each of whom
现在，让我们感谢我们的志愿者，每个人都
gets a wonderful parting gift here to read at home.
在这里收到一份很棒的离别礼物，可以在家阅读。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
All right.
好的。
And Thank you all so much.
非常感谢大家。
So with that said, there's another domain that we'll explore this week,
所以，我们这周将探索另一个领域，
and indeed, what you'll find in the coming weeks
事实上，在接下来的几周内你会发现
is that beyond just focusing on some of the fundamentals and the basics
除了专注于一些基础知识之外
like we've really done in the past couple of weeks talking about loops
就像我们在过去几周谈论循环那样，我们确实做了
and conditionals and Boolean expressions,
以及条件语句和布尔表达式，
really building blocks or puzzle pieces that we can assemble together,
真正可以拼凑在一起的积木或拼图碎片，
we're going to increasingly start talking about applications
我们将越来越多地开始讨论应用程序
of these ideas which, after all, is why any field is perhaps
这些想法的应用，毕竟，这也是为什么任何领域也许
important and applicable.
很重要且适用。
So here, for instance, we'll consider not only reading levels today,
因此，例如，我们今天将不仅考虑阅读水平，
and in turn, in problem set 2 this week, but also the world of cryptography,
反过来，在本周的习题集 2 中，还有密码学的世界，
which is the art, the science of scrambling, encrypting
它是加密、混淆信息的艺术和科学
information, and ciphering it in such a way
信息，并以这样的方式对其进行加密
that you can send a message securely through the internet, through the air,
这样你就可以通过互联网、通过空中安全地发送消息，
through any medium even though someone might intercept it.
通过任何媒介，即使有人可能会拦截它。
Ideally, thanks to cryptography, they shouldn't
理想情况下，多亏了密码学，他们不应该
be able to decrypt it or actually determine what it there says.
能够解密它或实际确定它上面写了什么。
So for instance, if you were to receive a message like this, at first glance,
例如，如果你收到这样一条消息，乍一看，
it's indeed a bit cryptic.
它确实有点神秘。
Three words maybe, but by day's end, we'll
也许三个词，但到今天结束的时候，我们将
have decrypted even this message for you.
为您解密这条消息。
So up until now, though, we've had some sort of conceptual training wheels on.
然而，直到现在，我们一直在使用一些概念性的辅助轮。
And I gave us this picture last week when we introduced the tool make via
上周我们在介绍工具 make 时给出了这张图片，
which you can make programs out of your source code because you need to turn
你可以用源代码创建程序，因为你需要将
that source code into machine code, the 0's and 1's.
该源代码转换为机器代码，即 0 和 1。
And in the middle here was this thing called a compiler.
中间这个东西叫做编译器。
But it really has been kind of an abstraction for us,
但它确实对我们来说是一种抽象，
and we've sort of had these metaphorical and physical training
我们也有一些隐喻性和物理性的辅助轮
wheels here in the sense that we haven't really
在这里，从某种意义上来说，我们没有真正地
needed to care like what the compiler is doing, how it works and so forth.
需要关心编译器在做什么，它如何工作等等。
But today, what we thought we'd do is peel back a bit of that layer so
但今天，我们想做的是剥离那层的一部分，以便
that even though after today you'll continue
即使在今天之后，你也会继续
to be able to use commands like make and sort of return
能够使用像 make 这样的命令并返回
to the beautiful abstraction that is not caring about some
到那个美好的抽象状态，即不必关心一些
of these lower-level details, we'll offer you
这些较低级别的细节，我们会向你提供
a glimpse of how some of these things work.
一些关于这些东西是如何运作的见解。
Because so that inevitably when something goes wrong,
因为这样，当不可避免地出现问题时，
you've got some bug, you're having some problem,
你遇到了一个错误，你遇到了问题，
you'll have a bottom-up understanding of what it could actually be.
你将对问题可能是什么有一个自下而上的理解。
And indeed, these basics, you'll find, will very often
事实上，你会发现，这些基本知识经常
help you troubleshoot problems and really solve problems more generally.
帮助你解决问题，并且更一般地解决问题。
So here, for instance, is the code that we keep coming back to.
例如，这里就是我们一直反复使用的代码。
And this code here is the simplest of C programs that just says "hello, world."
这里面的代码是最简单的C程序，它只是说“hello, world”。
This is the source code.
这是源代码。
This, we claimed, was the corresponding machine code.
我们声称，这是相应的机器代码。
And it was that program called a compiler that
而且，正是那个被称为编译器的程序
converted one into the other.
将一个转换为另一个。
But let's dive a little more deeply this week
但是，让我们本周更深入地探讨一下
into what we mean by compiling code.
我们所说的编译代码到底是什么意思。
Like what is happening so that by day's end,
就像发生的事情，所以到了晚上，
nothing really feels like magic anymore.
没有什么感觉像魔法了。
It's not just that it goes from source code to machine code
不仅仅是它从源代码变为机器代码
and that's that, you understand what's actually being done for you,
就是这样，你明白为你做了什么，
and frankly, what other humans have done over the decades to make
而且坦白地说，几十年来，其他人做了什么来让
make as beautifully abstract and as simple as it now might seem to be.
让它变得如此抽象，如此简单，以至于现在看起来可能就是如此。
So here are a couple of commands that you've
所以这里有一些你已经
been in the habit of running when you want to first compile your code
习惯运行的命令，当你想要第一次编译你的代码时
and then execute your code.
然后执行你的代码。
But it turns out that make is actually running another command for you.
但事实证明，make实际上为你运行了另一个命令。
The first of several white lies we'll tell in the course
这是我们在这门课程中要讲的几个善意的谎言中的第一个
is that make itself is not a compiler, per se.
就是说make本身并不是编译器。
It's actually a program that automatically runs a compiler for you.
它实际上是一个自动为你运行编译器的程序。
And by that, I mean this.
我的意思是这个。
Let me go over to VS Code here and let me create our familiar hello.c program.
让我转到VS Code，让我创建我们熟悉的hello.c程序。
And I'm going to go ahead and do include stdio.h, int main void, and inside
我将继续进行include stdio.h、int main void，以及在
of the curly braces, printf "hello," comma, "world," backslash n semicolon.
花括号内，printf "hello," 逗号，"world," 反斜杠 n 分号。
So that's the code that we keep writing again and again.
所以，这就是我们一直反复编写的代码。
And up until now, if I wanted to compile that, I would do make hello
到目前为止，如果我想编译它，我会使用make hello
dot slash hello, and voila, now my program is made
点斜杠hello，瞧，现在我的程序已经做好了
and it actually executes.
它实际上是执行的。
But what's actually going on underneath the hood
但是，实际上在幕后
there is that make is running an actual compiler for you,
是make正在为你运行一个真正的编译器，
and the reveal today is that the compiler we have been using
而今天要揭示的是，我们一直在使用的编译器
is something called Clang for C language.
是名为Clang的C语言编译器。
And this is just another program whose purpose in life
而这只是一个程序，它在生命中的目的是
is actually to do the conversion of source code to machine code.
实际上是将源代码转换为机器代码。
But it turns out that Clang by itself can
但事实证明，Clang本身可以
be used very simply like you see here, clang hello.c,
像你在这里看到的一样，非常简单地使用，clang hello.c，
but it doesn't behave nearly as user-friendly as you might like.
但是它不像你期望的那样友好。
So in particular, let me go ahead and do this.
因此，特别是，让我继续做这个。
I'm going to go ahead and remove my compiled program
我将继续删除我编译的程序
by running rm for remove, which I alluded to briefly last time.
通过运行 rm 命令来删除，我上次简要提到了。
And then I'm going to say y for yes, remove that regular file.
然后我会输入 y 表示 yes，删除那个普通文件。
And if I go ahead now and run just clang of hello.c and hit Enter,
如果我现在继续运行 clang hello.c 并按回车键，
it seems to be successful, at least insofar as there's no error messages.
看起来是成功的，至少没有错误信息。
But if I try to do dot slash hello, Enter,
但如果我尝试执行 ./hello 并按回车键，
there is no such file or directory called hello.
没有名为 hello 的文件或目录。
That is because by default, Clang somewhat goofily like just
这是因为默认情况下，Clang 有点傻，就像
outputs a file name called a dot out.
输出一个名为 a.out 的文件。
Like why a?
为什么是 a？
Well, it's sort of a simple name. a dot out, technically for assembler output,
嗯，它是一个简单名称。a.out，技术上用于汇编输出，
but this just means this is the default file
但这只是意味着这是 Clang 将要给我们的默认文件名。
name that Clang is going to give us.
Clang 将要给我们的默认文件名。
So OK, it turns out I can do dot slash a dot out Enter, and voila,
所以，我发现我可以执行 ./a.out 并按回车键，然后，
that now is my program, but that's just a stupid name for a program.
现在它就是我的程序，但这只是一个愚蠢的程序名称。
It's not very user-friendly.
它不太人性化。
It's certainly not an icon you would want
它肯定不是你想
to put on people's desktops or phones.
放在人们的桌面或手机上。
So how can we do better?
所以我们怎样才能做得更好？
Well, it turns out, with Clang, we can configure it using
事实证明，在 Clang 中，我们可以使用
what we'll call command line arguments.
我们称之为命令行参数。
And command line arguments are actually something we've been using thus far,
命令行参数实际上是我们一直在使用的，
we just didn't slap this word on it, but command line arguments
我们只是没有给它加上这个词，但命令行参数
are additional words or shorthand notation
是在命令提示符处输入的额外单词或简写符号，它们以某种方式
that you typed at your command prompt that somehow
以某种方式修改程序的行为。
modify the behavior of a program.
修改程序的行为。
And you can perhaps guess where this is going.
你可能已经猜到这将走向何方。
It turns out that if I actually want to create a program called hello--
事实证明，如果我确实想创建一个名为 hello 的程序，
not a.out, which is the default, I can actually
而不是 a.out，它是默认的，我可以实际
do this-- clang, space, dash lowercase o, space, hello,
执行以下操作：clang，空格，-o，空格，hello，
or whatever I want to call the thing, space, hello.c.
或者我想要给它起任何名字，空格，hello.c。
And now if I hit Enter, nothing seems to happen,
现在如果我按回车键，似乎什么也没发生，
but now if I do ./hello and Enter, now I've actually got that program.
但现在如果我执行 ./hello 并按回车键，我现在就得到了那个程序。
So why is make useful?
那么，为什么 make 有用呢？
Well, it just saves us the trouble of having
嗯，它只是让我们不必每次
to type out this longer line of command any time
都输入这条较长的命令行
we actually want to compile the code.
我们实际上想要编译代码时。
But in fact, it gets even worse than that
但实际上，它比这更糟糕
with commands like clang or compilers in general
对于像 clang 这样的命令或一般的编译器
because consider this code here.
因为考虑一下这里代码。
Not just the version of "hello, world," but maybe the second version wherein
不仅仅是 “hello, world” 的版本，还有可能是第二版，其中
last week, I started to get user input by adding the CS50 Library using
上周，我开始通过使用 CS50 库来获取用户输入
get_string and then saying, "hello," comma, "David."
使用 get_string，然后说：“hello，”逗号，“David”。
Well, if I go back to VS Code and I modify this program
那么，如果我回到 VS Code 并修改这个程序
to be that same one--
变成跟那个一样，
so let me go ahead and include cs50.h at the top.
所以我先在顶部包含 cs50.h。
Let me get rid of this simple print line and instead give myself
我删除这条简单的打印语句，而是给自己
a string called name equals get_string, "What's your name?"
一个名为 name 的字符串，等于 get_string，"What's your name?"。
Question mark, just like we did in Scratch.
问号，就像我们在 Scratch 中做的那样。
Then I can do printf, quote-unquote, "hello," comma.
然后我可以执行 printf，引号-反引号，“hello”，逗号。
And previously I typed "world."
之前我输入了“world”。
I obviously don't want to type "David" because I want it to be dynamic.
我显然不想输入“David”，因为我希望它动态。
What did I type last week for as a placeholder?
上周我输入了什么作为占位符？
So yeah, just-- not Command-S, but %S. So %S in this case,
所以，是的，只是——不是 Command-S，而是 %S。在本例中，%S
which is a placeholder for any such string.
是任何此类字符串的占位符。
Then I can still do my new line, close, quote, comma, and then
然后我仍然可以进行我的新行，关闭、引号、逗号，然后
I can substitute in something like the value of the name variable.
我可以替换成类似于名称变量的值。
All right, so if I go ahead now and compile this,
好的，所以如果我现在继续编译它，
now last week, I could just do make hello and I'm on my way,
上周，我可以直接执行 make hello，然后我就完成了，
it worked just fine.
它运行良好。
But if I instead do clang manually, it turns out
但是，如果我手动执行 clang，结果发现
that this is not going to be sufficient now. clang -o hello, space, hello.c.
现在这样就不够用了。clang -o hello，空格，hello.c。
Exact same thing I typed a moment ago, but I
我刚才输入的完全一样，但是我
think I'm going to see some errors.
认为我将看到一些错误。
So what's this error hinting at here?
那么这里这个错误暗示着什么？
Well, at the very bottom, it's a bit arcane with its output,
好吧，在最底部，它的输出有点神秘，
and much of this you can ignore, but there are some certain key words.
而且很多东西你可以忽略，但是有一些关键的词。
What's the first maybe keyword you recognize in these three
在这些三行错误输出中，你第一个认出来的关键词是什么？
lines of erroneous output?
错误的输出？
So it mentions main.
它提到了 main。
That's not that much of a clue because that's the only thing I wrote so far.
这不是什么线索，因为那是迄今为止我唯一写的。
Second line, though, get_string.
第二行，get_string。
There's some issue with an undefined reference to get_string.
存在对 get_string 的未定义引用问题。
Now why might that be?
现在，为什么会出现这种情况？
I did include cs50.h, but that's apparently not
我已经包含了 cs50.h，但这显然不够
enough to teach the compiler about get_string.
让编译器了解 get_string。
Well, it turns out that if you're using a third-party library, one
好吧，事实证明，如果你正在使用第三方库，也就是
that doesn't necessarily come with C the language, something like CS50's, it
并不一定随 C 语言提供的库，像 CS50 的库，它
turns out that you additionally have to tell the compiler that you
事实证明，你还要额外告诉编译器，你要
want to use that library.
使用这个库。
And not just by including the header file,
不仅仅是包含头文件，
but by an additional command as well.
还需要额外的命令。
So when you run Clang, you want to provide an additional
所以当你运行 Clang 时，你要提供额外的
rather command line argument.
命令行参数。
Literally -l for library, which is a term I used last week, cs50.
确切地说，是 -l，代表 library，这是我上周用过的术语，cs50。
A library is just code that someone else wrote
库就是别人写的代码，
that you want to use in your project.
你想要在你的项目中使用的代码。
So if I really want to compile this version that uses the CS50 Library,
所以，如果我真的想要编译使用 CS50 库的版本，
I can still do clang o hello hello.c, but before I finish my thought,
我仍然可以执行 clang o hello hello.c，但是在完成我的思路之前，
I need to tell the compiler to link, so to speak, in the library CS50.
我需要告诉编译器，用通俗的话来说，链接进 CS50 库。
And now I hit Enter, the error message goes away, I can do ./hello,
现在我按下回车键，错误信息消失了，我可以执行 ./hello，
I can type in my name, and voila, we're back to week 1.
我可以输入我的名字，瞧，我们回到了第一周。
And this is why, suffice it to say, we introduce make,
这就是为什么，简而言之，我们引入了 make，
which is not a CS50 thing.
它不是 CS50 的东西。
This is a popular tool that real people in the real world
这是一个流行的工具，现实世界中的人们
use to automate these kinds of processes.
用来自动化这些流程。
So unbeknownst to you, make has been using
所以，在你不知情的情况下，make一直在使用
the -o for you. make, unbeknownst to you, has been using -l cs50 for you
-o 为你。make，在你不知情的情况下，一直在为你使用 -l cs50
just because it makes our lives easier.
仅仅是因为它让我们的生活更轻松。
But today, we thought we would deliberately
但今天，我们想故意
peel back this layer so we at least understand
剥离这一层，这样我们至少能理解
what's going on behind this abstraction that is make itself
make本身这种抽象背后的运作方式
and compiling more generally.
以及更一般意义上的编译。
So let me propose that compiling itself is not quite what
所以，我想说，编译本身并不完全是我们所描述的那样。
we've described it to be.
我们所描述的那样。
Compiling is like this catch-all phrase that apparently I claim
编译就像是一个包罗万象的词语，我似乎认为
goes from source code to machine code.
它可以将源代码转换为机器码。
But if we really want to get pedantic, which we'll do briefly,
但如果我们真的想要吹毛求疵，我们会简要地做到这一点，
but this is not a sign of things to come because this, too,
但这并非将来会发生的事情的预兆，因为这件事也
will be abstract away, compiling is just one of four steps that are involved
会被抽象掉，编译只是涉及的四个步骤之一
in turning source code that you and I write into those 0's and 1's.
将你我编写的源代码转换为0和1。
But through an understanding of these four steps
但通过理解这四个步骤
today, you'll hopefully better understand
今天，你将有望更好地理解
how to troubleshoot issues like that and just know
如何解决此类问题，并了解
what's happening because it's not, in fact, magic.
发生了什么，因为它实际上不是魔法。
It's just the result of years of humans developing these four steps here.
它只是人类多年来开发这四个步骤的结果。
So when you run make, what's happening?
所以，当你运行 make 时，发生了什么？
Or in turn, when you run clang, four different things are happening.
或者，当你运行 clang 时，会发生四种不同的情况。
And the first one is called pre-processing.
第一个被称为预处理。
So what is this all about?
这到底是怎么回事呢？
Well, let's consider this code here.
那么，让我们看一下这里的代码。
And this code is a little bit interesting
这段代码有点意思
insofar as it's one of the more complicated examples from last week.
因为它是在上周比较复杂的例子之一。
And you'll notice, for instance, that I had include stdio at the top
你会注意到，例如，我在顶部添加了 include stdio
so I could use printf.
以便可以使用 printf。
I had main down here, whose purpose in life was just to meow three times.
我在这里写了 main，它的作用就是喵叫三声。
And then recall we made our own meow function just like we did in week 0
然后回想一下，我们就像在第 0 周使用 Scratch 一样，创建了自己的 meow 函数
with Scratch that just printed out, quote-unquote, "meow."
它只是打印出“喵”这个词。
But I also included this line here, which we called what?
但我还在此处添加了这一行，我们称它为什么？
This was a prototype.
这是一个原型。
And why did I have to include it there?
为什么我必须在那里添加它？
Or equivalently, what would happen if I didn't include a prototype up
或者等同地，如果我不在上面添加原型，会发生什么？
at the top there?
在顶部？
Yeah?
对吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
If I didn't include it up here, the program, when trying to compile main,
如果我不在这里添加它，程序在尝试编译 main 时，
would not know what meow is because it's not defined until later.
将不知道 meow 是什么，因为它直到后面才会被定义。
So this is kind of like a little hint of what is to come.
所以，这有点像对未来即将发生的事情的暗示。
Alternatively, we could just move this whole thing up at the top of the file,
或者，我们可以直接将整个内容移到文件的顶部，
but I claim that just devolves into a big mess
但我认为这最终会导致混乱
eventually once you have many different functions.
最终，当你有很多不同的函数时。
Like you can't realistically put them all at the top to solve this problem.
就像你不能现实地把它们都放在顶部来解决这个问题。
So these prototypes solve that problem.
所以这些原型解决了这个问题。
So nothing new here.
所以这里没有新东西。
Just a reminder of what motivated this one line of prototype.
只是一个提醒，是什么促使了这行原型代码的出现。
Now let's consider this simpler program, which
现在让我们考虑这个更简单的程序，它
is just the one we wrote most recently in VS Code.
只是我们最近在 VS Code 中编写的那个程序。
This program prompts the human for their name
这个程序提示用户输入他们的姓名
and then says hello to that person.
然后跟那个人打招呼。
But it has two includes at the top of the file.
但它在文件顶部有两个包含语句。
And in fact, any line of C that starts with this hash symbol
事实上，任何以这个井号开头的 C 代码行
is what we'll call now a preprocessor directive.
我们现在称之为预处理指令。
It's not really a word you need to remember in your vocabulary,
这不是一个你需要记住的词汇，
but it is a little bit different from most every other line
但它与大多数其他代码行略有不同，
because it starts with that hash.
因为它以井号开头。
That's a special symbol in C.
这是 C 语言中的一个特殊符号。
And what this means is the following.
它的意思如下。
This very first line, cs50.h, is indeed a file that I and CS50 staff
这第一行，cs50.h，实际上是一个文件，我和 CS50 员工
wrote and we installed somewhere in VS Code for you, somewhere in the cloud.
编写了并在 VS Code 中的某个地方为你安装了，在云端的某个地方。
And I've claimed you need to use this header file in order to use get_string.
我声称你需要使用这个头文件才能使用 get_string 函数。
So just logically, what is probably inside of cs50.h?
所以从逻辑上讲，cs50.h 里面可能是什么？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: Function [INAUDIBLE].
观众：函数 [听不清]。
DAVID MALAN: Super close.
大卫·马兰：非常接近。
So the function called get_string that does the getting of a string,
所以名为 get_string 的函数负责获取字符串，
but it's not quite as much as the function itself.
但它并不完全是函数本身。
It's actually a little bit less than that, but you're on the right track.
它实际上比这少一点，但你走在正确的轨道上。
What is inside of cs50.h, presumably?
cs50.h 里面可能是什么？
Just a what?
只是一个什么？
Just a prototype for?
只是一个原型？
Which function?
哪个函数？
get_string.
get_string 函数。
So admittedly, there's some other stuff in there, too,
所以说，里面还有一些其他的东西，
but the important line for today's discussion is that inside of cs50.h
但今天讨论中重要的是，在 cs50.h 里面
is indeed one line of code that defines what the return value, what
确实有一行代码定义了返回值，
the name is, and what the arguments, if any, are to get_string,
名称是什么，以及 get_string 函数的参数是什么，如果有的话，
and some other stuff.
以及一些其他的东西。
And so what happens effectively when you compile your code,
所以当你在编译你的代码时，实际上发生了什么，
step 1 is this pre-processing line.
第一步是这一行预处理代码。
And essentially, there is some code that someone else wrote inside
本质上，有一些代码是由其他人编写的，它们位于
of the clang compiler that looks for a line that starts with hash include,
clang 编译器中，它们会查找以井号 include 开头的代码行，
and when it sees that, it goes and finds this file and effectively copies
当它看到这个时，它会去找到这个文件，并有效地复制
and pastes the contents of that file right there into your code
并将该文件的内容粘贴到你的代码中，
so that you don't have to go find the file,
这样你就不用去找到这个文件，
copy and paste it, and make a mess of your own code.
复制粘贴它，并把你的代码弄乱。
So in particular, it's effectively as though you're copying and pasting
因此，实际上就像你在复制粘贴
the prototype of get_string to the very top of your file,
get_string 函数的原型到你的文件顶部，
thereby teaching the compiler that it exists.
从而告诉编译器它存在。
By that same logic, what is probably in stdio.h?
按照同样的逻辑，stdio.h 里面可能是什么？
The prototype for?
用于什么？
For printf.
用于printf。
And indeed, exactly that.
没错，正是它。
So this line effectively gets replaced with the equivalent
因此，这行代码实际上被替换成了等效的
of the prototype for printf, which, for today's purposes,
printf的原型，为了今天的目的，
is a bit more complicated, so let me wave my hand at the dot-dot-dot
它有点复杂，所以让我用省略号来表示它
just because it takes a variable number of arguments
因为它接受可变数量的参数
depending on how many placeholders or format codes you have.
取决于你有多少个占位符或格式代码。
But effectively, that, too, is what's happening.
但实际上，这也是正在发生的事情。
So the preprocessor step, step 1 of 4, just
所以预处理步骤，4 个步骤中的第一个，只是
does that find and replace, if you will.
进行查找和替换，如果你愿意的话。
Now there's some-- again, some other stuff in that file,
现在文件里还有一些其他的东西，
and this, too, is kind of a white lie. printf
这又是一个善意的谎言。printf
probably has its own file because that's a really big library,
可能拥有它自己的文件，因为这是一个非常大的库，
but the essence of it is exactly this.
但其本质就是这个。
So preprocessing converts all of those hash
所以预处理会将所有这些哈希
include lines to whatever the underlying prototypes are
include 行转换为底层原型
within the file plus some other stuff.
在文件内部加上一些其他的东西。
Now compiling we use it as this catch-all phrase, but it turns out,
现在，我们用它作为这个万能词语，但事实证明，
it has a very specific meaning that's worth
它有一个非常具体的含义，值得
knowing about even though after today, you
了解，即使在今天之后，你
can go back to using compiling as the sort of catch-all phrase.
可以回到使用编译作为万能词语。
So when you've got this same code here after the pre-processing step
所以，当你预处理步骤之后有了这段代码时，
has happened.
已经完成。
So this is essentially happening in the computer's memory.
所以，这实质上发生在计算机的内存中。
It's not changing your hello.c file permanently or anything like that.
它不会永久改变你的 hello.c 文件，或者类似的操作。
This code gets, quote-unquote, "compiled" into something
这段代码被“编译”成了
that looks more like this.
看起来像这样。
And this is a scarier language that we won't spend time
这是一种更可怕的语言，我们不会在这门课上花时间
on in this particular class.
来学习它。
This is what's known as assembly language.
这就是所谓的汇编语言。
And back in the day, before there was C, humans
在 C 出现之前，人类
wrote this to program their computers.
用它来编写程序。
Similarly, before there was assembly code back in the day,
同样地，在汇编语言出现之前，
humans very initially used what instead?
人类最开始使用什么来代替它？
AUDIENCE: 0's and 1's.
观众：0 和 1。
DAVID MALAN: So 0's and 1's-- like they actually wrote the machine code
戴维·马兰：所以 0 和 1 -- 他们实际上写了机器码
painfully, be it in code or be it in punch cards like physical objects
非常痛苦，无论是代码还是像打孔卡这样的物理对象
or the like.
或者类似的东西。
So again, these are sort of abstractions,
所以，这些都是抽象的概念，
but we're rewinding for today in time.
但我们今天要回顾一下。
But what this compiler for C is doing is converting C
但 C 语言的编译器所做的是将 C 语言
into this other language called assembly language.
转换为另一种叫做汇编语言的语言。
And even though this looks very esoteric,
虽然这看起来很深奥，
there's at least some juicy things in here.
这里至少有一些有趣的东西。
If I highlight get_string, it's mentioned in this code.
如果我高亮显示 get_string，它在这段代码中被提及。
printf is mentioned in this code.
printf 在这段代码中被提及。
And even some of these keywords here that
甚至这里的一些关键字
are spelled a bit weirdly, this relates to subtracting and moving
拼写有点奇怪，这与减法和移动有关。
something in memory and calling a function, calling a function.
内存中的一些东西以及调用函数，调用函数。
So there's some semantics that are probably
因此，有一些语义可能
somewhat familiar even though this is not code we ourselves will write.
多少有些熟悉，即使这不是我们自己会写的代码。
But unfortunately, this is not yet machine code,
但不幸的是，这还不是机器码，
and that's where step 3 comes in.
这就是第 3 步发挥作用的地方。
So step 3 of this four-step process is technically called assembling.
因此，这四个步骤中的第 3 步在技术上被称为汇编。
And assembling just takes that assembly code and converts it, thankfully,
而汇编只是将汇编代码转换，谢天谢地，
to the thing we do care about, the 0's and 1's.
转换成了我们关心的东西，0 和 1。
So assembling takes assembly code converts it to 0's and 1's.
因此，汇编将汇编代码转换为 0 和 1。
As an aside, and I alluded to this earlier,
顺便说一下，我之前提到了这一点，
the reason that Clang names its files a.out by default, assembler output,
Clang 默认将它的文件命名为 a.out 的原因是，汇编器输出，
is a side effect of that being one of the steps in this process,
这是该过程中的一个步骤的副作用，
dealing with assembly language and its subsequent output.
处理汇编语言及其后续输出。
All right, so here are some 0's and 1's, but unfortunately, there's
好的，所以这里有一些 0 和 1，但不幸的是，还有
still that fourth and final step, which is a word that I also used earlier,
第四步也是最后一步，这也是我之前用过的词，
namely linking.
就是链接。
So let me take a step back and look at this code here.
所以让我退一步看看这里面的代码。
And even though this code is exactly as I wrote in VS Code in hello.c--
即使这段代码与我在 VS Code 中 hello.c 中写的完全一样——
so no copying and pasting, no prototypes have
所以没有复制粘贴，也没有原型
been plugged in here, this is my code, technically, there's
被插入到这里，这是我的代码，从技术上讲，这里有
three different files involved in compiling even something relatively
三个不同的文件参与编译，即使是像这样相对
simple like this.
简单的东西。
There's obviously this thing itself, hello.c, which I wrote.
很明显，这里有它自己，hello.c，是我写的。
There's apparently cs50.h, and there's apparently stdio.h.
很明显有 cs50.h，还有 stdio.h。
But technically-- and you don't have to know this file name, per se, somewhere
但从技术上讲——你不需要知道这个文件名，本身来说，在某个地方
else on the computer's hard drive, so to speak,
在计算机的硬盘驱动器上，可以这么说，
is a cs50.c file, which actually contains
有一个 cs50.c 文件，它实际上包含
the staff's implementation of get_string and get_int and get_float
工作人员对 get_string、get_int 和 get_float 的实现
and all of those other functions.
以及所有其他函数。
Somewhere on the server's hard drive is stdio.c
服务器硬盘驱动器上的某个地方是 stdio.c
that implements printf and all of these other functions as well.
它实现了 printf 以及所有其他函数。
So the dot c is just inferred from the dot h here.
所以这里的 .c 是从 .h 推断出来的。
You don't ever mention the dot c file, but someone else wrote those files,
你从未提到过 .c 文件，但其他人编写了这些文件，
someone else stored them in the server for you--
其他人将它们存储在服务器上供你使用——
CS50 staff in this case.
在本例中是 CS50 工作人员。
So technically, even when compiling a relatively short program like this,
因此，从技术上讲，即使编译像这样相对较短的程序，
you're really combining three files at least at the end of the day.
你最终实际上至少将三个文件组合在一起。
And I'll write them from left to right. hello.c,
我会从左到右写它们。hello.c，
which I wrote, cs50.c, which the staff wrote, and then stdio.c as well.
是我写的，cs50.c 是工作人员写的，还有 stdio.c。
So somewhere there's these three files.
所以某个地方有这三个文件。
And Clang, our compiler, needs to compile each of these
而 Clang，我们的编译器，需要将这些文件中的每一个
into the corresponding 0's and 1's.
编译成相应的 0 和 1。
Lastly, this is not yet sufficient because these 0's and 1's haven't
最后，这还不够，因为这些 0 和 1 还没有
been linked together.
链接在一起。
I mean, I deliberately left a gap here to imply that these
我的意思是，我故意在这里留出空隙来暗示这些
are three separately-compiled files.
是三个单独编译的文件。
So that fourth and final step called linking
所以第四个也是最后一个步骤叫做链接
takes all of these 0's and 1's and an intelligent way
将所有这些 0 和 1 以一种智能的方式
combines them into just one final file named hello, named a.out,
组合成一个最终文件，名为 hello，名为 a.out，
whatever the file name is of choice.
无论你选择的文件名是什么。
So what you and I for the past week have just been calling compiling--
所以过去一周我们一直所说的编译——
and that's what a normal person will use henceforth
这就是普通人以后会用的
to describe this whole process, technically, there's
来描述整个过程，从技术上来说，这里
these four different steps underneath the hood, each of which
有四个不同的步骤，每一个步骤
is sort of a representative of an evolution of technology over the years.
在某种程度上代表了多年来技术的演变。
And nowadays, if we fast forward a few weeks
现在，如果我们快进几周
in class, when we start talking about Python, which
在课堂上，当我们开始讨论 Python 时，它
is another more modern language, that, too, is going to be conceptually even
是另一种更现代的语言，它在概念上也
higher level, even though underneath the hood,
更高级，即使在幕后，
there's going to be some lower-level principles at work.
也有一些底层原理在起作用。
So any questions on just terminology or these processes known as compiling?
所以关于术语或这些被称为编译的过程，有什么问题吗？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: I didn't really understand what compiling means.
观众：我不太明白编译是什么意思。
[INAUDIBLE]
[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
大卫·马兰：当然。
Compiling, if I rewind, is the process of taking your source code, which
如果我倒回去，编译就是将你的源代码，它
looks like this, recall-- whoops, this, and converting it into assembly code.
看起来像这样，回忆一下——哎哟，这个，然后把它转换成汇编代码。
So preprocessing just converts all of those hash
所以预处理只是将所有这些哈希
include lines and a few others to their equivalents.
include 行和一些其他的行转换为它们的等价物。
So that's step 1.
所以这是第一步。
Compiling converts the C code into the underlying assembly code.
编译将 C 代码转换为底层的汇编代码。
The assembling step, step 3, converts the assembly code to 0's and 1's.
汇编步骤，第三步，将汇编代码转换为 0 和 1。
And then the fourth step, linking, combines
然后第四步，链接，组合
all of the 0's and 1's from the one, the two, the three or more files
所有来自一个、两个、三个或更多文件的 0 和 1
that are involved in your project and links them
参与你项目的这些文件，并将它们链接
all together for you magically.
全部链接在一起，就像变魔术一样。
But at the end of the day, all of this is happening automatically for you.
但最终，所有这一切都是自动为你完成的。
If I jump now to the end here, whereby just by running
如果我现在跳到最后，只需要运行
make, which, in turn, runs clang for you, like all of this
make，它反过来又为你运行 clang，就像所有这一切
is abstracted away.
被抽象化了。
But the key here is that even with these commands that we've been running,
但这里的关键是，即使使用我们一直在运行的这些命令，
be it the make command or the clang command,
无论是 make 命令还是 clang 命令，
everything should be explainable what you are typing at the prompt
你最终在提示符下输入的任何内容都应该能够解释清楚
ultimately.
最终。
Each of those things has a purpose.
每一个都有其目的。
So any questions, then, on what we've just
那么，关于我们刚刚
now called compiling even though it's only when you take another CS
现在称之为编译，即使只有当你学习另一门计算机科学课程时
course that you might spend more time on assembly
你才会花更多时间在汇编
language or these lower-level details?
语言或这些底层细节上？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
大卫·马兰：一个好问题。
Are there other types of compilers?
还有其他类型的编译器吗？
Yes.
是的。
Back when I took CS50, I used a popular compiler called GCC, the GNU Compiler
当我学习 CS50 的时候，我使用了一个流行的编译器，叫做 GCC，GNU 编译器
Collection, which still exists actually in the code space
集合，实际上它仍然存在于代码空间
that you're using for CS50.
你用来学习 CS50 的。
Clang is somewhat more recent.
Clang 相对来说比较新。
It's gaining popularity.
它越来越流行。
And frankly, we use it in large part because it's error messages
坦白说，我们使用它很大程度上是因为它的错误消息
are slightly more user-friendly.
更加人性化。
You might not believe us because if you encountered some errors with your code
你可能不信我们，因为如果你在你的代码中遇到了一些错误
this past week, they were probably just as arcane as the error messages I saw,
在上周，他们可能就像我看到的错误消息一样难以理解，
but it's better than it was some years ago.
但它比几年前好多了。
And there's alternatives to compiling, too,
而且也有编译的替代方案，
but more on that when we get to Python as well.
但当我们谈到 Python 的时候，我们会详细讨论它。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
Well, what are the implications of the fact that we're going from source code
那么，从源代码到机器代码，这意味着什么呢？
to machine code?
到机器代码？
Well, it stands to reason that if you can compile code,
很明显，如果你可以编译代码，
maybe you can decompile it-- that is, go in the reverse direction.
也许你可以反编译它——也就是说，反过来操作。
Go from 0's and 1's to actual source code.
从 0 和 1 到实际的源代码。
Now that would be handy if you want to go in as a programmer and change
现在，如果你想作为程序员去修改
something in a program that you or someone else already wrote.
你或其他人已经编写的程序中的某些内容。
It's maybe not ideal for your intellectual property,
这可能对你的知识产权不利，
though, if you are the person who wrote that program in the first place.
不过，如果你本来就是编写该程序的人。
If you are Microsoft and you wrote Microsoft Word or Excel
如果你就是微软，而且你编写了 Microsoft Word 或 Excel
that people with Macs and PCs and phones have installed on their devices,
这些软件被 Mac、PC 和手机用户安装在他们的设备上，
it doesn't actually sound very appealing if any old customer
如果任何一个老客户
can take those 0's and 1's and reverse them, reverse engineer them,
可以将这些 0 和 1 反转，逆向工程它们，
so to speak, into the original source code
可以说，将它们转化为原始的源代码
because then they can have their own version of Microsoft Word
因为这样他们就可以拥有他们自己的 Microsoft Word 版本
and make changes to it without really having put in all of the R&D
并对其进行修改，而无需投入所有研发
that it might have taken to build the first version thereof.
可能需要构建它的第一个版本。
But it turns out that reverse engineering--
但事实证明，反向工程——
so doing things in the opposite direction-- is easier
做相反的事情——说起来容易
said than done because there are multiple ways, as you've seen already,
做起来难，因为正如你已经看到的，
to implement programs.
有很多方法可以实现程序。
Like loops alone, you can use for loops, while loops, even do-while loops.
比如循环本身，你可以使用 for 循环、while 循环，甚至 do-while 循环。
And so there's other ways-- there's multiple ways
因此，还有其他方法——有几种方法
to solve the same problem.
可以解决相同的问题。
So even if you try to reverse engineer a program
因此，即使你尝试反向工程一个程序
and convert machine code back to source code,
并将机器代码转换回源代码，
there's not necessarily going to be an obvious way to do so.
也不一定有一个明显的方法可以做到这一点。
And the reality is, that it ends up being such a mess
现实情况是，最终会变得一团糟
because you lose the variable names typically,
因为你通常会丢失变量名，
you lose the function names typically, that what you end up looking at
你通常会丢失函数名，最终你看到的是
might very well be C code, but it's completely difficult for you,
可能确实是 C 代码，但这对你来说非常困难，
even a good programmer, to read.
即使是一个优秀的程序员，也能读懂。
And generally, the mindset is, if you're really good enough
一般来说，人们的想法是，如果你真的足够优秀
to decompile code in that way and read it subsequently
以这种方式反编译代码并随后阅读它
even without good variable names, good function
即使没有好的变量名、好的函数名
names, good documentation and the like, could probably have just implemented
好的文档等等，你可能可以自己直接实现
the program in the first place yourself without jumping through those hoops.
这个程序，而不需要经过这些繁琐的步骤。
So there's some practicality pushing back
所以有一些实用性在回推
on what are otherwise potential threats to, say, your intellectual property.
在其他情况下，可能会对你的知识产权构成威胁。
But that's not going to be the case later on in the term when
但在学期后期，情况就不一样了
we do get to languages like Python to some extent, other languages
我们确实会接触到像 Python 这样的语言，在某种程度上，其他语言
like JavaScript.
像 JavaScript。
Some of those are actually going to be readable by anyone.
其中一些实际上任何人都可以阅读。
Any of your customers, any of your friends,
你的任何客户、任何朋友
and your family that actually use your programs.
以及你家里的那些实际使用你程序的人。
So with that said, let's introduce now another tool to our toolkit
因此，现在让我们向我们的工具箱中添加另一个工具
that will hopefully make some of the pain
希望这能够减轻一些痛苦
from this past week when you did encounter
在上周你遇到问题的时候
bugs a little more manageable.
使调试 bug 变得更加容易。
And indeed, part of the process of writing code to this day
事实上，如今编写代码的一部分过程
is debugging it.
就是调试它。
And it is a rare thing to write a program,
写一个程序，这是一件很罕见的事情
be it in C or any other language, and get it 100% right the first time.
无论是在 C 语言还是其他任何语言中，都能在第一次就做到 100% 正确。
I mean, to this day, I still, 20-plus years later, still write buggy code.
我的意思是，直到今天，我已经 20 多年了，仍然会写出有 bug 的代码。
Hopefully a little bit less of it, but any time you're adding a new feature,
希望现在会少一些，但无论何时你添加一个新功能，
any time you're doing something for the first time,
无论何时你第一次做某事，
you're not necessarily going to see all of the possible mistakes.
你不会一定能看到所有可能出现的错误。
So even in industry, bugs are omnipresent, which is really to say,
因此，即使在工业界，bug 也是无处不在的，这意味着
having techniques to debug code-- that is, eliminate bugs,
拥有调试代码的技术——也就是说，消除 bug，
is super compelling.
非常有说服力。
Now just for a bit of history, here is Admiral Grace Hopper,
现在我们来谈谈历史，这是海军上将 Grace Hopper，
who was actually in not only the military,
她不仅在军队服役，
but also on the faculty of Harvard years ago
而且多年前也在哈佛大学任教
and worked on a Harvard computer called the Harvard Mark
并且参与了哈佛大学的一台名为哈佛 Mark 的计算机
I, which is actually on display at the School of Engineering and Applied
I，这台计算机现在实际展出在工程与应用科学学院
Sciences if you take a tour over there sometime.
如果有一天你去参观那里的话。
But also when working on the Harvard Mark II,
在参与哈佛 Mark II 项目时
she is known for having at least popularized the phrase "bug" to mean
她以至少普及了“bug”这个词来表示
a mistake in a computer's program--
计算机程序中的错误——
a mistake in a computer's code.
计算机代码中的错误。
And the etymology of this supposedly is this here logbook
据推测，这个词的词源来自于这本航海日志
wherein she and her colleagues were documenting processes being computed
她在日志中和她的同事记录了计算机上正在执行的进程
on computers, that a moth actually got stuck
在计算机上，一只飞蛾卡住了
in one of the relays, one of the mechanical-- the electric relays inside
卡在了其中一个继电器中，一个机械继电器——这台非常古老的计算机里面的电继电器，然后有人非常聪明地
of the very old now computer, and someone very cleverly
写下了，“第一个被发现的 bug 的实际案例”。
wrote, "First actual case of bug being found."
所以并不是她真正发现了这个 bug，
So it wasn't she who actually discovered it,
而是她的同事们记录了这件事，然后这件事就被流传下来了。
but this was a story she was thereafter fond of telling as a famed computer
但是，这是一个她后来作为著名的计算机科学家喜欢讲述的故事。
scientist thereafter.
科学家。
We now know bugs to be all too familiar when it comes to writing our own code,
我们现在知道，在编写自己的代码时，bug 太常见了，
and I thought I would deliberately write some buggy code based
我认为我会故意编写一些有bug的代码，这些代码基于
on some of the programs with which we experimented last week.
我们上周做实验的一些程序。
So let me go back over to VS Code here and let
所以，让我回到这里的 VS Code，并让我
me propose that I do something somewhat simplistic just like this to print out
我建议我做一些像这样简单的事情来打印
a column of bricks of height 3.
一列高为 3 的砖块。
So I'm going into VS Code and I'm going to deliberately call this program
所以，我将进入 VS Code，并且我将故意将这个程序称为
buggy.c because I intend to do this poorly.
buggy.c，因为我打算把它做得不好。
I'm going to include stdio.h as before, int main void as before.
我将像以前一样包含 stdio.h，像以前一样包含 int main void。
And in here, if I want to print a pyramid of height 3,
在里面，如果我想打印一个高为 3 的金字塔，
I'm going to do 4 int i gets--
我要做 4 个 int i 获取--
all right, I'm still new to programming in my mind
好吧，我仍然不熟悉我的编程思维
here, so I know I'm supposed to start counting at 0, OK.
在这里，所以我知道我应该从 0 开始计数，好的。
And I want to do this until I count up to 3, so I'm going to do that.
而且，我想一直这样做，直到我数到 3，所以我要这样做。
And then i++ I remember from class in this way.
然后，我记得从课堂上以这种方式学到 i++。
And now I might go ahead and print out just a hash mark, backslash n,
现在，我可能会继续打印一个井号，反斜杠 n，
which I do want because I want to move this cursor to the next line
这是我想要的，因为我想将光标移动到下一行
to make this vertical.
使其垂直。
But of course, if you've noticed with your eye already, when I do make buggy,
但是，当然，如果你已经注意到，当我做 buggy 时，
it compiles OK.
它编译良好。
So no typos, no syntactical errors.
所以，没有错别字，没有语法错误。
But when I run this, I'm going to see how many bricks.
但是，当我运行它时，我将看到有多少块砖。
So four in this case.
在这种情况下是四块。
Now this is meant to be a simplistic example
现在，这应该是一个简单的例子
so that we don't spend time trying to figure out what the bug is, but rather,
这样我们就不用花时间去弄清楚错误是什么，而是
focus on techniques for actually identifying the bug.
专注于识别错误的技巧。
So-- finding, rather, the bug.
所以，就是找到错误。
So what's one of the first tools in your toolkit?
那么，你工具箱里的第一个工具是什么？
Literally one you have already. printf is your friend.
你已经有了它。printf 是你的朋友。
And it is a very quick and dirty tool for just seeing
它是一个非常快速简便的工具，可以用来查看
what's going on inside of the computer when
当你在计算机内部发生什么时，
you don't have more sophisticated tools or even the time to use them.
你没有更复杂的工具，甚至没有时间使用它们。
And so in this case, for instance, what I'd propose is that--
所以，在这种情况下，例如，我建议--
all right, I'm obviously seeing four hashes.
好吧，我显然看到四个井号。
And let me play a little slow here.
让我在这里放慢一点。
It'd be helpful for me to understand why logically I'm ending up with four, even
对我来说，了解为什么从逻辑上来说我最终得到四个，即使
though I'm starting at 0 like I remember from class and I'm going up to 3
尽管我记得从课堂上开始从 0 开始，我正在数到 3
as we did in class, like I'm just not seeing it in this particular story.
就像我们在课堂上做的那样，我只是没有在这个特定的故事中看到它。
So what I would commonly do is go into my code and just help me see
所以我通常会进入我的代码，帮助我查看
what's going on, and I might literally write a printf line like, i is %i,
发生了什么，我可能会直接写一行 printf，比如，i 是 %i，
backslash n, comma, and then just print out the value of i.
反斜杠 n，逗号，然后只打印出 i 的值。
I just want to see on every iteration, what
我只是想在每次迭代时查看，什么是
is i, what is i, what is i just to help me see what the computer already knows.
i 是什么，i 是什么，i 是什么，只是为了帮助我查看计算机已经知道的。
So let me go ahead and recompile buggy, let me rerun buggy,
所以让我继续重新编译 buggy，让我重新运行 buggy，
and then let me make my terminal window bigger
然后让我把我的终端窗口放大
just to make clear what's going on.
只是为了让事情更清楚。
And now it's a little more pedantic.
现在它有点儿更刻板了。
Now i is 0, I get a hash. i is 1, I get a hash. i is 2, I get a hash.
现在 i 是 0，我得到一个井号。i 是 1，我得到一个井号。i 是 2，我得到一个井号。
Wait a minute. i is 3, I get a hash.
等一下。i 是 3，我得到一个井号。
So clearly now, it should be maybe more obvious to you,
所以很明显，现在对你来说应该更明显了，
especially if the syntax itself is unfamiliar,
特别是如果语法本身不熟悉，
I certainly don't want this last one printing,
我当然不希望最后一个打印，
or maybe equivalently, I don't want the first one printing.
或者等效地，我不希望第一个打印。
So I can fix this in a couple of ways, but the solution,
所以我可以通过几种方法来解决这个问题，但解决方案，
the most canonical solution is probably to do what with my code?
最规范的解决方案可能是用我的代码做什么？
To change to what to what?
改为什么？
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰： 是的。
So change the less than or equal sign to just a less than sign.
所以把小于等于号改为小于号。
So even though this is like counting from 0 to 3 instead of 1 through 3,
所以即使这是从 0 到 3 计数而不是从 1 到 3，
it's the more typical programmatic way to write code like this.
这是编写这种代码更典型的编程方式。
And now, of course, if I do make buggy--
现在，当然，如果我做 buggy--
and I'll increase my terminal window again, ./buggy,
我会再次放大我的终端窗口，./buggy，
now I see what's going on inside of the code.
现在我看到了代码内部发生的事情。
Now it matches my expectations, and so now the bug is gone.
现在它符合我的预期，所以现在 bug 消失了。
Now of course, if I'm submitting this or shipping it,
现在当然，如果我要提交或发布它，
I should delete the temporary printf.
我应该删除临时 printf。
And let me disclaim that using printf in this way just to help you
我声明以这种方式使用 printf 只是为了帮助你
see what's going on is generally a good thing,
了解正在发生的事情通常是一件好事，
but generally adding a printf and a printf and a printf and a printf--
但通常添加一个 printf、一个 printf、一个 printf 和一个 printf--
like it starts to devolve into just trial and error and you
就像它开始退化为纯粹的试错，而你
have no idea what's going on, so you're just printing out everything.
不知道发生了什么，所以你只是打印出所有内容。
Let me propose that if you ever find yourself slipping down
我建议如果你发现自己滑下了
that hill into just trying this, trying this, trying this,
那座山，仅仅尝试这个，尝试那个，尝试另一个，
you need a better tool, not just doing printf.
你需要一个更好的工具，而不仅仅是使用 printf。
And frankly, it's annoying to use printf because every time you add a printf,
坦白地说，使用 printf 很烦人，因为每次你添加一个 printf，
you have to recompile the code, rerun the code.
你必须重新编译代码，重新运行代码。
It's just adding to the number of steps.
这只是增加了步骤数量。
So let me propose instead that we do this.
所以让我建议我们这样做。
I'm going to go back into VS Code here and I'm
我将回到这里的 VS Code 中，并且我
going to write a different program that actually
将要编写一个不同的程序，实际上
has a helper function, so to speak.
有一个辅助函数，可以这么说。
A second function whose purpose in life is maybe just
第二个函数，它的生命目标可能是仅仅
to print that column for me.
为我打印那列。
So I'm going to say this-- void print_column,
所以我会说这个——void print_column，
though I could call it anything I want, and this function
虽然我可以随意命名，但这个函数
is going to take a argument or a parameter called
将要接受一个参数，叫做
height which will tell it how many bricks to print,
height，它将告诉函数要打印多少块砖，
how many vertical bricks.
多少块竖着的砖。
I'm going to do the same kind of logic. for int i equals 0.
我要做同样的逻辑。for int i 等于 0。
i is less than--
i 小于 --
I'm going to make the same mistake again-- less than or equal to height,
我会再次犯同样的错误 -- 小于或等于高度，
i++.
i++。
And then inside of this for loop, let me go ahead and print out the hash mark.
然后在这个 for 循环中，我先打印出井号。
So I've made the same mistake, but I've made it
所以，我犯了同样的错误，但我把它
in the context now of a helper function only because in main,
现在放在了一个辅助函数的上下文中，因为在主函数中，
what I'd like to do now, just to be a little more sophisticated is get int
我现在想做的是，为了更精细一点，从用户那里获取整数
from the user for the height.
作为高度。
And when I do get that int, I want to store it in a variable called n,
当我获取到这个整数时，我想把它存储在一个叫做 n 的变量中，
but I do need to give that variable a type like last week.
但是我需要给这个变量一个类型，就像上周一样。
So I'll say that it's an integer.
所以，我会说它是一个整数。
And now, lastly, I can print_column, passing in-- actually, I'll
现在，最后，我可以调用 print_column，传入 -- 实际上，我会
call it h just because height is h.
把它叫做 h，因为高度是 h。
Print column h, semicolon.
打印列 h，分号。
OK, so it's the exact same program except I'm getting user input now.
好的，所以它和之前的程序完全一样，只是我现在在获取用户输入。
So it's not just going to be 3, it's going to be a variable height,
所以它不再是固定的 3，而是会根据高度变量变化，
but I've done something stupid.
但是，我做了一些蠢事。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不见]
DAVID MALAN: I've done two stupid things.
戴维·马兰：我犯了两个蠢错误。
So this, of course, is not supposed to be there, so I'll fix that.
当然，这个是不应该出现在这里的，所以我会把它修复。
And someone else.
还有其他人。
What else have I done?
我还做了什么？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不见]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
戴维·马兰：是的。
I'm missing the prototype.
我漏掉了原型。
And this is, let me reiterate, probably the only time where copy-paste is OK.
并且，让我再次强调，这可能是唯一可以进行复制粘贴的情况。
Once you've implemented the function, you
一旦你实现了函数，你
can copy paste its first line at a semicolon
就可以复制粘贴它的第一行，并加上一个分号
so that it teaches the compiler that this function will exist.
这样编译器就知道这个函数存在了。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不见]
DAVID MALAN: Three stupid things.
戴维·马兰：三个蠢错误。
OK.
好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So, good.
所以，很好。
Include cs50.h.
包含 cs50.h。
And now, anyone want to go for four?
现在，有人想尝试第四个错误吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
Slightly unintended here.
这里有点意外。
So let's see. make buggy.
让我们看看。执行 make buggy。
OK, no syntax errors thanks to you all.
好的，多亏了你们，没有语法错误。
So the code compiles, but of course, when I run buggy
所以代码编译通过了，但当然，当我运行 buggy
and I type in something like 3 manually, I'm still going to get 1, 2, 3 4 out.
并且我手动输入了 3，我还是会得到 1, 2, 3, 4 的输出。
So let me now introduce a more powerful tool
现在，我将介绍一个更强大的工具
that's generally known as a debugger.
它通常被称为调试器。
And within the VS Code environment that you're using,
在你们使用的 VS Code 环境中，
we actually have a command that makes it a little easier to use this tool,
我们实际上有一个命令可以让使用这个工具变得更简单，
but we didn't write the tool itself.
但我们没有编写这个工具本身。
You are about to see a very graphical, a very popular industry standard
你们即将看到一个非常图形化的、非常流行的行业标准
tool called a debugger, but we'll start the debugger using a CS50-specific
工具，叫做调试器，但我们会使用 CS50 特定的命令来启动它
command called debug50, which just makes it easier with a single command
名为 debug50 的命令，只需一个命令就能简化调试过程
to start the debugger without having to configure a text
无需配置文本文件即可启动调试器
file with all of your preferred settings and all of that.
文件包含所有你喜欢的设置等等。
It's just an annoying hoop otherwise to jump through.
否则，这只是一个令人讨厌的障碍。
So what I'm going to do is go back to my code here.
所以我要回到我的代码这里。
I have already compiled it, but just for good measure,
我已经编译了它，但为了保险起见，
I'll make buggy again because the debugger needs your code
我将再次使它出现错误，因为调试器需要你的代码
to be compiled.
被编译。
It's not going to help with syntax errors
它不会帮助解决语法错误
like the stupid mistakes I just made unintentionally,
比如我刚才无意中犯的愚蠢错误，
it will help you though with programmatic errors, logical errors
它将帮助你解决程序错误，逻辑错误
in your code once your code is running.
在你的代码运行后。
So to run debug50, I'm going to do this. debug50, space, and then
所以要运行 debug50，我会这样做。 debug50，空格，然后
the exact same command I would normally run to just run the program itself.
与我通常运行程序本身的命令完全相同。
So ./buggy.
所以 ./buggy。
So exact same thing, ./buggy, but I prefix it now with debug50.
所以完全相同，./buggy，但现在我在它前面加上 debug50。
When I hit Enter, a whole bunch of--
当我按下回车键时，一大堆——
another error is going to pop up on the screen, which
另一个错误将在屏幕上弹出，这
is a good reminder because this will happen to you, too, invariably.
是一个很好的提醒，因为这也会不可避免地发生在你身上。
It's reminding me that I have to set what's called a breakpoint.
它提醒我必须设置一个所谓的断点。
And as that word suggests, it is the point
正如这个词所暗示的那样，它是代码需要中断的点
at which you want your code to break.
你想要让你的代码中断的地方。
Not break in make the situation worse sense, but rather,
不是指让情况更糟，而是指
where do you want to pause?
你想要暂停的地方？
Execution, break, execution-- like hitting the brakes on a car
执行，中断，执行——就像踩汽车的刹车
so the program doesn't run all at once.
这样程序就不会一下子全部运行。
And you can put this any number of places,
你可以在任何地方放置它，
and you might have done this accidentally
你可能无意中这样做过
if you've ever hovered over the gutter of VS Code,
如果你曾经将鼠标悬停在 VS Code 的代码区，
the left-hand side next to your line numbers.
行号旁边的左侧。
See the little red dot that appears?
看到出现的小红点了吗？
If I click on any of these lines, that's going to set a breakpoint, so to speak.
如果我点击这些行中的任何一行，就会设置一个断点，可以说是。
And I want to break execution at main.
我想要在 main 函数处中断执行。
So I'm just going to click to the left of line 6 in this case.
所以我要点击第 6 行左侧。
That makes it a darker red circle, a stop sign
它变成了一个更深的红色圆圈，一个停止标志
of sorts that tells the debugger to pause execution on that line,
告诉调试器在该行暂停执行，
though I could put it elsewhere if I so choose.
虽然我也可以选择把它放在其他地方。
Let me go ahead and rerun debug50 ./buggy, Enter,
让我重新运行 debug50 ./buggy，回车，
and now a bunch of things are going to happen on the screen.
现在屏幕上将发生很多事情。
It's going to look a little overwhelming perhaps at first glance,
它可能乍一看会让人觉得有点不知所措，
but there's some useful stuff that just happened.
但刚刚发生了一些有用的事情。
So one, my code is still here, but the line that I set the breakpoint on is--
所以，第一，我的代码还在，但我设置断点的行是——
rather, the first line of actual executable
更确切地说，是设置断点之后的第一个可执行的
code at or below the breakpoint I set is highlighted in this yellowish green
代码行，用这种黄绿色高亮显示，
here, which says, this line of code has not yet been executed.
表示这行代码尚未执行。
We broke at this point, but if I click a button, this line of code
我们在这里中断，但是如果我点击一个按钮，这行代码
will be executed.
将被执行。
Because up until now, every C program you write runs as fast as that.
因为到目前为止，你编写的每个 C 程序都以这种速度运行。
I want to pump the brakes and pause here.
我想踩刹车，在这里暂停一下。
But notice a few other aspects of the window here.
但是，请注意这里窗口的其他几个方面。
So notice that up here some weirdness.
所以请注意，这里有一些奇怪的东西。
There's mentions of variables and we're familiar with these.
这里提到了变量，我们对此很熟悉。
Local is a term we'll use this week.
“局部”是我们本周将会使用的术语。
But there's this variable h, which weirdly,
但这里有一个变量 h，奇怪的是，
where did the value 21912 come from?
值 21912 是从哪里来的？
So it turns out, in C, before you initialize a variable with a value
事实证明，在 C 语言中，在你用一个值初始化一个变量之前，
by literally typing the number 3, or by using a function like get_int,
比如直接输入数字 3，或使用 get_int 这样的函数，
it often contains what's called a garbage value.
它通常包含一个被称为“垃圾值”的东西。
More on those in a couple of weeks.
我们将在几周后详细讲解这些。
But a garbage value is you can think of it
但你可以把“垃圾值”理解为
as like remnants of whatever was in the computer's memory
计算机内存中残留的，在你运行程序之前存在的任何东西。
before you ran your program.
在你运行程序之前存在的任何东西。
And that's a bit of a oversimplification,
这有点过于简化了，
but you cannot trust that a variable will have a certain value in this case
但你不能相信一个变量在这种情况下会具有特定的值，
if you did not put one there yourself.
如果你自己没有赋予它值。
So for now, h is nonsensical.
所以现在，h 毫无意义。
It's a garbage value it means nothing.
它是一个“垃圾值”，没有任何意义。
But once I execute this line, it should contain whatever the human types in.
但一旦我执行这一行代码，它应该包含用户输入的任何内容。
All right.
好的。
Down here, there's a watch section, which is a more sophisticated feature.
这里有一个“监视”区域，这是一个更高级的功能。
Down here is what's called the call stack.
这里被称为“调用栈”。
More on that in the future.
我们将在将来详细讲解。
But what this means for now is that I'm executing the main function, not,
但现在这意味着我正在执行 main 函数，而不是，
for instance, print_column.
例如 print_column 函数。
So notice up here, these are the most useful controls within the interface.
所以请注意，这里是在界面中最有用的控件。
If I hit this Play button, it's just going
如果我点击这个“播放”按钮，它只会
to actually run my program to the end of it without bothering me further.
实际运行我的程序，直到结束，不会再打扰我。
However, I can actually step over this line of code and execute it,
然而，我实际上可以“单步跳过”这一行代码并执行它，
or I can step into this line of code and actually
或者我可以“单步进入”这一行代码，并实际上
poke around the contents of get_int if it's available on the system.
查看 get_int 函数的内容，如果它在系统上可用的话。
So conceptually you can either execute this line
从概念上讲，你可以执行这一行代码，
or you can dive down conceptually deeper and see what's inside of that function.
或者你可以从概念上更深入地潜入，看看这个函数内部的内容。
Lastly, this will let you step out, this will
最后，这个按钮可以让你“单步跳出”，它将
allow you to restart the whole process, and this will just stop the debugger.
允许你重新启动整个过程，而这个按钮只会停止调试器。
So these buttons are going to be our friends.
所以这些按钮将会是我们的好朋友。
And the one I'll click first is the first one I described,
而我将要点击的第一个按钮就是我描述的第一个按钮，
which is step over.
那就是“单步跳过”。
So step over doesn't mean, skip this step, it just means execute it,
所以“单步跳过”并不意味着跳过这一步，它只是意味着执行它，
but don't bother me by going into the weeds of what is on the specific line,
但不要因为要深入到这一行代码中的具体细节而打扰我，
namely get_int.
特别是 get_int 函数。
So when I click this button in a moment, you'll
所以，当我过一会儿点击这个按钮时，你会
see that my terminal, which is still at the bottom, prompts me for a height.
看到我的终端（还在底部）会提示我输入高度。
I'm going to go ahead and type 3.
我将输入 3。
As soon as I hit Enter, what part of the screen
我一按下回车键，屏幕的哪个部分
probably will change based on what I've said?
可能会根据我所说内容而改变？
So h, the variable h should hopefully take on the number 3.
所以，变量 h 希望可以取值为 3。
And I'll probably see a different line of code
我可能还会看到不同的代码行
highlighted, probably line 9 next once I'm done executing line 8.
高亮显示，可能在我执行完第 8 行后，接下来高亮显示的是第 9 行。
So let me go ahead and hit Enter and watch the top-left of the screen.
所以我按下回车键，然后观察屏幕的左上角。
And voila, h now has the value 3, and execution has now paused on line 9
瞧，h 现在取值为 3，执行现在暂停在第 9 行
because the debugger is allowing me to step through my code line by line.
因为调试器允许我逐行调试我的代码。
Now let me go ahead and print out-- let me go ahead and just say, all right,
现在我继续打印出来，我继续说，好吧，
I'm done with this.
我完成了。
Let's go ahead and run the rest of the program.
让我们继续运行程序的剩余部分。
It clearly got the value 3.
它显然得到了值 3。
But wait a minute--
但是等一下
oh, and at this point, it closed the window
哦，在这一点上，它关闭了窗口
in which I would have seen the output, I would have still seen four hashes.
我本来应该在那里看到输出，但我还是看到了四个井号。
So let me actually do this again.
所以让我再来做一遍。
Let me go back into debug50 by running the exact same command again.
让我再次运行相同的命令来回到 debug50。
It's going to think for a moment, it's going to reconfigure the screen.
它会思考一下，它会重新配置屏幕。
I'm going to do the exact same thing.
我要做完全相同的事情。
I'm going to step over this line, but I'd
我将跳过这一行，但我
like to actually see what's going on inside of my print_column function.
想真正看看我的 print_column 函数内部发生了什么。
So this time, instead of just saying run to the end
所以这次，而不是说直接运行到最后
and close all the windows on me, let me go ahead
然后关闭所有窗口，让我继续
and step into my print_column function.
进入我的 print_column 函数。
So don't step over, step into.
所以不要跳过，要进入。
Because if I step over--
因为如果我跳过
and now this is what I meant to show earlier,
现在，这就是我之前想展示的内容，
you can see that it's still printing out 4.
你可以看到它仍然在打印 4。
So in fact, let me undo this, let me just stop the whole thing.
事实上，让我撤销这个，让我停掉整个程序。
Let me rerun the command a final time.
让我最后一次重新运行该命令。
So it goes back to where we began before.
所以它回到了我们之前开始的地方。
It's going to prompt me again once I step over line 8 for a number like 3.
当我跳过第 8 行时，它会再次提示我输入一个像 3 这样的数字。
But this time, instead of stepping over line 9, let's poke around.
但这次，而不是跳过第 9 行，让我们四处看看。
I wrote print_column, so let's look at print_column step by step,
我写了 print_column，所以让我们一步一步地看看 print_column，
step into it, and watch what happens to the yellow highlight.
进入它，然后观察黄色高亮发生了什么。
It now jumps logically to the inside of print_column,
它现在逻辑地跳转到 print_column 的内部，
thereby letting me walk through this code.
从而让我逐步遍历这段代码。
And now I can just step over each of these lines one at a time.
现在我可以逐行跳过这些代码行。
So stepping over.
所以跳过。
OK, so what did it do?
好的，它做了什么？
It did that whole narrative that I did verbally last week
它做了上周我口头描述的整个过程
where it compared i against height.
它将 i 与 height 进行了比较。
It then went inside of the loop.
然后它进入了循环。
When I click Step Over, watch what happens in my terminal-- one hash
当我点击 Step Over 时，观察我的终端发生了什么——一个井号
prints out.
打印出来。
Now line 14 is highlighted again.
现在第 14 行再次高亮显示。
It's comparing per the Boolean expression, i,
它根据布尔表达式比较，i，
is it less than or equal to height?
它是否小于或等于 height？
If so, it's going to go ahead and print out the hash.
如果是这样，它将继续打印哈希值。
It's going to do this again, print out the hash.
它将再次这样做，打印出哈希值。
But notice at the top-left of the screen, height
但请注意屏幕左上角的高度
is still the same, it's still 3, but what has been changing, apparently?
仍然是相同的，它仍然是3，但显然是什么一直在改变？
i on each iteration.
每次迭代中的i。
So the debugger is letting me see what's going on slowly inside of this loop
所以调试器让我慢慢地看到这个循环内部发生了什么
because i keeps getting incremented.
因为i一直在增加。
So if I step over this line now, notice that I've now printed 3.
所以，如果我现在跨过这一行，请注意，我现在已经打印了3。
So ideally I want this loop to end, but if I click Step Over once more,
理想情况下，我希望这个循环结束，但是如果我再次点击“跨过”，
notice that the value of i at top-left is 3,
请注意，左上角i的值是3，
but 3 is less than or equal to height-- oh, now I get it, if I play along here.
但是3小于或等于高度——哦，我现在明白了，如果我在这里配合的话。
Now I see why less than or equals to, mathematically, is clearly incorrect.
现在我明白了为什么从数学角度来看，小于或等于显然是错误的。
And as soon as that light bulb goes off, you can just sort of
一旦灯泡亮起来，你就可以
bail out, click the red Stop button to turn the debugger off,
退出，点击红色的停止按钮来关闭调试器，
go back in, fix your code, and voila, recompile, run it,
回到里面，修复你的代码，瞧，重新编译，运行它，
and you're back in business.
你就又恢复正常了。
So the takeaways here really are just what tools now exist?
所以，这里真正的收获就是现在有哪些工具？
Printf is your friend, but only for quick-and-dirty debugging techniques.
Printf是你的朋友，但它只适用于快速且简单的调试技术。
Get into the habit now of using debug50, and in turn, VS Code's debugger.
现在养成使用debug50的习惯，进而使用VS Code的调试器。
You will invariably not take this advice, say,
你总是不会采纳这个建议，比如，
for problem set 2 as you first begin because it's
在问题集2中，当你第一次开始的时候，因为它是
going to feel easier and quicker just to use printf, just to use printf,
感觉用printf更容易、更快捷，用printf就行了，用printf就行了，
just to use printf.
用printf就行了。
And the problem with that logic is that you
而这种逻辑的问题在于，你
begin to build up like technical debt, so to speak,
开始积累技术债务，可以这么说，
where you really should have learned it earlier,
你本应该早点学习的，
you really should have learned it earlier,
you really should have learned it earlier, at which point,
你本应该早点学习的，那时，
you end up spending more time wasted using printf
你最终会浪费更多的时间使用printf
and doing things manually than if you had just spent 10 minutes,
手动操作比你花10分钟
30 minutes just learning the user interface
30分钟学习用户界面
and the buttons of a proper debugger.
和一个合适的调试器的按钮要快得多。
So please take that advice because it will save you
所以请采纳这个建议，因为它可以为你节省
significant amounts of time over time.
大量的时间。
Questions on printf or debugging in this way?
关于printf或这种调试方式有什么问题吗？
Any questions on this?
关于这个有什么问题吗？
No?
没有？
OK.
好的。
So let me give you a third and final technique for debugging, which has been
所以，让我告诉你第三种也是最后一种调试技术，它一直
looming over us here for some time.
萦绕在我们心头。
So there is actually this technique known as rubber duck debugging.
实际上，有一种叫做“橡皮鸭调试”的技术。
And in the absence of a roommate who is taking CS50 or who has taken CS50
如果没有一个正在学习CS50或者已经学过CS50的室友
or knows how to program, in the absence of having a TF or TA or CA
或者知道如何编程，如果没有一个教学助理或助教或课程助理
sitting next to you, in the absence of having a family member available to ask
坐在你旁边，如果没有一个可以问问题的家人
questions of, if you have simply an inanimate object on your desk,
问题，如果你桌上只有一个无生命的物体，
goes the tradition, just talk to that inanimate object.
传统上，就和这个无生命的物体说话。
Better yet, if it's an adorable rubber duck in this way.
更好的是，如果是一个可爱的橡皮鸭，用这种方式。
And the idea of rubber duck debugging is that simply
而橡皮鸭调试的想法是，简单地
by verbalizing literally out loud to this inanimate object--
通过文字形式大声地对这个无生命的物体说出来——
probably with the door closed and no one knowing
可能门是关着的，没有人知道
that you're talking to this rubber duck, you invariably
你在和这只橡皮鸭说话，你总是
end up hearing any illogic in your own thoughts, at which point
最终听到你自己的想法中任何不合理的地方，此时
the proverbial light bulb tends to go off and you're like, oh, I'm an idiot.
俗话说灯泡亮了，你就像，哦，我真蠢。
It's supposed to be less than, not less than or equal to.
应该是小于，而不是小于等于。
So literally just explaining to a duck or any inanimate object what's
所以，文字上来说，就是向一只鸭子或任何无生命的物体解释发生了什么
going on in your code will quite frequently just
在你代码中发生的事情，这经常会
help you see in your mind's eye what it is you've been doing wrong.
帮助你在脑海中看到你一直在做错的地方。
So rubber duck debugging is indeed a very effective technique
所以橡皮鸭调试确实是一种非常有效的技巧
even if you don't happen to have a small or large rubber duck.
即使你碰巧没有一只小或大的橡皮鸭。
Of course, you're also welcome to use the CS50 Duck who
当然，你也可以使用CS50 Duck，它
lives at cs50.ai, and also within a pane in VS Code at cs50.dev.
居住在cs50.ai，以及VS Code的窗格中，在cs50.dev。
You can ask the CS50 Duck about concepts you don't understand,
你可以向CS50 Duck询问你不理解的概念，
or you can even copy paste certain lines of code
或者，你甚至可以复制粘贴某些代码行
with which you might be having trouble and ask the duck for its own advice.
你可能遇到了一些麻烦，并向这只鸭子寻求它自己的建议。
All right.
好吧。
So, with those tools in our toolkit, let me propose now that we do--
所以，有了这些工具，现在我建议我们做——
that we introduce now a few lower-level features of C
现在介绍一下C语言中的一些低级特性
itself and better understand how we can start solving some of those problems
本身，并更好地理解如何开始解决其中的一些问题
like the readability of text or the encryption of data.
比如文本的可读性或数据的加密。
These were our so-called types last week when
这些是我们上周所说的类型，当
we introduced at least a subset of them or used them just to store data
我们至少介绍了其中的一部分，或者只是用它们来存储数据
in a certain format, so to speak.
以某种格式，可以说。
Like in week 0, we said that everything at the end of the day
就像在第0周，我们说，最终来说，一切
is just 0's and 1's, binary.
都是0和1，二进制。
And I claimed conceptually that how a computer knows if a set of bits
我概念上声称，计算机如何知道一组比特
is a number versus a letter versus a color or a sound or an image or a video
是一个数字还是一个字母，还是一个颜色，或者一个声音，或者一张图片，或者一个视频
is just context-dependent, like you're using Photoshop
仅仅是依赖于上下文，就像你使用Photoshop
or you're using Microsoft Word or something else.
或者你使用Microsoft Word或其他东西。
But last week, we saw a little more precisely that it's
但上周，我们更精确地看到了，它是
not quite as broad strokes as that.
不像那样宽泛。
It's more about what the programmer has told the software is
更多的是关于程序员告诉软件的是
being stored in a given variable.
存储在给定的变量中。
Is it an integer?
它是一个整数吗？
Is it a char, a character?
它是一个char，一个字符吗？
Is it a whole string?
它是一个完整的字符串吗？
Is it a longer integer or the like?
它是一个更长的整数还是类似的东西？
So you now have this control.
所以你现在有这种控制权。
The catch, though, recall, though, is that each of these types
不过，回想一下，是这些类型中的每一个
has only a finite amount of space allocated to it.
都只分配了有限的空间。
So for instance, an integer is typically 4 bytes,
例如，一个整数通常是4个字节，
and 4 bytes is 32 bits because it's 8 times 4.
而4个字节是32位，因为它是8乘以4。
32 bits, we claimed, is roughly 4 billion,
我们声称，32位大约是40亿，
but if you want to represent negative and positive numbers,
但如果你想表示负数和正数，
the biggest integer you can store is like 2 billion.
你能存储的最大整数大约是20亿。
Now that's really big for a lot of applications,
这对很多应用来说已经很大了，
but years ago, Facebook, for instance, was
但几年前，比如Facebook，
rumored to be using integers when they had fewer users.
据说在用户数量较少的时候使用了整数。
But now that they have billions of users--
但现在他们有数十亿用户——
3-plus billion users, an integer is no longer big enough for the Facebooks,
超过30亿用户，整数对于Facebook、
the Googles, the Microsofts and so forth of the world.
谷歌、微软等世界级公司来说已经不够大了。
So we also have longs, which use twice as many bytes, but exponentially
所以我们还有long，它使用两倍的字节数，但指数级地
bigger range of values.
更大的值范围。
Meanwhile, a bool, interestingly, is a byte, which
与此同时，bool很有趣，它是一个字节，这
is kind of bad design in what sense?
在某种程度上算是一种糟糕的设计？
Why might that be bad design?
为什么那可能是糟糕的设计？
It's only-- it should only be 2--
它应该只有2——
1 bit, rather, because a 0 or 1 should suffice.
确切地说，应该是1位，因为0或1就足够了。
Turns out, it's just easier to use a whole byte
事实证明，使用一个完整的字节更容易
even though we're wasting seven of those bits,
即使我们浪费了其中七个位，
but bools are represented nonetheless with 1 byte.
但bool仍然用1个字节表示。
Chars are going to be 1 byte.
char将占用1个字节。
Floats tend to be 4 bytes.
float通常是4个字节。
Doubles tend to be 8 bytes.
double通常是8个字节。
Some of this is system-dependent, but nowadays on modern computers,
有些是系统相关的，但在现代计算机上，
this tends to be a useful rule of thumb.
这通常是一个有用的经验法则。
The only one I can't commit to here is a string
这里我唯一不能确定的就是字符串
because a string, recall, is a sequence of text.
因为字符串，回想一下，是文本的序列。
And maybe it has no characters, one character, two, 10, 100.
它可能没有字符，一个字符，两个，十个，一百个。
So it's a variable number of bytes presumably
所以它很可能是一个可变数量的字节
where each byte represents a given character.
其中每个字节代表一个给定的字符。
So with that said, how do we get from an actual computer
综上所述，我们如何从实际的计算机
to information being represented therein?
到其中表示的信息？
Well, let me remind us that this is what's inside of our Macs, PCs, phones.
好吧，让我提醒大家，这就是我们Mac、PC、手机里面的东西。
Even though this isn't a scale and it might not be the same shape,
即使这不是一个比例尺，它可能也不同形状，
this is memory, random access memory.
这就是内存，随机存取内存。
And on these black chips, on the circuit board
在这些黑色芯片上，在电路板上
here, are the bytes that we keep talking about.
这里，就是我们一直在谈论的字节。
In fact, let's go ahead and zoom in on one of these chips,
事实上，让我们放大其中一个芯片，
fill the screen here.
填充这里屏幕。
And just for an artist's depiction's sake,
为了艺术描绘的缘故，
let me propose that if you've got, I don't know,
我建议，如果你有，我不知道，
a megabyte, a gigabyte-- like a lot of bytes packed into this chip nowadays,
一个兆字节，一个吉字节——像现在许多字节被塞进这个芯片一样，
it stands to reason that no matter how many of them you have,
可以推测，无论你有多少个，
we could just number them from top to bottom
我们可以从上到下对它们进行编号
and we could say that this is byte 1, or you know what?
我们可以说，这是字节1，或者你知道吗？
This is byte 0, 1, 2, 3, and this is maybe byte 1 billion or whatever it is.
这是字节0、1、2、3，也许这是字节10亿或者其他什么东西。
So you can think of memory as having addresses
所以你可以认为内存有地址
or just locations, numeric indices that identify each of those bytes
或者位置，数值索引，用来识别每一个字节
individually.
分别。
Why a byte?
为什么是字节？
Individual bits are not that useful, so 8, again, 1 byte
单个比特没有太大用处，所以 8 个比特，也就是 1 字节
tends to be the de facto standard.
通常是事实上的标准。
Let me-- so, for instance, if you're storing just a single character,
比如说，如果你只是存储一个字符，
a char, it might be stored literally in this top-left corner, so to speak,
一个字符，它可能存储在内存芯片的左上角，打个比方，
of the chip of memory.
在内存芯片的左上角。
If you're storing maybe an integer, 4 bytes,
如果你要存储一个整数，4 个字节，
it might take up that many bytes.
它可能占用这么多字节。
If you're storing a long, it might take up that many bytes instead.
如果你要存储一个长整型，它可能会占用这么多字节。
Now we don't have to dwell on the particulars of the circuit board
现在我们不需要纠结电路板的细节
and these traces and all the connections, so let me just abstract
这些走线以及所有的连接，所以我简单抽象一下
this away and claim that what your computer's memory really
这个概念，并断言你的电脑内存实际上
is is just kind of this canvas, I mean kind of in the Photoshop sense.
就是一个画布，我指的是类似于 Photoshop 的画布。
If you've ever made pictures, it's just a grid
如果你曾经画过画，它就是一个网格
of pixels, up, down, left, right, that's really all your memory is.
像素网格，上下左右，这就是你的内存。
It's this canvas that you can manipulate the bits on to store numbers anywhere
它是一个画布，你可以在上面操控比特，在任何地方存储数字
you want in the computer's memory.
你想要在电脑的内存中存储数字。
So in fact, let's zoom in here and let's consider
实际上，让我们放大看看，并考虑一下
how your computer is actually storing information using just these bytes.
你的电脑如何使用这些字节来存储信息。
At the end of the day, no matter how sophisticated
归根结底，无论你的 Mac、PC 或者手机有多高端，
your Mac, your PC, your phone is, like this is all
这都是
it has access to for storing information.
它用来存储信息的东西。
It's a canvas of bytes, and what you do with this
它是一个字节的画布，你如何使用它
now really invites design decisions.
现在真的需要设计决策。
So let's consider this.
所以让我们考虑一下。
Here is an excerpt from a program wherein maybe I'm
这里有一个程序片段，我可能在
prompting the user for three scores.
提示用户输入三个分数。
Like three test, scores, exam scores, something like that.
比如三次考试的分数，类似这样。
And the purpose in life of this program is maybe
这个程序的目的是
to average those three scores together if you
把这三个分数加起来求平均数，如果你
want to get a sense of where you stand in some class.
想了解你在某门课上的成绩情况。
So we can certainly whip up some code like this.
所以我们可以写出这样的代码。
And in just a moment, let me go ahead and flip over to VS Code here.
过一会儿，我切换到 VS Code。
And I'll write up a new program called scores.c.
我将编写一个名为 scores.c 的新程序。
And in this, let me go ahead and first include stdio.h,
在这个程序中，首先包含 stdio.h 头文件，
int main void at the top.
在开头添加 int main 函数。
And in here, let me go ahead and assume that, eh,
在这里，我假设，
it's not been the greatest semester.
这学期不太顺利。
So my first score, which I'll call score1, was a 72,
我的第一个分数，我将它命名为 score1，是 72，
my second score was a 73, but my third score, score3, was like a 33.
我的第二个分数是 73，但我的第三个分数，score3，是 33。
Now you might remember these numbers in another context,
你可能在另一个情况下记得这些数字，
they might spell a message, but in this case, it's just integers.
它们可能拼出一个信息，但在这种情况下，它们仅仅是整数。
It's just numbers because I'm telling the computer to treat these as ints.
它们只是数字，因为我告诉电脑将它们视为整数。
Now if I want to figure out what my average is, I can do a bit of math.
现在，如果我想计算我的平均分，我可以做一些计算。
So let me just print out that my average is--
所以，我只需要打印出我的平均分是--
and I don't want to shortchange myself.
我不想低估自己。
I'm not going to use %i because I don't want to lose even anything after
我不会使用 %i，因为我不想在
the decimal point.
小数点后丢失任何东西。
So we're going to use a float instead.
所以我们将使用浮点数。
And my average i claim will be score1 plus score2 plus score3
我声称我的平均值将是 score1 加 score2 加 score3
divided by 3, semicolon.
除以 3，分号。
With parentheses, because just like grade school math,
用括号，因为就像小学数学一样，
like order of operations, I parenthesize the numerator,
就像运算顺序一样，我将分子括起来，
so I can divide the whole thing by 3.
这样我就可以用 3 除以整个表达式。
But I have screwed up already.
但我已经搞砸了。
I am going to shortchange myself and not give myself as high a grade
我要亏待自己，不给自己这么高的分数
as I deserve, but this one's subtle.
尽管我应得，但这有点微妙。
What have I done wrong?
我做错了什么？
Yeah, I might want to cast these scores to floats
是的，我可能想要将这些分数转换为浮点数
because if you do integral math, divide an integer or the sum of an integers--
因为如果你做的是整数运算，除以一个整数或者几个整数的和——
some integers by an integer, it's going to be an integer as the result,
用一个整数除以几个整数，结果也会是一个整数，
so it's going to throw away anything after the decimal point.
所以它会丢弃小数点后的任何东西。
Even if it's something-point-1, something-point-5, something-point-9,
即使是 something-point-1，something-point-5，something-point-9，
that fraction is going to be thrown away.
那个小数部分会被丢弃。
There's a bunch of ways to fix this.
有很多方法可以解决这个问题。
I could just use floats or doubles for all of these.
我可以简单地对所有这些使用浮点数或双精度数。
I could cast score1, score2, or score3 as you propose.
我可以像你建议的那样，将 score1，score2 或 score3 转换为浮点数。
Frankly, the simplest way is just change the denominator
坦白地说，最简单的方法就是改变分母
because so long as I've got one float involved in the math,
因为只要在运算中包含一个浮点数，
this will promote the whole arithmetic expression to being floating point
整个算术表达式就会提升为浮点运算
math instead of integer math.
而不是整数运算。
So let me go ahead now and do make scores, Enter.
所以我现在就开始做 make scores，回车。
So far, so good. ./scores, and my average seems to be not great,
到目前为止一切都好。 ./scores，我的平均分似乎不太好，
but 59.33333--
但 59.33333——
so in the third.
所以排在第三名。
But I would have lost that third if I hadn't
但我如果没
used a float in this particular way.
用这种方式使用浮点数，我就会失去第三名。
Well, let's consider now what's actually going on inside of the computer
好吧，现在让我们考虑一下计算机内部实际上发生了什么
when I store these three variables.
当我存储这三个变量时。
So, back to the grid here, just my canvas of memory.
所以，回到这里的网格，也就是我的内存画布。
It doesn't really matter where things end up.
它们最终出现在哪里并不重要。
I might put it here, I might put it there,
我可能把它放在这里，也可能放在那里，
the computer makes these decisions.
计算机会做出这些决定。
But for the artist's sake, I'm going to put it at the top left-hand corner
但为了艺术的缘故，我要把它放在左上角
here.
这里。
So, score1 is containing the integer 72.
所以，score1 包含整数 72。
Why is it taking up four squares, though?
为什么它占用了四个方格呢？
Because?
因为？
It's an integer.
它是一个整数。
And on this system, an integer is 4 bytes.
在这个系统上，一个整数是 4 字节。
So I've drawn it to scale, if you will. score2 is the number 73,
所以，如果你愿意，我把它画成了比例。 score2 是数字 73，
it also takes 4 bytes.
它也占用了 4 字节。
By coincidence, but also by convention, it
巧合的是，也是按照惯例，它
will likely end up next to the first integer
很可能最终会出现在第一个整数旁边
in memory because I've only got three variables going on anyway,
在内存中，因为我只有三个变量在运行。
so the computer quite likely will store them back to back to back.
所以计算机很可能将它们存储在一起。
And indeed, by that logic, score3, containing the number 33,
实际上，根据这种逻辑，score3包含数字33，
is going to fill in this space here.
将填充这里空间。
We'll consider down the road what happens
我们将在后面考虑发生什么
if things get fragmented-- something's here,
如果事情变得碎片化——这里有些东西，
something's here, something's here, but for now, we
这里有些东西，这里有些东西，但现在，我们
can assume that this is probably contiguous, though not necessarily so.
可以假设这可能是连续的，虽然不一定如此。
All right, so that's pretty straightforward,
好的，所以这很简单，
but what's really going on?
但实际上发生了什么？
Well, these are just bytes of memory--
嗯，这些只是内存字节——
that is, bits of memory times 8.
也就是说，内存位乘以8。
And so what's really going on is this pattern
因此，实际上正在发生的是这种模式
of 0's and 1's is being stored to represent 72.
0和1被存储起来表示72。
This pattern of 0's and 1's is being stored
这种0和1的模式被存储
to represent 73, and similarly, 33.
用来表示73，同样，33。
But that's a very low level detail that we don't really care about,
但这是一个非常底层的细节，我们并不关心，
so we'll generally just think about these as numbers like 72, 73, 33.
所以我们通常只把它们当作72、73、33这样的数字来考虑。
All right.
好的。
So if we go back to the actual code, though, here, I
所以如果我们回到实际代码，这里，我
wonder if this is the best idea.
想知道这是否是最好的主意。
These three lines of code are correct.
这三行代码是正确的。
I got my 59 and 1/3 for my average, which I claim
我得到了我的平均分59又1/3，我声称
is correct, but code-wise, this should maybe rub you the wrong way.
是正确的，但从代码的角度来说，这可能让你觉得不舒服。
Even if you hadn't programmed before CS50,
即使你在CS50之前没有编程过，
why might this not be the best approach to storing things
为什么这可能不是存储东西的最佳方法
like scores in a program?
比如程序中的分数？
How might this get us in trouble?
这可能会给我们带来什么麻烦？
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不见]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：是的。
It's not the best because you have to use a whole bunch
这不是最好的，因为你必须使用很多
of different variables for each score.
不同的变量来表示每个分数。
They're almost identically named, though, but just imagine
虽然它们的名字几乎完全相同，但请想象
in almost any question involving the design of your code, what happens is n,
在几乎任何涉及你代码设计的问题中，发生的事情是n，
the number of things involved, gets larger?
参与的事物数量变大？
Am I really going to start writing code that has score4, score5, score6,
我真的要开始写包含score4、score5、score6的代码吗？
score10, score20?
score10、score20？
I mean, your code is just going to look like this mess of mostly copy-paste
我的意思是，你的代码看起来就像这样一堆大部分是复制粘贴的东西
except that the number at the end of the variable is changing.
除了变量末尾的数字在改变。
Like that should make you cringe a little bit because it's not
这应该让你有点畏缩，因为这不是
going to end well eventually.
最终会得到好的结果。
And typographical errors are going to get in the way most likely
而且打字错误很可能会妨碍
because we'll make mistakes.
因为我们会犯错误。
So how can we do a little bit better than that?
那么我们如何做得比这更好一些呢？
Well, let me propose that we introduce what we're going to now call an array.
好吧，我建议我们引入一个现在叫做数组的东西。
An array is a sequence of values back to back to back in memory.
数组是内存中一系列紧挨着的数值。
So an array is just a chunk of memory storing values back to back to back.
所以数组只是一块存储紧挨着数值的内存。
So no gaps, no fragmentation.
所以没有间隙，没有碎片化。
From left to right, top to bottom, just as I already drew.
从左到右，从上到下，就像我之前画的那样。
But these arrays in C, at least, are going
但是，至少在 C 语言中，这些数组将
to give a slightly new syntax that addresses exactly your concern.
提供一种稍微新的语法，准确地解决你的问题。
So here instead is I would propose how you define a one variable--
所以，这里我建议你如何定义一个变量——
not three, one variable called scores, plural, each of whose values
不是三个，而是名为 scores（复数）的一个变量，其每个值
is going to be an int, and you want three integers tucked away
将是一个 int 类型，你想将三个整数存储
in that variable.
在这个变量中。
So now I can pluralize the name of my variable
所以现在我可以将我的变量名改为复数形式
because by using square brackets and the number 3, I'm telling the compiler,
因为使用方括号和数字 3，我告诉编译器，
give me enough room for not one, not two, but three integers in total.
给我足够的空间，不是一个，不是两个，而是总共三个整数。
And the computer is going to do me a favor by storing them back
而且计算机将帮我一个忙，将它们存储回去
to back to back in the computer's memory.
到计算机内存中，相邻存放。
Now assigning values to these variables is almost the same,
现在给这些变量赋值几乎是一样的，
but the syntax looks like this.
但是语法看起来是这样的。
To assign the first value, I do scores, bracket, 0 equals whatever, 72.
要分配第一个值，我使用 scores，方括号，0 等于任何值，72。
scores, bracket, 1 equals 73; scores, bracket, 2 equals 33.
scores，方括号，1 等于 73；scores，方括号，2 等于 33。
And it's square brackets consistently.
并且始终使用方括号。
And notice, this is a feature--
请注意，这是一项功能——
or a downside of C.
或者说 C 语言的缺点。
We very frequently use the same syntax for slightly different ideas.
我们经常使用相同的语法表达略微不同的含义。
This first line tells the computer, give me an array of size 3.
第一行告诉计算机，给我一个大小为 3 的数组。
These next three lines mean, go into this array at location 0
接下来的三行意味着，进入这个数组的第 0 个位置
and put this value there.
并将这个值放在那里。
Location 1, put this value there; location 2, put this value there.
第 1 个位置，将这个值放在那里；第 2 个位置，将这个值放在那里。
So same syntax, but different meaning depending on the context here.
所以，相同的语法，但根据上下文，含义不同。
But the equal sign indeed means that this is assignment from right
但是，等号确实意味着，这是从右
to left just like last week.
到左的赋值，就像上周一样。
So what does this mean in the computer's memory?
那么，在计算机内存中，这意味着什么呢？
Well, in this case here, we now have a slightly different way of doing this.
好吧，在这个例子中，我们现在有一种稍微不同的方法来做到这一点。
And actually, let me do it first in code.
实际上，让我先在代码中演示一下。
Let me go back to VS Code here, and let me
让我回到 VS Code 这里，然后让我
propose that instead of having these three separate variables,
建议，与其使用这三个独立的变量，
let me give myself an int, scores variable of size 3,
让我给自己一个大小为 3 的 int 型 scores 变量，
and then do scores, bracket, 0 equals 72; scores, bracket, 1 equals 73;
然后执行 scores，方括号，0 等于 72；scores，方括号，1 等于 73；
scores, bracket, 2 equals 33.
scores，方括号，2 等于 33。
And now I have to change this syntax slightly, but same idea.
现在我需要稍微改变一下语法，但想法是一样的。
scores, bracket, 0; scores, bracket, 1; and lastly, scores, bracket, 2.
scores，方括号，0；scores，方括号，1；最后，scores，方括号，2。
So a couple of key details.
所以，一些关键细节。
I started counting at 0.
我从 0 开始计数。
Why?
为什么？
That's just the way it is with arrays.
这就是数组的规则。
You must start counting at 0 unless you want to waste one of those spaces.
你必须从 0 开始计数，除非你想要浪费其中一个空间。
And what you definitely don't want to do is
你绝对不想做的是
go into scores, bracket, 3 because I only
访问 scores，方括号，3，因为我只有
ask the computer for three integers.
要求计算机提供三个整数。
If I blindly do something like this, you're going too far.
如果我盲目地这样做，你就超出了范围。
You're going beyond the end of the chunk of memory
你正在超出内存块的末尾
and bad things will often happen.
而且经常会发生不好的事情。
So we won't do that just yet.
所以我们现在还不会这样做。
But for now, 0, 1, and 2 are the first, second, and third locations.
但就目前而言，0、1 和 2 分别是第一个、第二个和第三个位置。
So if I recompile this code-- so make scores seems OK. ./scores,
所以，如果我重新编译此代码——让得分看起来没问题。./得分，
and I get the exact same answer there.
我在这里得到了完全相同的答案。
But let me make it more dynamic because this
但让我把它变得更动态，因为这
is a little stupid that I'm compiling a program with my scores hardcoded.
我用我的得分硬编码来编译一个程序，这有点愚蠢。
What if I have a fourth exam tomorrow or something like that?
如果我明天再考一次，或者类似的事情呢？
So let's make it more dynamic and I think
所以让我们把它变得更动态，我认为
the syntax will start to make a little more sense.
语法会开始变得更合理。
Let's go ahead and use get_int and ask the user for a score.
让我们继续使用 get_int，并询问用户一个分数。
Let's go ahead and get_int and ask the user for another score.
让我们继续使用 get_int，并询问用户另一个分数。
Let's go ahead and get_int and ask the user for a third score,
让我们继续使用 get_int，并询问用户一个第三个分数，
now storing the return values in each of those variables.
现在将返回值存储在这些变量中的每一个中。
If I now do make scores--
如果我现在做 make scores——
oh, darn it.
哦，糟糕。
a mistake.
一个错误。
Similar to one I've made before, but we didn't see the error message last time.
类似于我之前犯过的错误，但我们上次没有看到错误信息。
What'd I do wrong?
我做错了什么？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不见]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
大卫·马兰： 好的。
What did I do wrong-- how about over here?
我做错了什么——这边怎么样？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不见]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰： 是的。
So I'm missing the CS50 header file.
所以，我缺少 CS50 头文件。
So how do you know that?
所以你是怎么知道的？
Well, implicit declaration of function get_int.
嗯，get_int 函数的隐式声明。
So it just doesn't know what get_int is.
所以它只是不知道 get_int 是什么。
Well, who does know what get_int is?
那么，谁知道 get_int 是什么？
The CS50 Library, that should be your first instinct.
CS50 库，这应该是你的第一直觉。
All right.
好吧。
Let me go to the top here and let me go ahead and squeeze in the CS50 Library
让我到顶部，然后让 CS50 库挤进来。
like this.
像这样。
Now let me clear my terminal.
现在让我清除我的终端。
make scores again.
再次 make scores。
We're back in business.
我们又回来了。
And notice, I don't need to do -l cs50.
并且注意，我不需要做 -l cs50。
make is doing that for me for clang, but we don't even see clang being executed,
make 正在为我做 clang 的工作，但我们甚至没有看到 clang 被执行，
but it is being executed underneath the hood, so to speak.
但它正在幕后执行，可以这么说。
All right, so ./scores, here we go.
好吧，所以 ./scores，我们开始了。
72, 73, 33.
72、73、33。
Math is still the same, but now the program is more interactive.
数学仍然是一样的，但现在这个程序更具交互性。
Now this, too, hopefully should rub you the wrong way.
现在，这也会让你感到不舒服。
This is correct, I would claim, but bad design still.
我敢说，这是正确的，但设计仍然很糟糕。
Reeks of week 0 inefficiencies.
充满了第 0 周的低效率。
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不见]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
大卫·马兰： 好的。
So I could ask the human how many scores do you want to input?
所以我可以问人类你想输入多少个分数？
Let's come back to that.
我们稍后再讨论这个问题。
But I think even in this construct, what better could I do?
但我认为，即使在这个结构中，我还能做得更好吗？
Use a loop, right?
使用循环，对吧？
Because I'm literally doing the same thing again and again.
因为我实际上是在一遍又一遍地做同样的事情。
And notice, this number is just changing slightly.
请注意，这个数字只是稍微改变了一下。
I would think that a little plus-plus could help there. get_int Score,
我认为加加运算符可能会有帮助。 get_int Score，
get_int Score, get_int Score-- that's the exact same thing.
get_int Score， get_int Score - 这完全一样。
So a loop is a perfect solution here.
所以循环在这里是一个完美的解决方案。
So let me go over into this code here, and I can still for now
所以让我看一下这里的代码，我现在仍然可以
declare it to be of size 3, but I think I
声明它的大小为 3，但我认为我
could do something like this-- for int i get 0, i is less than 3,
可以做这样的事情 - 对于 int i 获取 0，i 小于 3，
so I'm not going to make the same buggy mistake as I made earlier.
所以我不打算再犯之前犯过的同样的错误。
I++.
我++。
Inside of the loop now, I can do scores, bracket, i, and now
现在在循环里面，我可以做分数，方括号，i，现在
arrays are getting really interesting because you
数组变得非常有趣，因为你可以
can use and reuse them, but dynamically go to a specific location.
使用和重用它们，但动态地转到一个特定位置。
Equals get_int, quote-unquote, "Score."
等于 get_int，引号中的“分数”。
Now I can type that phrase just once and this loop ultimately
现在，我可以只键入一次这句话，而这个循环最终
will do the same thing, but it's getting better.
会做同样的事情，但它正在变得更好。
The code is getting better designed because it's more compact
代码的设计变得更好，因为它更紧凑
and I'm not repeating myself.
而且我没有重复自己。
72, 73, 33.
72、73、33。
Still works the same, but we're iteratively improving the code here.
它仍然以相同的方式工作，但我们正在迭代地改进这里的代码。
Now how else-- there's one design flaw here that I still don't love
现在还有什么方法呢？- 这里有一个设计缺陷，我仍然不喜欢
it's a little more subtle.
它更微妙。
Any observations?
有什么发现吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Ah, interesting.
大卫·马兰：啊，有趣。
So instead of dividing by 3.0, maybe I should divide it
所以，与其除以 3.0，我或许应该除以
by the array size, which at the moment is technically still 3,
数组的大小，目前它在技术上仍然是 3，
but I do concur that that is worrisome because they could get out of sync.
但我同意，这是令人担忧的，因为它们可能会不同步。
But there's something else that still isn't quite right.
但是，还有其他一些事情不太对劲。
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: I'm OK moving to this zero-indexed model.
大卫·马兰：我同意转向这种零索引模型。
So this is a new term of art.
所以这是一个新的术语。
To index into an array means to go to a specific location.
索引到数组中意味着转到一个特定位置。
So here, I'm indexing into location i, but i is going
所以在这里，我索引到位置 i，但 i 将
to start at 0 and then 1 and then 2.
从 0 开始，然后是 1，然后是 2。
I'm actually OK with that.
我实际上可以接受这一点。
Even though in common day life we would say score1, score2, score3,
即使在日常生活中我们会说 score1、score2、score3，
as a programmer, I just have to get into the habit
作为一个程序员，我必须养成
of saying score0, score1, score2 now.
现在说 score0、score1、score2 的习惯。
But something else.
但还有其他事情。
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: I could compute the average.
观众：我可以计算平均值。
DAVID MALAN: I could also compute the average in a loop
大卫·马兰：我也可以在循环中计算平均值
because indeed, this is only going-- so solving the problem halfway.
因为实际上，这只是...所以只解决了问题的一半。
I'm gathering the information in the loop,
我在循环中收集信息，
but then I'm manually writing it all out.
但我随后又手动将所有内容都写出来。
So it does feel like there should be a better solution here.
所以这里应该存在更好的解决方案。
But let me also identify one other issue I really don't like,
但请允许我指出另一个我不喜欢的問題，
and this is, indeed, subtle.
它确实很微妙。
I've got 3 here, I've got 3 here, and I essentially have 3 here,
这里有 3，这里也有 3，本质上这里也有 3，
albeit a floating point version.
尽管它是浮点版本。
This is just ripe for me making a mistake eventually and changing one
这最终让我很容易犯错，并改变其中
of those values, but not the other two?
一个值，但没改另外两个？
So how might I fix this?
那么我该如何解决呢？
I might at least do something like this.
我可能至少可以做这样的事情。
I could say integer maybe n for scores, I'll set that equal to 3.
我可以说整数 n 代表分数，我将它设置为 3。
I could then use n here, I could use n here.
然后我可以在此处使用 n，也可以在此处使用 n。
I could use n here, but that's a step backwards
我可以在此处使用 n，但这是一种倒退
because I don't want an int because I'm going to run into the same math issue
因为我不想要一个整数，因为我将遇到相同数学问题
as before, but I could convert it-- that is, cast it to a float,
与之前一样，但我可以将其转换，即将其转换为浮点数，
and we did that briefly last week.
我们上周简要介绍了这一点。
But there's one other thing I could do here that we did introduced last week.
但这里还有一种上周介绍过的做法。
This is better because I don't have a magic number floating around
这更好，因为我没有一个到处乱飞的魔术数字
in multiple places.
在多个地方。
Yeah, if I really want to be proper, I should probably
是的，如果我真的想做到规范，我可能应该
say this should be a constant integer.
说这应该是一个常数整数。
Why?
为什么？
Because I don't want to accidentally change it myself.
因为我不希望自己不小心修改它。
I don't want to be collaborating with a colleague
我不想与同事合作
and they foolishly change it on me.
而他们愚蠢地修改了它。
This just sends a stronger signal to the compiler, do not let the humans change
这向编译器发送了一个更强的信号，不要让人类修改
this value.
这个值。
And now just to point out one other feature of C,
现在，只指出 C 语言的另一个特性，
if you have a number like this, like the number 3,
如果你有一个这样的数字，比如数字 3，
I've deliberately capitalized this variable name really
我特意将这个变量名首字母大写，实际上
for the first time.
是第一次这样做。
Any time you have a constant, it tends to be a convention
任何时候你有一个常数，这往往是一个约定
to capitalize it just to draw your attention to it.
将其首字母大写，只是为了吸引你的注意。
It doesn't mean anything technically.
在技术上这没有任何意义。
Capitalizing a variable does nothing to it,
将变量首字母大写不会对它产生任何影响，
but it draws attention visually to it to the human.
但它会视觉上地吸引人们对它的注意。
So if you declare something as a constant,
所以如果你将某物声明为常数，
it's commonplace to capitalize it just because.
将它首字母大写是很常见的，仅仅是因为如此。
Moreover, if you have a constant that you might want to occasionally modify--
此外，如果你有一个常数，你可能偶尔想修改它，
maybe next semester when there's four exams or five exams instead of three,
也许下学期会有四次考试或五次考试，而不是三次，
it actually is OK sometimes to define what
有时定义以下内容实际上是可以的，
might be called a global variable, a variable that is not
可能被称为全局变量，一个不在
inside of curly braces, it's literally at the top of the file outside of main,
花括号内的变量，它实际上位于文件顶部的 main 函数外部，
and despite what I said about scope last week,
尽管我上周谈到了作用域，
a global variable like this on line 4 will be in scope
像这样在第 4 行上的全局变量将位于作用域内
to every function in this file.
对该文件中每个函数而言。
So it's actually a way of sharing a variable
所以它实际上是一种共享变量的方式
across multiple functions, which is generally fine if you're
跨多个函数共享，如果你使用常量，通常是可以的。
using a constant.
使用常量。
If you intend to change it, there's probably a better way
如果你打算更改它，可能有一种更好的方法
than actually using a global variable, but this is just
而不是使用全局变量，但这仅仅是
in contrast to what I previously did, which I would
与我之前做的事情形成对比，我会
call, by contrast, a local variable.
称之为局部变量。
But again, I'm just trying to reduce the probability of making mistakes
但再次强调，我只是在尝试降低犯错的概率
somewhere in the code.
在代码的某个地方。
And I do agree.
我同意。
I don't like that I'm still adding all of these scores
我不喜欢我仍然手动添加所有这些分数
manually even though clearly I had a loop a moment ago.
手动添加，尽管我之前有循环。
But for now, let's at least consider what's
但现在，让我们至少考虑一下
been going on inside of the computer's memory.
计算机内存中发生了什么。
So with this array, I now have not three variables, score1, score2, score3.
有了这个数组，现在我只有三个变量，score1、score2、score3。
I have one variable, an array variable, called scores, plural.
我只有一个变量，一个数组变量，叫做scores，复数。
And if I want to access the first element, its scores, bracket, 0.
如果我想访问第一个元素，它是scores，方括号，0。
If I want to access the second element, its scores, bracket, 1.
如果我想访问第二个元素，它是scores，方括号，1。
If I want to access the third element, it's scores, bracket, 2.
如果我想访问第三个元素，它是scores，方括号，2。
If I were to make a mistake and do scores, bracket, 3,
如果我犯了错误，并做了scores，方括号，3，
which is the fourth element, I'd end up in no man's land here,
这是第四个元素，我会在无人区，
and worst case, your program could crash or something weird will happen,
最糟糕的情况下，你的程序可能会崩溃，或者发生一些奇怪的事情，
spinning beach balls, those kinds of things.
旋转沙滩球，那些东西。
Just don't make those mistakes.
不要犯这些错误。
And C makes it easy to make those mistakes,
C让犯这些错误变得容易，
so the onus is really on you programmatically.
所以，编程上的责任真的在你身上。
Questions on this use of arrays?
关于数组使用的问题？
Question on this use of arrays?
Yeah, in back.
好的，在后面。
AUDIENCE: Is there any way [INAUDIBLE]?
观众：有没有什么方法[听不清]？
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
大卫·马兰：一个很好的问题。
Is there any way to create an array just by using syntax alone
有没有什么方法，只使用语法
without prompting the human for it?
而不提示用户？
Short answer, yes.
简短回答，是的。
If you want to have an array of integers called, for instance, array,
如果你想要一个名为array的整数数组，
you could actually do like 13, 42, 50, something like this,
你可以实际做成像13, 42, 50这样的，
would give you an array if you use this syntax.
如果使用这种语法，会给你一个数组。
This would give you an array of size 3 where the three values by default
这会给你一个大小为3的数组，其中三个值默认情况下
are 13, 42 and 50.
是13、42和50。
It's not syntax we'll use for now, but there is syntax like that.
我们现在不会使用这种语法，但有这样的语法。
It's not quite as user-friendly, though, as other languages
不过，它不像其他语言那样用户友好
if you've indeed programmed before.
如果你之前确实编程过。
Other questions on this use of arrays?
关于数组使用其他问题？
Yeah, in front.
好的，前面。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Is there a way to copy what?
大卫·马兰：有没有办法复制什么？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Oh, is there a way to calculate the length of an array?
大卫·马兰：哦，有没有办法计算数组的长度？
Short answer, no, and I'm about to show you one demonstration of this.
简短回答，没有，我马上要向你展示一个演示。
Those of you who have programmed before in Java, in JavaScript,
对于那些之前用 Java、JavaScript 或其他语言编程过的人来说，
in certain other languages, it's very easy to get the length of an array.
在其他一些语言中，获取数组的长度非常容易。
You essentially just ask the array, what's its length?
你只需直接问数组：它的长度是多少？
C does not give you that capability.
C 语言没有提供这种功能。
The onus is entirely on you and me to remember, s as with another variable,
我们必须自己记住，就像其他变量一样，
like n, how long the array is.
例如变量 n，数组的长度是多少。
And so in fact, let me go ahead and do this.
事实上，让我来做这件事。
I'm going to go ahead and open up a baking style, a program
我将打开一个烘焙风格的程序，
that I wrote in advance here which kind of escalates quickly,
我之前写过这个程序，它会很快变得复杂，
but there's not really too many new ideas here except for the array
但除了数组之外，这里没有太多新的想法。
specifics.
具体细节。
So this is scores.c premade this time.
所以这次是预先制作的 scores.c。
And notice what I have.
注意我这里有什么。
One, I've included cs50.h and stdio.h at the top, so that's the same.
首先，我在顶部包含了 cs50.h 和 stdio.h，这和之前一样。
I have declared a constant called n, set it equal to 3.
我声明了一个名为 n 的常量，将其设置为 3。
That is now the same as of my most recent change.
这和我的最新更改保持一致。
I did introduce an average function, which was one of the remaining concerns
我引入了一个平均值函数，这是我之前剩下的一个问题。
that I could compute the average with some kind of loop, too.
我可以用某种循环来计算平均值。
That average function is going to return a float, which is what.
这个平均值函数将返回一个浮点数，也就是...
I want my average to be a float with the fraction.
我希望我的平均值是一个带有小数部分的浮点数。
But notice this.
但注意这个。
In answer to your question, if I want a function called
为了回答你的问题，如果我想要一个名为
average to do something iterate over an array step by step by step,
average 的函数来执行一些操作，循环遍历数组，一步一步地，
add up all the numbers, and divide by the total number of numbers,
将所有数字加起来，然后除以数字的总数，
I need to give it the array of numbers, and I need to tell it how many of those
我需要将数字数组传递给它，并且需要告诉它有多少个
numbers are.
数字。
So I literally have to pass in two values.
所以我必须传递两个值。
Meanwhile, this code is the same as before inside of main.
与此同时，这段代码在 main 函数内部与之前相同。
I'm declaring a variable called scores of size n.
我声明了一个名为 scores 的变量，大小为 n。
I'm iterating from i to n.
我从 i 迭代到 n。
And actually-- yep.
实际上，是的。
And then in this loop, I'm assigning each of the scores a return
然后在这个循环中，我为每个分数分配一个返回值
value of get_int.
get_int 的值。
The last line of main is this-- print out the average with f,
main 函数的最后一行是：用 f 打印出平均值，
but don't just do it manually by adding and dividing with parentheses.
但不要用括号手动进行加法和除法。
Call the average function, pass in the length of the array and the array
调用平均值函数，传入数组的长度和数组本身，
itself, and hope that it returns a float that then gets plugged into percent f
并希望它返回一个浮点数，然后被插入到百分号 f 中。
So I would claim that pretty much all of this, even though it's a lot,
我认为，尽管代码量很大，但所有这些
should be familiar.
应该都是熟悉的。
There's no real new ideas except for this use of the global variable now
除了现在使用全局变量和这个平均值函数之外，没有真正的新想法。
and this average function.
这个平均值函数。
So let me scroll down to the average function
所以让我滚动到平均值函数
because this is the takeaway from this final example.
因为这是这个最后一个例子的重点。
In this example here--
在这个例子中，
let me scroll up to the average function,
让我滚动到平均值函数，
copy-pasted the prototype for the very first line.
复制粘贴第一行的原型。
And here's how I'm computing the average.
这就是我计算平均值的方式。
There's different ways of doing this, but here's an accumulator way.
有很多种方法可以做到这一点，但这里有一个累加器的方式。
On line 28, I'm declaring a variable inside of the average function called
在第 28 行，我在平均值函数内部声明一个名为
sum, and I'm just initializing it to 0.
sum 的变量，并且我将其初始化为 0。
Why?
为什么？
Mentally I want to add up all of the person scores
在脑海中，我想把所有人的分数加起来
and then I want to divide by the total and that's my mathematical average.
然后，我想除以总数，这就是我的数学平均值。
So here's my loop where I'm iterating from 0 up to, but not
所以，这是我的循环，我从 0 开始迭代，但不会
through the length-- so that should be three times.
到达长度，所以应该执行三次。
I am adding to the sum variable whatever is at the i-th location, so to speak,
我将 i 位置的值，也就是数组的第 i 个元素，加到 sum 变量上。
of the array.
数组的第 i 个元素。
So this is array, bracket 0; array, bracket, 1; array, bracket,
所以这是数组 [0]，数组 [1]，数组 [
2 on each iteration.
2]，在每次迭代中。
And then the last thing I'm doing is a nice one-liner.
最后，我做了一行简洁的代码。
I'm dividing the sum, which is an int, which is the sum of 72, 73, 33,
我将 sum 除以 length，sum 是一个 int 类型的值，它等于 72 + 73 + 33，
divided by the length, which is 3, but 3 is not a float, so I cast it to a float
length 等于 3，但 3 不是一个 float 类型的值，所以将其强制转换为 float 类型
so that the end value, hopefully, is going to be 59.33333 and so forth.
以便最终的值，我希望会是 59.33333 等等。
So the only thing that's weird syntactically is this, though.
然而，语法上唯一奇怪的是这一点。
When you define a function in C that takes an argument that isn't just
在 C 语言中，当你定义一个函数，它接收一个参数，这个参数不是一个简单的
a simple char, isn't just a simple integer, it's actually an array,
字符，不是一个简单的整数，而是一个数组，
you don't have to know the array's length in advance.
你不需要预先知道数组的长度。
You can just put square brackets after the name you give it.
你可以在你给它起的名字后面加上方括号。
And I don't have to call it array.
而且我不必把它叫做 array。
I could call it x or y or z or anything else.
我可以把它叫做 x 或 y 或 z，或者任何其他东西。
I called it array just to make clear that it's an array,
我把它叫做 array 只是为了清楚地表明它是一个数组，
but you do need to know the length somehow.
但你确实需要以某种方式知道它的长度。
OK.
好的。
Questions on combining those ideas in that there way?
关于以这种方式将这些想法结合在一起，你们有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
Well, we've only dealt with numbers thus far.
嗯，到目前为止，我们只处理了数字。
It would be nice to actually deal with letters and words and paragraphs
实际上，如果能处理字母、单词和段落，那会很不错，
and the like, much like our readability example,
就像我们的可读性示例一样，
but I think first, some snacks and some fruit are served in the transept.
但我想，首先，在中殿会供应一些小吃和水果。
So we'll see you in 10.
所以我们 10 分钟后再见。
See you in 10.
10 分钟后再见。
All right.
好的。
So we're back.
所以我们回来了。
And up until now, we've been representing
到目前为止，我们一直在表示
just numbers underneath the hood, but we've
只是数字，但在幕后，我们已经
introduced arrays, which gave us this ability, recall,
引入了数组，这给了我们这种能力，还记得吗？
to store numbers back to back to back.
将数字一个接一个地存储起来。
So it turns out, you actually had this capability for the past
所以事实证明，过去的一周你实际上就拥有了这种能力，
week even though you might not have realized it.
即使你可能没有意识到这一点。
And let me propose that we first consider very simple example of three
我建议我们首先考虑三个非常简单的例子
chars instead of three integers.
字符，而不是三个整数。
And for simplistically, I'm going to call them c1, c2,
为了简单起见，我将它们称为 c1、c2，
and c3 just for the sake of discussion.
以及 c3，仅仅为了讨论。
But I'm going to put our familiar characters, "HI!"
但我要用单引号将我们熟悉的字符“HI!”
in those variables using single quotes because again.
放入这些变量中，因为再次。
That's what you do when using individual chars
这就是你在使用单个字符时所做的
to make the point that I can store three chars in three separate variables.
为了说明我可以将三个字符存储在三个单独的变量中。
So let me go ahead and go over to VS Code
所以让我继续，到 VS Code
here and let me create something called hi.c.
这里，让我创建一个名为 hi.c 的文件。
And in this program, I'll first include stdio.h, int main void as before.
在这个程序中，我将首先像之前一样包含 stdio.h、int main void。
And then inside of main, let's just do exactly that.
然后在 main 内部，让我们做完全相同的操作。
Char c1 equals, quote-unquote, capital H. Char C2 equals,
char c1 等于，引号、引号，大写 H。char c2 等于，
quote-unquote, capital I. Char C3 equals,
引号、引号，大写 I。char c3 等于，
quote-unquote, exclamation point.
引号、引号，感叹号。
So clearly not the best approach, but just for demonstration's sake.
所以显然这不是最好的方法，但仅仅是为了演示。
And here now that you understand hopefully
现在，希望你能明白
from week 1 that really number-- and really, from week 0,
从第一周开始，数字实际上是——实际上，从第零周开始，
that numbers are just letters, which can be something more, too.
数字只是字母，它们也可以是更多的东西。
We can really just use our basic understanding of C
我们实际上只需要使用我们对 C 的基本理解
to tinker with these ideas now and see them such
现在来修改这些想法，并看到它们
that there is indeed going to be no magic happening for us ultimately.
最终，对于我们来说，确实不会发生任何神奇的事情。
So let me go ahead and print out three characters-- %c, %c, %c, backslash n.
所以让我继续，打印出三个字符——%c、%c、%c、反斜杠 n。
And then print out c1, c2, c3.
然后打印出 c1、c2、c3。
So I've got three separate placeholders.
所以我有三个独立的占位符。
And we haven't really had occasion to use %c, but it means put char here,
我们还没有机会使用 %c，但它的意思是将字符放在这里，
unlike %s, which is put a whole string here, or %i, put an integer.
与 %s 不同，%s 是将整个字符串放在这里，或者 %i 是将整数放在这里。
Let me go ahead and make hi, no syntax errors, ./hi,
让我继续，创建 hi，没有语法错误，./hi，
and it should print out "HI!"
它应该打印出“HI!”
in exclamation points because I'm printing out
用感叹号，因为我正在打印
just three simple characters.
只是三个简单的字符。
But per our discussion as far back as week 0,
但根据我们早在第零周的讨论，
letters are just numbers and numbers are just letters,
字母只是数字，数字也仅仅是字母，
it just depends on the context in which we use them.
这取决于我们使用它们的上下文。
So let me change this %c to an i.
所以让我将 %c 更改为 i。
And I'm going to add a space just so that you can obviously
我将添加一个空格，这样你就可以清楚地
separate one number from another.
将一个数字与另一个数字分开。
Change this to i, change this to i, but still print out c1, c2, c3.
将这个改为 i，将这个改为 i，但仍然打印出 c1、c2、c3。
So no integers, per se.
所以没有真正的整数。
Let me just print out those chars.
让我只打印出那些字符。
Let me do make hi, no errors, ./hi, and now I see 72, 73, 33.
让我创建 hi，没有错误，./hi，现在我看到了 72、73、33。
So in the case of chars and ints, you can actually treat one as the other
所以对于字符和整数来说，你实际上可以将其中一个视为另一个
so long as you have enough bits to fit one in the other.
只要你有足够的位来容纳其中一个。
You don't have to cast even or do anything explicitly.
你甚至不需要强制转换或显式地做任何事情。
You do have to cast one of--
你必须强制转换其中一个——
converting an integer to a float to make clear to the compiler
将整数转换为浮点数，以便让编译器清楚
that you really intend to do this because that
你真的想这样做，因为这
could be destructive if it can't quite represent the number as you intend.
如果它不能完全如你预期的那样表示数字，那么这可能是破坏性的。
But in this case here, I think we're OK just poking around and seeing
但在这里，我认为我们只需要四处查看，看看
what's going on underneath the hood.
引擎盖下发生了什么。
Well, what is going on underneath the hood memory-wise?
那么，从内存的角度来看，底层到底发生了什么呢？
Well, something very similar.
嗯，非常相似。
Here's that canvas of memory.
这是内存的画布。
And maybe we got lucky and it's in the top left-hand corner
也许我们很幸运，它在左上角
like this-- c1, c2, c3.
就像这样——c1、c2、c3。
But these are just three individual characters,
但这些仅仅是三个独立的字符，
but we're getting awfully close to what we last week called
但我们正在非常接近上周我们所说的
a string, which are just characters, a sequence of characters
一个字符串，它仅仅是字符，一个字符序列
from left to right.
从左到右。
And in fact, I think if we combine this revelation that these are just
事实上，我认为如果我们将这些只是
numbers underneath the hood back to back to back combined
数字的发现，在底层一个接一个地组合起来
with the idea of an array from earlier, we can
与之前数组的概念结合起来，我们就可以
start to see what's really going on.
开始看到真正发生的事情。
Because indeed, underneath the hood, this is just a number, 72, 73, 33.
因为实际上，在底层，这只是一个数字，72、73、33。
And really, if we go lower level than that,
实际上，如果我们更底层一点，
it's these three patterns of 0's and 1's.
它就是这三个0和1的模式。
That's all that's going on inside of the computer,
这就是计算机内部发生的一切，
but it's our use of int that shows it to us as an integer.
但我们使用int将其显示为一个整数。
It's our use of char that makes it clear that it's a char, or equivalently,
我们使用char使它很清楚这是一个char，或者等效地，
%i and %c respectively.
分别为%i和%c。
But what exactly is a string?
但到底什么是字符串呢？
Well, it's really just a sequence of characters,
嗯，它实际上只是一系列字符，
and so why don't we go there?
所以我们为什么不去那里呢？
Let me propose that we actually give ourselves an actual string,
我建议我们给自己一个真实的字符串，
call it s-- we'll use double quotes this time.
叫做s——这次我们将使用双引号。
So if I go back to VS Code here, let me shorten this program
所以如果我回到这里的VS Code，让我简化一下这个程序
and just give myself a single string s, set it equal to "HI!"
只给自己一个字符串s，将其设置为"HI！"
in double quotes.
用双引号。
And then below that, let's go ahead and print out %s, backslash n,
然后在下面，让我们继续打印出%s、反斜杠n，
and then s itself.
然后是s本身。
And then, turns out, for reasons we'll soon
然后，事实证明，由于我们很快就会
see, I do need to include the CS50 Library so as
看到，我需要包含CS50库，以便
to use the actual keyword string here even though I'm not using get_string,
在这里使用实际的关键字字符串，即使我没有使用get_string，
but more on that another time.
但我们下次再讨论这个。
But if I now do make hi, it does compile ./hi and it still prints out the exact
但如果我现在编译hi，它确实会编译./hi，并且它仍然打印出完全一样的
same thing.
东西。
But what's going on inside of the computer's memory
但是当我在计算机内存中使用一个叫做s的字符串而不是三个字符时，
when I use a string called s instead of three chars, well,
到底发生了什么呢？嗯，
you can think of the string as taking up at least three bytes, H,
你可以认为这个字符串至少占用了三个字节，H，
I, exclamation point.
I，感叹号。
But it's not three separate variables, it's one variable.
但它不是三个独立的变量，而是一个变量。
But what does this really look like now, especially
但现在它真正是什么样子，尤其是
if I add back the yellow lines?
如果我添加回黄线呢？
s is really just an array of characters.
s实际上只是一个字符数组。
So we called it a string last week, and I claim today
所以上周我们称它为字符串，而我今天声称
that this is an abstraction in the CS50 library that's giving us this string,
这是一个CS50库中的抽象，它给了我们这个字符串，
but it's really just an array of size at least 3
但它实际上只是一个至少有3个大小的数组
here where s, bracket, 0 presumably gives me the H, s, bracket,
这里s，方括号，0可能给了我H，s，方括号，
1 is the I, s, bracket, 2 is the exclamation point.
1 是 I，s，括号，2 是感叹号。
But just by saying string, all of that happens automatically.
但只要说字符串，所有这些都会自动发生。
I don't even need to tell the computer how many chars are
我甚至不需要告诉计算机有多少个字符
going to be in this string all at once.
将要在这个字符串中一次性出现。
So in fact, let me go over to maybe a variant of this program
实际上，让我看一下这个程序的变体
and we can see this syntactically.
我们可以从语法上看到这一点。
So instead of printing out the whole string with %s,
所以，与其用 %s 打印出整个字符串，
let me actually be a little curious and print out %c, %c, %c,
让我有点好奇，并打印出 %c，%c，%c，
and then change s to s, bracket, 0, s, bracket, 1, s, bracket, 2.
然后将 s 更改为 s，括号，0，s，括号，1，s，括号，2。
Which is not better in any sense.
从任何意义上说，这都不算好。
This is way more tedious now, but it does
现在这要繁琐得多，但它确实
demonstrate that I can treat here in week 2
证明了我可以在第 2 周中将它
as though it's an array, which means even in week 1 it was an array,
像数组一样对待，这意味着即使在第 1 周，它也是一个数组，
we just didn't know it.
我们只是不知道。
We didn't have the syntax with which to express that.
我们没有语法来表达这一点。
So if I now do make hi, still compiles ./hi.
所以，如果我现在制作 hi，它仍然会编译 ./hi。
Same exact output, but I'm now just kind of manipulating
输出完全相同，但我现在只是在操作
the string in these different ways because I
字符串，用不同的方式，因为我
a string is just an array of characters, so I can
一个字符串仅仅是字符数组，所以我可以
treat with the square bracket notation.
用方括号表示法来处理。
But how do I know-- how does the computer know where hi ends?
但我怎么知道，计算机怎么知道 hi 在哪里结束？
And this is where strings get a little dangerous.
而这就是字符串变得有点危险的地方。
Like a char is 1 byte no matter what.
就像一个字符无论如何都是 1 个字节。
1 char, 1 character, that's it.
1 个字符，就是它了。
But a string, recall my question mark from earlier,
但是字符串，还记得我之前问的那个问题吗？
could be null bytes if it's--
如果它可能为空字节，因为它
you would think could be 0 bytes if you have nothing in it inside the quotes.
你会认为，如果你在引号里面什么都没有，它可能就是 0 个字节。
It could be one character, two, 10, 100 like I claimed,
它可能是一个字符，两个字符，10 个字符，100 个字符，就像我说的，
but how does the computer know where strings end?
但计算机怎么知道字符串在哪里结束？
Like how does the computer not know that the string is not
比如，计算机怎么不知道字符串不是
the whole row of memory here?
这里整行内存？
How does it know that it ends here?
它怎么知道它在这里结束？
Well, it turns out, all this time, when we've been using, quote-unquote,
好吧，事实证明，一直以来，当我们使用，引号引起来的，
string and using get_string from the CS50 library,
字符串，并使用 CS50 库中的 get_string，
there's actually a special sentinel value
实际上在计算机内存中每个字符串的末尾
at the end of every string in a computer's memory
都有一个特殊的哨兵值
that tells the computer string, stops here.
它告诉计算机字符串，到此为止。
And the sentinel value-- and by sentinel, I
而这个哨兵值—— 我说哨兵，是指
just mean special value that the world decided on decades ago, is all 0 bits.
几十年前全世界都决定使用的一个特殊值，它就是全 0 位。
If you have a byte with all 0 bits in it, that means string ends here.
如果你有一个字节，它的所有位都是 0，那就意味着字符串在这里结束。
So the implication is that the computer now, using a loop or something,
所以，这意味着计算机现在，使用循环或者其他什么，
can print out char, char, char-- oh, done,
可以打印出字符，字符，字符—— 哦，完成了，
because it sees this special value.
因为它看到了这个特殊值。
If it didn't have that, it might blindly go char, char, char, char char--
如果没有它，它可能会盲目地打印出字符，字符，字符，字符，字符——
printing out values of memory that don't belong to that given string.
打印出不属于该字符串的内存值。
So I was correcting myself verbally a moment ago
所以我刚才在口头上纠正了自己。
because I said that this string is of length 3, it's 3 bytes, but it's not.
因为我说这个字符串的长度是3，它有3个字节，但事实并非如此。
Every string in the world, both last week and now, this
世界上所有的字符串，无论是上周还是现在，都是
is actually n plus 1 bytes where n is the actual human length
实际上是 n+1 个字节，其中 n 是人类实际看到的长度
that you care about, H-I, exclamation point, or 3,
比如你关心的 H-I，感叹号，或者 3，
but it's always going to use one extra byte for this so-called zero value
但它始终会为这个所谓的零值使用一个额外的字节
at the end.
在结尾。
And this 0 value is very tedious to write a 0--
而这个 0 值用 8 个 0 比特来表示非常麻烦。
as 8 0 bits.
作为 8 个 0 比特。
So we would actually typically just write it as a 0.
所以我们通常会直接写成一个 0。
But you don't want to confuse a 0 on the screen-- it's actually being
但你不想把屏幕上的 0 和键盘上的数字 0 混淆。
like the number 0 on the keyboard.
它实际上就像键盘上的数字 0。
And so we would actually typically write this symbol with a backslash 0.
所以我们通常会用反斜杠 0 来写这个符号。
So this is the char-based representation of 0.
所以这是 0 的字符表示形式。
So it means the exact same thing, this is just
所以它表示的意义完全相同，这仅仅是
C notation that indicates that this is 8 0 bits,
C 语言的符号表示，它表示这是 8 个 0 比特，
but just makes clear that it's not literally the number
但它明确表示这并非是你在屏幕上看到的数字
0 that you want to see on the screen, it's a sentinel value
0，而是一个哨兵值
that is terminating this here string.
用来终止这个字符串。
So now what can I do once I know this information?
那么现在，知道了这些信息之后，我该怎么做呢？
Well, I can actually even see this let me go back to this code
我可以看到，让我回到这个代码
here in VS Code.
在 VS Code 里。
Let me change these %c's to %i's just like before.
像之前一样，把这些 %c 改成 %i。
And now, we'll see again those same numbers, make hi ./hi,
现在我们又会看到相同的数字，make hi ./hi，
there are the three.
它们是 3 个。
I can technically poke around a little bit further, %i one more,
我可以在技术上再深入一点，再来一个 %i，
and let's look at s, bracket, 3.
然后让我们看看 s，方括号，3。
I was not exaggerating earlier when I said,
之前我说的时候没有夸张，
in general, if you go past the end of an array, bad things can happen.
通常情况下，如果你超出数组的末尾，就会出现问题。
But in this case, I know that there is one more thing at the end of this array
但在这种情况下，我知道在这个数组的末尾还有一个东西
because this is how strings are built. This is not a CS50 thing,
因为字符串就是这样构建的。这与 CS50 无关，
this is a thing in C. Every string in the world in double quotes
这是 C 语言中的特性。世界上所有用双引号括起来的字符串
ends with a backslash 0-- that is 8 0 bits.
都以反斜杠 0 结尾，也就是 8 个 0 比特。
So if I really want, I can see this by printing out s, bracket, 3,
所以如果我真想看到，我可以打印出 s，方括号，3，
which is the fourth and final location.
也就是第四个也是最后一个位置。
If I recompile my code now, make hi ./hi, I should see 72, 73, 33, and 0.
如果我现在重新编译我的代码，make hi ./hi，我应该会看到 72，73，33 和 0。
That's always been there.
这些一直都在。
So I'm always using 4 bytes, somewhat wastefully, but somewhat necessarily
所以我一直使用 4 个字节，有些浪费，但也有些必要
so that the computer actually knows where that string ends.
这样计算机才能知道字符串的结尾在哪里。
So if we go back to the memory representation of this here,
所以如果我们回到这里这个内存的表示形式，
it's just as though you have an array of integers being stored contiguously back
就好像你有一个整数数组被连续存储在后面
to back to back, the last one of which means this is the end of the array
一个接一个，最后一个表示数组的结尾
of characters, but because I'm using, quote-unquote, "string,"
的字符，但因为我使用了“字符串”，
because I'm using %s and %c, I'm not seeing these numbers by default,
因为我使用了 %s 和 %c，所以默认情况下我没有看到这些数字，
I'm seeing H-I, exclamation point unless I explicitly tell printf, no, no, no,
我看到的是 H-I，感叹号，除非我明确告诉 printf，不，不，不，
no, show me with %i these actual integers.
不，用 %i 显示这些实际的整数。
This, then, is how you can think about the string.
那么，这就是你如何思考字符串的方式。
Like you don't really need to think about
就好像你并不需要去思考
it as being individual characters.
它是单个字符。
This is just s, and it has some length here,
这只是一个 s，它在这里有一些长度，
but it does not necessarily an array that you yourself have to create,
但它不一定是你自己需要创建的数组，
you get it automatically just by using a string.
你只要使用字符串，就可以自动获得它。
Now there's just-- not to add on to the jargon.
现在只是-- 不想增加专业术语。
This backslash 0, these 8 0 bits, there's
这个反斜杠 0，这些 8 位 0，有
actually a technical term for them.
实际上有一个专门的术语来称呼它们。
You can call them NUL.
你可以称它们为 NUL。
It's typically written in all caps like this, confusingly.
它通常像这样全部大写，很令人困惑。
In a couple of weeks, we're going to see another word pronounced null,
几周后，我们会看到另一个发音为 null 的词，
but spelled N-U-L-L. Left hand wasn't talking to right hand years ago,
但拼写为 N-U-L-L。几年前，左手和右手没有沟通，
but N-U-L means this is the 0 byte that terminates strings,
但 N-U-L 表示这是终止字符串的 0 字节，
that indicate the end of a string.
它表示字符串的结尾。
And fun fact, you've actually seen this before even though we glossed over it.
有趣的是，你实际上以前见过这个，即使我们把它略过了。
Here's that ASCII chart from last time.
这是上次的 ASCII 表。
If I focus on the leftmost column, guess what is the 0 ASCII character?
如果我把注意力集中在最左边的列，猜猜 0 ASCII 字符是什么？
NUL.
NUL。
You never see null on the screen, it's just how you pronounce 8 0 bits.
你永远不会在屏幕上看到 null，它只是你如何读出 8 位 0 的方式。
Whew!
呼！
questions on this representation of strings?
关于这种字符串表示方式，有什么问题吗？
Yeah?
有吗？
AUDIENCE: Are strings [INAUDIBLE]?
观众：字符串是 [听不清] 吗？
DAVID MALAN: Are string structured differently in other languages?
大卫·马兰：在其他语言中，字符串的结构是否不同？
Yes.
是的。
They are more powerful in other languages.
它们在其他语言中更强大。
In C, you have to build them yourself in this way.
在 C 语言中，你必须以这种方式自己构建它们。
More on that when we get to Python.
我们讲到 Python 时会详细介绍。
Other questions.
还有其他问题吗？
Yeah?
有吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
大卫·马兰：这个问题问得很好。
Does that mean we don't have a function to get the length of a string?
这意味着我们没有函数来获取字符串的长度吗？
Do we have to create it?
我们必须创建它吗？
Short answer, there is a function, but you have to-- someone
简短的回答，有一个函数，但你必须-- 有人
had to write code for it.
必须为它编写代码。
You can't just ask the string itself like you can in JavaScript or Java.
你不能像在 JavaScript 或 Java 中那样直接询问字符串本身。
What is the--
什么是--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you can.
大卫·马兰：是的，你可以。
It's actually more similar to Python than it is to JavaScript or Java,
它实际上更类似于 Python，而不是 JavaScript 或 Java，
but we'll see that in just a few minutes, in fact.
但事实上，我们将在几分钟内看到这一点。
So let's introduce maybe a couple of strings.
所以让我们引入几个字符串。
So here's two strings in the abstract called s and t,
所以这里有两个抽象的字符串，分别称为 s 和 t，
and I've initialized them arbitrarily to "HI!" and "BYE!"
我随机地将它们初始化为“HI！”和“BYE！”
just so we can explore what's going to actually happen underneath the hood.
这样我们就可以探索幕后实际发生的事情。
So let me go back to VS Code.
所以让我回到 VS Code。
Let me just completely change this program to be that instead.
让我完全改变这个程序，让它变成那样。
So string equals, quote-unquote, "HI!"
所以字符串等于，引号，"HI!"
String t equals, quote-unquote, "BYE!"
字符串t 等于，引号，"BYE!"
in all caps.
全部大写。
And then let's print them both out very simply. %s backslash n, s.
然后让我们简单地将它们都打印出来。%s 反斜杠 n，s。
Print out %s backslash n, t just so we can see what's going on.
打印出 %s 反斜杠 n，t，这样我们就可以看到发生了什么。
If I do make hi ./hi, I should, of course, see these two strings.
如果我确实创建了 hi ./hi，我当然应该看到这两个字符串。
But what's going on inside of the computer's memory?
但是计算机内存里发生了什么呢？
Well, in this computer's memory, assuming
嗯，在这个计算机的内存中，假设
these are the only two variables involved and assuming the computer
这两个是唯一涉及的变量，并且假设计算机
is just doing things top to bottom, "HI!"
只是从上到下做事，"HI!"
is probably going to be stored somewhere like this on my canvas of memory,
可能将存储在我记忆画布上的某个地方，
"BYE!"
is probably going to be stored there.
可能将存储在那里。
And it's wrapping around, but that's just an artist's representation.
它正在循环，但这只是一个艺术家的表示。
But notice that it is now really important
但请注意，现在非常重要
that there is this NUL byte at the end of each string
每个字符串的末尾都有这个 NUL 字节
because that's how the computer is going to know where "HI!"
因为这是计算机知道 "HI!" 的位置的方式
ends and where "BYE!"
结束，以及 "BYE!" 的位置
begins, otherwise you might see "HI!"
开始，否则你可能会看到 "HI!"
"BYE!"
all on the screen at once if there weren't the sentinel value indicating
如果不存在指示哨兵值的，所有这些都会同时出现在屏幕上
to printf, stop at this character.
告诉 printf 在此字符处停止。
But that's all that's going on in your program
但这就是你的程序中发生的一切
when you have two variables in this way.
当你用这种方式有两个变量时。
And in fact, what's really going on and things get a little more interesting
实际上，真正发生的事情，并且事情变得更加有趣
here, if I were to want two of these things,
这里，如果我想得到两个这样的东西，
notice that I could refer to them two as arrays.
请注意，我可以将它们称为数组。
So s, bracket, 0, 1, 2, and even 3.
所以 s，方括号，0，1，2，甚至 3。
t, bracket, 0, 1, 2, and even 3 and 4.
t，方括号，0，1，2，甚至 3 和 4。
But if I want to actually really blend some ideas,
但如果我实际上想真正融合一些想法，
just playing around with these basic principles now,
现在只是玩玩这些基本原则，
notice what I can do in this version.
请注意在这个版本中我可以做什么。
If I know I've got two arrays in VS Code,
如果我知道我在 VS Code 中有两个数组，
I don't strictly need to do string s and t and u
我不需要严格地使用字符串 s 和 t 以及 u
and v. That's devolving back into the scores1, scores2, scores3 mantra where
和 v。这又变成了 scores1、scores2、scores3 咒语，在那里
I had multiple variables almost the same name
我有几个几乎同名的变量
even though I'm using different letters of the alphabet.
即使我使用的是不同的字母。
What if I want--
如果我想要 -
what if I do this?
如果我这样做？
string words, and if I want to store two words in the computer's memory, fine.
字符串 words，如果我想在计算机的内存中存储两个单词，没问题。
Create an array of two strings.
创建一个包含两个字符串的数组。
But what is a string?
但是什么是字符串？
A string is an array of characters, so it's getting a little bit trippy here,
字符串是字符数组，所以这里有点奇怪，
but the ideas are still going to be the same. words, bracket,
但想法仍然是一样的。 words，方括号，
0 could certainly equal "HI!"
0 当然可以等于 "HI!"
words, bracket, 1 can certainly equal "BYE!" just like the scores example.
words，方括号，1 当然可以等于 "BYE!"，就像 scores 示例一样。
And then if I want to print these things with %s, I can print out words,
然后，如果我想用 %s 打印这些内容，我可以打印出 words，
bracket, 0.
方括号，0。
And then I can print out %s backslash n words bracket 1.
然后我可以打印出 %s 反斜杠 n words 方括号 1。
And the example is not going to be any different in terms of its output,
这个例子在输出方面不会有任何不同，
but I've now avoided s and t, I now just have one variable called words
但我现在避免了 s 和 t，现在只有一个名为 words 的变量
containing both of these here things.
包含这两个东西。
And if I really want to poke around, here's
如果我真的想四处看看，这里有
where things get even more visually overwhelming,
让事情变得更加视觉上让人眼花缭乱的地方，
but just the logical extension of these same ideas.
但只是这些相同想法的逻辑扩展。
Right now is the previous version where I had two variables, s and t.
现在是之前版本，我在那里有两个变量，s 和 t。
If I now use this new version where I have one variable called words,
如果我现在使用这个新版本，我有一个名为 words 的变量，
just like this here, the picture should follow logically like this.
就像这样，图片应该逻辑上像这样。
words, bracket, 0 is this string; words, bracket, 1 is this string;
words，方括号，0 是这个字符串；words，方括号，1 是这个字符串；
but what is each string?
但是每个字符串是什么？
It's an array of characters.
它是一个字符数组。
And so you can also think of it like this, where this H is words, bracket,
所以你也可以这样想，这里这个 H 是 words，方括号，
0, bracket, 0.
0，方括号，0。
So the 0-th character of the 0-th word.
所以是第 0 个单词的第 0 个字符。
And this is words, bracket, 0, 1; words, bracket, 0, 2; words, bracket, 0, 3.
而这是 words，方括号，0，1；words，方括号，0，2；words，方括号，0，3。
And then words, bracket, 1, 0.
然后 words，方括号，1，0。
So it's kind of like a two-dimensional array, almost.
所以它有点像一个二维数组，几乎。
And you can think about it that way if helpful.
如果你觉得有帮助，你可以这样想。
But for now, it's just applying the same principles to the code.
但现在，它只是将相同的原则应用到代码中。
So if I go to my code here and I've got my "HI!" and my "BYE!"--
所以如果我在这里去我的代码，我有我的“HI！”和我的“BYE！”--
this is going to look a little stupid, but let me change this %s to %c, %c,
这看起来有点蠢，但让我把这个 %s 更改为 %c，%c，
%c, and print out words, bracket, 0.
%c，并打印出 words，方括号，0。
words, bracket, 0, bracket 1.
words，方括号，0，方括号 1。
words, bracket, 0, bracket, 2 to print out that three-letter word.
words，方括号，0，方括号，2 来打印出那个三个字母的单词。
And now down here, let me print out %c, %c, %c,
现在在这里，让我打印出 %c，%c，%c，
%c because it's four letters in BYE, exclamation point.
%c 因为它在 BYE 中有四个字母，感叹号。
This is words, bracket, 1, but the first character; words, bracket, 1,
这是 words，方括号，1，但第一个字符；words，方括号，1，
the second character; words, bracket, 1, the third character;
第二个字符；words，方括号，1，第三个字符；
and words, bracket, 1, the fourth character.
以及 words，方括号，1，第四个字符。
It's hard to say when you're typing a different number,
当你输入不同的数字时，很难说，
but that's what we get by using zero indexing, so to speak.
但这就是我们使用零索引获得的，可以这么说。
make hi.
制作 hi。
Whew!
呼！
No mistakes.
没有错误。
"HI!"
“HI！”
Says the same thing.
说的是同一件事。
So again, there's no magic.
所以再说一次，没有魔法。
Like you are fully in control over what's going
就像你完全控制着正在发生的事情
on inside of the computer's memory.
在计算机的内存中。
And now that we have this array syntax with square brackets,
现在我们有了这个带有方括号的数组语法，
you can both create these things and then manipulate them or access them
你可以创建这些东西，然后操纵它们或访问它们
however you so choose.
根据你的选择。
Whew!
呼！
Questions on arrays or strings in this way?
关于数组或字符串以这种方式的问题？
Yeah, over here.
是的，这边。
AUDIENCE: Can you have any array that has multiple data types in it?
观众：你能有一个包含多个数据类型的数组吗？
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
大卫·马兰：好问题。
Can you have an array with multiple different data types?
你能有一个包含多个不同数据类型的数组吗？
Short answer, no; longer answer, sort of,
简短的回答，不；更长的回答，有点像，
but not in nearly the same user-friendly way as with languages
但不像 Python 或 JavaScript 等语言那样用户友好。
like Python or JavaScript or others.
例如 Python 或 JavaScript 等。
So assume for now arrays should be the same type in C. Other questions?
所以现在假设在 C 语言中，数组应该具有相同类型。还有其他问题吗？
Yeah, over here.
是的，这边。
AUDIENCE: When you talk about [INAUDIBLE]??
观众：当你说到 [听不清] ??
DAVID MALAN: Oh, a really good question.
大卫·马兰：哦，一个很好的问题。
It will-- so for those who couldn't hear,
它会——对于那些没有听到的人，
if you were to look past the end of one array,
如果你要看一下一个数组的末尾，
would you start to see the beginning of the second?
你会开始看到第二个的开头吗？
In this case, maybe the word "BYE!"
在这种情况下，也许是“再见！”这个词。
Could depend on the particulars of your code in the computer.
这可能取决于你的代码在计算机中的具体细节。
Let's try this.
让我们试试这个。
So let's get a little greedy here and go one past H-I, exclamation point,
所以让我们稍微贪心一点，在 H-I 后面加一个感叹号，
null character by looking at words, bracket, 0, 3,
通过查看单词、括号、0、3 来查看空字符，
which should actually be our null character, so that's going to be there.
它实际上应该是我们的空字符，所以它将存在于那里。
And actually, let's see.
实际上，让我们看看。
Let's go ahead and do this.
让我们继续执行这个操作。
Make hi ./hi.
将 hi 设置为 ./hi。
Still works as expected, but let me change this to integer,
它按预期工作，但我把它改为整数，
integer so we can actually see what's going on.
整数，这样我们就能真正看到发生了什么。
Integer.
整数。
And now, if I recompile make hi, I should see the same thing,
现在，如果我重新编译 make hi，我应该看到相同的东西，
but numerically.
但以数字形式。
And now what I think you're proposing is let's get a little crazy
现在我认为你建议我们稍微疯狂一点
and go even past that to what could be location 4,
并且超过它，到达可能的位置 4，
but we know semantically doesn't exist, but maybe is bumping up against "BYE!"
但我们知道语义上不存在，但可能正在与“再见！”发生碰撞。
So make hi ./hi.
所以将 hi 设置为 ./hi。
And guess what 66 is.
猜猜 66 是什么。
Well, just the B, but yes.
嗯，只是 B，但没错。
66, recall, is capital B because in week 0, capital A was 65.
请记住，66 是大写 B，因为在第 0 周，大写 A 是 65。
So indeed, now we're really poking around.
所以的确，现在我们真的在四处探查。
And you can get crazy.
你可以变得疯狂。
Like, what's 400 characters away and see what's going on there.
比如，400 个字符以外是什么，看看那里发生了什么。
Eventually your program will probably crash,
最终你的程序可能会崩溃，
and so don't poke around too much, but more on that in the coming days, too.
所以不要过多地四处探查，但在接下来的几天里，我们会详细介绍这一点。
All right, well how about some other revelations and problem-solving?
好的，我们来谈谈其他一些启示和问题解决方法吧？
Now coming back to the question about strings length earlier,
现在回到之前关于字符串长度的问题，
and we'll see if we can then tie this all together to something
我们将看看是否可以将所有这些结合起来，
like cryptography in the end and manipulating strings
最终像密码学一样，操纵字符串
for the purpose of sending them securely.
目的是安全地发送它们。
So let me propose that we go into VS Code here again in a moment.
所以，我建议我们过一会儿再回到 VS Code 中。
And I'm going to create a program called length.
我将创建一个名为 length 的程序。
Let's actually figure out ourselves the length of a string initially.
让我们先自己弄清楚一个字符串的长度。
So I'm going to go ahead and code length.c.
所以我将继续编写 length.c 代码。
I'm going to go ahead and include cs50.h.
我将继续包含 cs50.h。
I'm going to include stdio.h, int main void.
我将包含 stdio.h，int main void。
And then inside of main, I'm going to prompt the user for their name.
然后在 main 内部，我将提示用户输入他们的姓名。
get_string, quote-unquote, "Name."
获取字符串，引号括起来，"姓名"。
And then I'm going to go ahead and I want
然后我要
to count the length of this string.
计算这个字符串的长度。
But I know what a string is now.
但我现在知道字符串是什么了。
It's char, char, char, char, and then eventually the null character.
它是一个字符，一个字符，一个字符，一个字符，然后最终是空字符。
So I can look for that.
所以我可以寻找它。
And I can write this in a few different ways.
我可以用几种不同的方法来写它。
I know a bunch of different types of loops now,
我现在知道很多不同类型的循环，
but I'm going to go with a while loop by first declaring a variable n,
但我要用一个 while 循环，首先声明一个变量 n，
for number of characters, set it equal to 0.
表示字符数，将其设置为 0。
It's like starting to count with your fingers all down,
就像开始用手指往下数一样，
and I want to do the equivalent of this, counting each of the letters
我想要做等效的事情，计算我输入的每个字母
that I type in.
的个数。
So I can do that as follows.
所以我可以用以下方法来做。
While the name variable at location n does not equal,
当位置 n 处的 name 变量不等于
quote-unquote, backslash 0, which looks weird,
引号括起来，反斜杠 0，看起来很奇怪，
but it's just asking the question, is the character
但它只是在问，这个字符
at that location equal to the so-called null character?
在这个位置等于所谓的空字符吗？
Which is written with single quotes and backslash 0 by convention.
按照惯例，它是用单引号和反斜杠 0 写成的。
And what I want to do, while that is true, is just add 1 to n.
而我想要做的，当这是真的时，就是将 n 加 1。
And then at the very bottom here, let's just go ahead and print out with %i
然后在最下面这里，让我们直接用 %i 打印出来
the value of n because presumably if I type in HI, exclamation point,
n 的值，因为如果我输入 HI，感叹号，
I'm starting at 0 and I'm going to have H, I, exclamation point,
我从 0 开始，我要有 H、I、感叹号，
null character so I don't increment n a fourth time.
空字符，所以我不会在第四次递增 n。
So let's go ahead and run down here.
所以让我们继续运行到这里。
make length ./length, Enter.
make length ./length，回车。
Well, I guess I'm asking for name, so I'll do my name for real.
好吧，我想我是在要名字，所以我会用我的真实名字。
David, five characters, and I indeed get 5.
David，五个字符，我确实得到了 5。
If I used a for loop, I could do something similar,
如果我使用 for 循环，我可以做类似的事情，
but I think this while loop approach, much like our counter from the past,
但我认为这种 while 循环方法，就像我们过去使用的计数器一样，
is fairly straightforward.
相当简单。
But what if I want to do this?
但如果我想要这样做呢？
What if I want to make another function for this?
如果我想要为此创建一个新的函数呢？
Well, I could do that.
好吧，我可以这样做。
Let me--
让我 -
All right, let's do this.
好吧，让我们来做这个。
Let's write a quick function called string_length.
让我们编写一个名为 string_length 的简短函数。
It's going to take a string called s or whatever as input.
它将以一个名为 s 或其他任何字符串作为输入。
And then you know what?
然后你知道吗？
Let's just do this in that function.
让我们直接在这个函数中执行这个操作。
I'm going to borrow my code from a moment ago.
我要借用我之前写过的代码。
I'm going to paste it into this function.
我要把它粘贴到这个函数中。
But I'm not going to print out the length,
但我不会打印出长度，
I'm going to return the length n.
我要返回长度 n。
So I have a helper function of sorts that's
所以，我有一个辅助函数，它
going to hand me back the length of the string,
将把字符串的长度返回给我，
and that's why this returns an int, but takes a string as its argument.
这就是为什么它返回一个 int，但接收一个字符串作为参数的原因。
How do I use this?
我该如何使用它？
Well, first, I do need to copy the prototype
好吧，首先，我需要复制原型。
so I don't get into trouble as before.
所以我不再像以前那样陷入麻烦。
Semicolon.
分号。
And then in my main function, what I think I can do now
然后在我的主函数中，我认为我现在可以做的事情是
is something like this.
像这样。
I can do int length equals the string length of the name variable
我可以做 int length 等于 name 变量的字符串长度
that was just typed in.
刚刚输入的。
And now using printf %i, print out length, semicolon.
现在使用 printf %i，打印出 length，分号。
So exact same logic.
所以逻辑完全一样。
The only thing I've done that's different this time is I've
这一次我做的不同的事情是
added a helper function just to demonstrate
添加了一个辅助函数来演示
how I can take some pretty basic functionality,
如何获取一些非常基本的功能，
find the length of a string, and modularize it
找到字符串的长度，并将其模块化
into a function abstract it away so I never again have
进入一个函数抽象它，这样我就不必再
to copy-paste that for loop.
复制粘贴那个 for 循环。
I now have a function called string_length
我现在有一个名为 string_length 的函数
that will solve this problem for me.
可以为我解决这个问题。
Whoops, wrong program. make length.
糟糕，程序错了。 make length。
Huh.
嗯。
Use of undeclared identifier 'name.'
使用未声明的标识符“name”。
What did I do wrong?
我做错什么了？
Apparently on line 16 of length.c, what did I do wrong here?
显然在 length.c 的第 16 行，我在这里做错了什么？
Yeah, in front.
是的，前面。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Good.
大卫·马兰：好。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Good.
大卫·马兰：好。
Perfect terminology.
完美的术语。
So name is local to main.
所以 name 对于 main 来说是局部的。
The scope of name is main, though sounds similar, but different words.
name 的作用域是 main，尽管听起来很相似，但却是不同的词。
And so I'm actually should be calling this
所以实际上我应该把它叫做
s because s is the name of the local variable being passed in even though it
s，因为 s 是被传递进来的局部变量的名称，即使它
happens to be 1 and the same as name because on line 9,
碰巧与 name 相同，因为在第 9 行，
I'm indeed passing in name as the argument.
我确实将 name 作为参数传递进来。
All right.
好的。
So this is where, again, copy-paste can sometimes get you into trouble.
所以，这里再次说明了，复制粘贴有时会让你陷入困境。
Let's try to make length again.
让我们再试着 make length。
Now it works. ./length, D-A-V-I-D, and now we have a function that seems to be
现在它可以工作了。 ./length，D-A-V-I-D，现在我们有一个似乎可以工作的函数。
working.
工作。
But this is such like commodity functionality.
但这就像商品功能一样。
Like my God, like surely someone before us
我的天啊，肯定在我们之前
has written a function to get the length of a string before,
已经写过一个函数来获取字符串的长度，
and indeed, other people have.
事实上，其他人已经写过了。
So it turns out that in C, just as you have the stdio library,
事实证明，在 C 中，就像你拥有 stdio 库一样，
you also have a string library whose header file is called, appropriately,
你还有一个字符串库，它的头文件被称为，恰当地，
string.h.
string.h。
In fact CS50 has documentation, therefore, in its own manual pages,
事实上，CS50 在自己的手册页中拥有文档，
so to speak, along with some sample usage thereof.
可以说是，连同一些示例用法。
But it turns out, in the string library, there
但事实证明，在字符串库中，存在
is a very popular function analogous to the Python one
一个非常受欢迎的函数，类似于你之前询问的 Python 函数
that you asked about earlier called strlen
叫做 strlen。
where strlen, one word, no underscores, just
其中 strlen，一个单词，没有下划线，仅仅
figures out the length of a string.
计算出一个字符串的长度。
And honestly, I've never looked at its source code,
老实说，我从未看过它的源代码，
but it probably uses a while loop, maybe it uses a for loop,
但它可能使用 while 循环，也许它使用 for 循环，
but it certainly uses the same idea of just iterating-- that is,
但它肯定使用相同的迭代思想——也就是说，
walking from left to right over a variable
从左到右遍历一个变量
in order to figure out what the length of a given string is.
以便找出给定字符串的长度。
So how do we use this?
所以我们如何使用它？
Well if I go back to VS Code here, I can throw away
好吧，如果我回到 VS Code，我可以扔掉
the entirety of my string length function,
我的整个字符串长度函数，
I can throw away the prototype, therefore,
我也可以扔掉原型，因此，
and I can include a third header file, string.h, inside
我可以在里面包含第三个头文件 string.h，
of which I claim now is this function called strlen
我声称现在是这个名为 strlen 的函数
that I can just now use out of the box for free
我现在可以直接免费使用
because someone else wrote this function for me.
因为其他人为我写了这个函数。
And string.h will teach the compiler that it exists.
而 string.h 会告诉编译器它存在。
So if I now do make length and ./length, now I have a similarly working program
所以如果我现在执行 make length 以及 ./length，我现在就有了一个类似的工作程序
that doesn't bother having me write unnecessary code.
它不让我编写不必要的代码。
So this is another example of a library.
所以这是库的另一个例子。
The string library is just going to make our lives easier by not having to--
字符串库只是为了让我们的生活更轻松，而不必——
for us not having to reinvent some wheel.
为了让我们不必重新发明轮子。
All right, well where else does this get interesting?
好的，那么这个还有哪些有趣的地方呢？
How about something like this?
比如这样怎么样？
Let me go back into VS Code here.
让我回到 VS Code 中。
Let's create a program called string.c--
让我们创建一个名为 string.c 的程序——
we'll play around with our own strings-- that's going to start similarly.
我们将会使用我们自己的字符串——开始部分类似。
So let's include cs50.h, let's include stdio.h,
所以让我们包含 cs50.h，让我们包含 stdio.h，
let's include string.h so we can use that same strlen function.
让我们包含 string.h，这样我们就可以使用相同的 strlen 函数。
int main void.
int main void。
And inside of this, let's do this.
在里面，让我们做这个。
Let's get a string s and prompt the user for any old string as input.
让我们获取一个字符串 s，并提示用户输入任何字符串。
All right.
好的。
And then let's go ahead and maybe print out, quote-unquote, "Output."
然后让我们继续打印，带引号的，"Output"。
And I'm just going to line up my spaces just right because these words are
而且我只是一直把我的空格对齐，因为这些单词是
slightly different lengths, but we'll see why I'm doing this.
长度略有不同，但我们会看到我为什么这么做。
It's just for aesthetics' sake in a moment.
只是一会儿为了美观。
And let's go ahead now and do this.
现在让我们继续做这个。
If I want to print out every character in a string, how can I now do this?
如果我想打印出字符串中的每个字符，我现在该怎么做呢？
Well, this is actually a pretty common task
好吧，这实际上是一项很常见的任务
even though this version, thereof, will seem pointless. for int i gets 0,
尽管这个版本看起来毫无意义。 for int i gets 0，
i is less than the length of s.
i 小于 s 的长度。
i++ is just the conventional way to start a loop that iterates from left
i++ 只是从左开始迭代循环的常规方法
to right over a string of that length.
到该长度字符串的右侧。
And then let's go ahead and print out each character, %c,
然后让我们继续打印出每个字符，%c，
printing out the string at location i using our fancy new array syntax.
使用我们新奇的数组语法打印出位置 i 处的字符串。
And at the very end of this program, let's just
在这个程序的最后，让我们只是
print out a new line character just to move the cursor to the bottom
打印一个新的换行符，以将光标移到底部
like we've done in the past.
就像我们过去所做的那样。
So this is kind of a stupid program like I am reinventing the wheel that is
所以这有点像一个愚蠢的程序，就像我重新发明了轮子一样
the %s format code.
%s 格式代码。
I already know that printf can print out a whole string.
我已经知道 printf 可以打印出一个完整的字符串。
Suppose it didn't.
假设它没有。
Suppose I forgot about %s and I only knew about %c,
假设我忘记了 %s，我只知道 %c，
these lines of code here collectively will print out the entirety of a string
这里这些代码行将共同打印出字符串的全部内容
character by character based on its length.
逐个字符地基于它的长度。
So if I compile this program, make string ./string and type in my name--
所以如果我编译这个程序，使字符串 ./string 并输入我的名字 -
for instance, David, the output is D-A-V-I-D,
例如，大卫，输出是 D-A-V-I-D，
and here's why I hit the spacebar an extra time,
这就是我多按一次空格键的原因，
because I wanted input and output to line up nicely so we could see that
因为我希望输入和输出整齐地排列，这样我们就可以看到
they're, in fact, the same length.
它们实际上是相同的长度。
So let me just stipulate.
所以让我声明一下。
This code is correct, but there is an inefficiency with this line of code.
这段代码是正确的，但是这行代码存在效率低下。
Let's talk about design instinctively.
让我们本能地谈谈设计。
What is maybe bad about this line of code 9--
这行代码 9 有什么不好的地方 -
line 9 that I've highlighted?
我高亮显示的第 9 行？
This one is subtle.
这个很微妙。
Let's go over here.
让我们看看这里。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：是的。
I'm calling strlen inside of the loop again and again and again.
我在循环内部一遍又一遍地调用 strlen。
Why?
为什么？
Well, recall how for loops worked.
好吧，回忆一下 for 循环是如何工作的。
When we walked through it last week, that middle part of for loop
当我们上周遍历它时，for 循环的中间部分
in between the semicolons keeps getting checked, keeps getting checked,
在分号之间一直被检查，一直被检查，
keeps getting checked.
一直被检查。
And so if you put a function call there, which is totally fine syntactically,
所以如果你在那里放一个函数调用，在语法上是完全可以的，
you're asking the same damn question again and again and again.
你一遍又一遍地问同一个问题。
And the length of David, D-A-V-I-D, is never changing.
而大卫的长度，D-A-V-I-D，是永远不变的。
So strlen, implemented decades ago by some other human,
所以 strlen，几十年前由其他人实现，
has some kind of loop in it, and you're literally
它里面有一些循环，而你实际上
making that code run again and again and again just
一遍又一遍地运行那段代码，仅仅
to get the same answer 5 again and again.
为了再次得到相同的答案 5。
So I think your instinct is right.
所以我觉得你的直觉是对的。
I could come up with another variable outside of the loop.
我可以想出一个循环之外的另一个变量。
I could do something like this.
我可以做这样的事情。
int length equals strlen of s, and then I could just plug that in.
int length 等于 s 的 strlen，然后我就可以直接把它插进去。
But there's a slightly more elegant way.
但是有一个更优雅的方式。
If you like doing things with slightly less code,
如果你喜欢用更少的代码来做事情，
this is correct as I've now written it.
现在我写的这个是正确的。
It's less efficient-- it's more efficient because I'm only
它效率更低 - 它效率更高，因为我只
calling strlen once now on this new line 9,
现在在这条新的 9 行代码上调用一次 strlen，
but a more common way to write this would typically
但是更常见的写法通常
be to do something like this.
是这样的。
After initializing i, you can also initialize something else like length.
在初始化 i 之后，你也可以初始化其他东西，比如 length。
And you can set length equal to strlen of s, then your semicolon,
你可以将 length 设置为 s 的 strlen，然后你的分号，
and now you can say while i is less than that length.
现在你可以说当 i 小于那个长度时。
Or I can tighten this up further.
或者我可以进一步压缩它。
If it's just a number and it's a super short loop, might as well just call it
如果它只是一个数字，并且是一个超短循环，不妨直接把它叫做
n.
n。
So this now would be a canonical way of implementing the exact same idea,
所以这现在将是实现完全相同想法的规范方法，
but without the inefficiency because now you're
但没有效率低下，因为现在你正在
calling strlen in the initialization part of for loop,
在 for 循环的初始化部分调用 strlen，
not inside of the Boolean expression that gets checked and executed
而不是在被检查和执行的布尔表达式中
again and again.
一次又一次地执行。
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不见]
DAVID MALAN: Correct.
大卫·马兰：没错。
Well, I'm declaring i as an int, but by way of the comma,
好吧，我将 i 声明为一个 int，但通过逗号，
I am also declaring n as an int.
我也将 n 声明为一个 int。
So they've got to be the same type for this trick to work.
所以它们必须是相同类型，这个技巧才能起作用。
Good observation.
观察得很好。
Other questions on this one here?
还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
Well, let's play around further here.
好吧，让我们在这里再玩一玩。
Let me propose that there's other libraries and header files
让我提议一下，还有其他库和头文件
as well that you might find useful.
也可能对你很有用。
There's also something called ctype, which relates to types
还有一个叫做 ctype 的东西，它与类型有关
and c's that's got a bunch of useful functions
和 C 语言，它包含许多有用的函数
that we can actually see if we visit the documentation here.
我们可以在这里访问文档，就能看到。
But before we get there, let me actually whip up
但在此之前，让我实际写一个
a program that maybe does something a little bit fun, albeit low level,
程序，它可能做一些有趣的事情，尽管比较低级，
like forcing some string to uppercase if the human types it in lowercase.
比如强制某个字符串大写，如果人类输入的是小写。
So let me go ahead and write a program called uppercase.c.
所以，让我继续编写一个名为 uppercase.c 的程序。
Let me go ahead and give myself the same header files.
让我继续给自己相同的头文件。
Include cs50.h, include stdio.h.
包含 cs50.h，包含 stdio.h。
And for now, let's include string.h for the length.
现在，让我们包含 string.h 以获得长度。
And let's go ahead and have int main void as before.
然后让我们像以前一样，将 int main void 添加进来。
And inside of main, let's give myself a string
在 main 内部，让我们给自己一个字符串
s equaling get_string "Before," just so I know what the string is initially.
s 等于 get_string "Before"，这样我就知道字符串最初是什么。
Now I'm going to print out proactively "After" with two spaces
现在，我将主动打印 "After"，并带有两个空格
just so that things line up aesthetically on the screen
这样，屏幕上看起来就会美观一些
because "After" is one character shorter.
因为 "After" 少了一个字符。
And now I'm going to do the same technique as before.
现在，我将使用与之前相同的技术。
for int i equals 0, n equals the string length of s, i is less than n, i++.
对于 int i 等于 0，n 等于 s 的字符串长度，i 小于 n，i++。
And then inside of this loop, what do I want to do logically?
然后在这个循环内部，我从逻辑上想做什么？
I want to force these characters to uppercase if they are, in fact,
如果这些字符实际上是小写，我想将它们强制大写。
lowercase.
小写。
And so how might I do this?
那么我该怎么做呢？
Well, there's a bunch of ways to express this,
好吧，有很多方法可以表达这一点，
but I'm going to do it maybe the most straightforward way
但我会以最直接的方式来做
even if you've not seen this before.
即使你以前没见过。
If the current letter in the string at location i,
如果字符串中位置 i 处的当前字母，
because I'm in a loop starting from 0 all the way up to, but not
因为我是在一个从 0 开始一直到，但没有的循环中，
through the string length, is greater than
在字符串长度内，大于
or equal to a lowercase a, in single quotes, and that letter is less than
或等于单引号内的一个小写字母a，并且该字母小于
or equal to a lowercase z.
或等于一个小写字母z。
What does this mean in English?
用英语怎么说呢？
Well, this essentially means if lowercase--
本质上，如果小写——
logically, if it's greater than or equal to little a and less than
从逻辑上讲，如果它大于或等于一个小写字母a，并且小于
or equal to little z, it's somewhere between a and z in lowercase.
或等于一个小写字母z，那么它就在a和z之间。
What do I want to do?
我想做什么？
Well, I want to force it to uppercase.
我想把它强制转换成大写。
So I want to print out a character without a new line yet
所以我想打印一个字符，但还没有换行
that prints out the current character, but force it to uppercase.
它会打印出当前的字符，但将其强制转换成大写。
Well, how can I do this?
怎么做呢？
Well, this is where this gets into some low-level hacking,
这就是我们要进入一些低级黑客的领域，
but notice the same ASCII chart.
但请注意相同的ASCII表。
Here's our uppercase letters from last time.
这是我们上次的大写字母。
Here's our lowercase characters, and let me highlight those.
这是我们的所有小写字母，我将它们高亮显示。
Does anyone notice a relationship between capital A and lowercase a
有没有人注意到大写字母A和小写字母a之间的关系
that happens to be the same for capital B and lowercase b?
对于大写字母B和小写字母b来说，这种情况也一样？
AUDIENCE: Capital A [INAUDIBLE].
观众：大写字母A[听不清]。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：是的。
Like this pattern is true.
这种模式是正确的。
So 97 minus 65 is 32, and that's true for every lowercase and uppercase
所以97减去65等于32，这对所有的小写字母和大写字母来说都是正确的
letter respectively.
字母来说都是一样的。
So I can leverage that.
所以我可以利用这一点。
And this is not a CS50 thing.
这不是CS50专属的。
Like this is ASCII.
这是ASCII码。
This is, in turn, Unicode.
这也反过来，是Unicode。
This is how modern computers work.
这就是现代计算机的工作方式。
So if I go back to VS Code here, you know what I could do.
所以如果我回到VS Code，你应该知道我能做什么。
Let's just literally subtract 32.
让我们直接减去32。
But because I'm displaying this as a char, not as an int,
但因为我将它显示为char，而不是int，
I'm going to see the lowercase letter seemingly become an uppercase instead.
我将看到小写字母似乎变成了大写字母。
Else, if it's not lowercase-- maybe it's already uppercase,
否则，如果它不是小写字母——也许它已经是大写字母，
maybe it is punctuation, let's just go ahead and print out with %c
也许它是标点符号，让我们直接用%c打印出来
the original character unaltered.
原来的字符保持不变。
And then at the very end of this program,
然后在这个程序的最后，
let's print a new line just to move the cursor to the next line.
我们打印一个换行符，让光标移动到下一行。
All right, so let's do make uppercase.
好了，让我们来执行make uppercase。
And let me type ./uppercase.
我输入./uppercase。
And I'll type in D-A-V-I-D, all lowercase, and now,
我输入D-A-V-I-D，全都是小写字母，现在，
you'll see it's in all caps.
你会看到它变成了全大写。
If, though, I type in maybe my last name but capitalized M, that's OK,
但是，如果我输入我的姓，但M是大写的，没关系，
the rest of it will still be capitalized for me.
其余的字母仍然会自动变成大写。
Now I don't love this technique.
我对这种方法不太满意。
It's a little bit fragile because I had to do some math.
它有点脆弱，因为我需要做一些数学运算。
I had to check my reference sheet and then incorporate it into my program.
我不得不查看参考表，然后将其纳入到程序中。
Even though it will be correct, I could be a little more clever.
虽然它是正确的，但我可以更聪明一点。
I could actually do something like this.
我可以这样做。
Well, whatever the value of lowercase is--
无论小写的值是多少——
lowercase a is minus whatever the value of capital A is,
小写字母 a 是大写字母 A 的值减去某个值，
and I could actually do it arithmetically even though that, too,
我实际上可以进行算术运算来实现，尽管这种方式也
is somewhat inefficient in that it's asking the same question again
在一定程度上效率低下，因为它重复询问同一个问题
and again, but the compiler is probably smart enough to optimize that.
又一次，但编译器可能足够智能，可以优化它。
And frankly, for those more comfortable, a good compiler
坦率地说，对于那些更舒适的人来说，一个好的编译器
will also notice, no, no, no, no, you don't
也会注意到，不，不，不，不，你不会
want to call strlen again and again.
想一遍又一遍地调用 strlen。
The compiler can do some of these optimizations for you,
编译器可以为你做一些这些优化，
but it's still good practice to get into yourself.
但养成自己这样做的习惯仍然是好的。
But there's probably a better way.
但可能有一种更好的方法。
Instead of rolling this solution ourselves
而不是自己编写这个解决方案
and subtracting 32 or doing any arithmetic,
并减去 32 或进行任何算术运算，
let's use that ctype library.
让我们使用那个 ctype 库。
Let me go back up to my header files.
让我回到我的头文件。
Let's additionally include ctype.h.
让我们另外包含 ctype.h。
Let's pretend like I read the documentation in advance, which I did,
让我们假装我提前阅读了文档，事实上，我确实阅读了，
in fact.
确实。
And let's instead of doing any math here,
让我们不要在这里进行任何数学运算，
let's use a function that exists in that library called toupper
让我们使用该库中存在的名为 toupper 的函数
and pass to it whatever the current character is in s at location i.
并传递给它 s 中位置 i 的当前字符。
Otherwise, I still print out the unchanged character.
否则，我仍然打印出未更改的字符。
And let me go ahead and do make uppercase ./uppercase.
让我继续执行 make uppercase ./uppercase。
And now without any math, no subtracting 32, that, too, also works.
现在，没有任何数学运算，没有减去 32，它也工作了。
But it gets better.
但它变得更好了。
If you read the documentation for toupper,
如果你阅读 toupper 的文档，
it turns out its documentation tells you, if C is already uppercase,
事实证明，它的文档告诉您，如果 C 已经是大写，
it just passes it through for you.
它只是为你直接传递它。
So you don't even need to ask this conditional question.
所以你甚至不需要问这个条件问题。
I can actually cut this to my clipboard, get rid of all of this,
我实际上可以剪切它到我的剪贴板，删除所有这些，
and just replace that one line only and just
只替换那一行，然后
let toupper handle the situation for me because again, its documentation
让 toupper 为我处理这种情况，因为再次，它的文档
has assured me that if it's already uppercase,
向我保证，如果它已经是大写，
it's just going to return the original value.
它只会返回原始值。
So if I make uppercase, this time, ./uppercase,
所以如果我执行 make uppercase，这次是 ./uppercase，
now it works and now things are getting kind of fun.
现在它工作了，现在事情变得有点有趣了。
I mean, these are mundane tasks, admittedly,
我的意思是，这些都是平凡的任务，不可否认，
but at least I'm standing on the shoulders of smart people
但至少我站在了之前那些聪明人的肩膀上
who came before me who implemented the string library, the ctype library--
他们在我之前实现字符串库、ctype 库——
heck, even the CS50 Library so I don't need to reinvent any of those wheels.
哎呀，甚至 CS50 库，所以我不需要重新发明这些轮子。
Questions on any of these library techniques?
关于这些库技术的任何问题？
It's all still arrays, it's all still strings and chars,
它们仍然都是数组，它们仍然都是字符串和字符，
but now we're leveraging libraries to solve some of our problems for us.
但现在我们正在利用库来为我们解决一些问题。
All right.
好的。
So let's come full circle to where we began,
所以让我们回到起点，
where and I mentioned that some programs include
我在那里提到一些程序包括
support for command line arguments.
对命令行参数的支持。
Like Clang takes command line arguments words after the word clang.
比如 Clang 会接受命令行参数，这些参数是 clang 之后的所有词。
CD, which you've used in Linux, takes command line arguments.
CD 命令，你在 Linux 中用过，它接受命令行参数。
If you type cd, space, pset1 or cd, space,
如果你输入 cd，空格，pset1 或者 cd，空格，
mario in order to change directories into another folder.
mario 来改变目录到另一个文件夹。
If you do rm like I did earlier, you can remove a file
如果你像我之前一样使用 rm，你可以删除文件
by using a command line argument, a second word that
通过使用命令行参数，也就是第二个词，它
tells the computer what to remove.
告诉计算机要删除什么。
Well, it turns out that you, too, can write
实际上，你也可以编写
code that takes words at the command prompt and uses them as input.
接受命令提示符中的词语并将其作为输入的代码。
Up until now, you and I have only gotten user input via get_string, get_int,
到目前为止，我们只通过 get_string、get_int、
get_float, and functions like that.
get_float 和类似的函数获取用户输入。
You, too, can write code that take command line arguments which,
你也可以编写接受命令行参数的代码，这些参数实际上，
frankly, just save the human time.
节省了人类的时间。
They can type their entire thought at the command line, hit Enter, and boom,
他们在命令行输入完整的想法，按下回车，然后，
the program can complete without prompting them and re-prompting them
程序可以在没有提示他们的情况下完成，并且不会再次提示他们
again.
。
So here's where we can now start to take off some more training wheels.
所以现在我们可以开始去掉一些辅助轮了。
Up until now, we've just put void inside of the parentheses here any time
到目前为止，我们每次在实现 main 时，都只是在括号里写 void
we implement main.
。
It turns out that you can put something else in parentheses
事实证明，在使用 C 语言时，你可以在括号中写其他内容
when using C. It's a mouthful, but you can replace void
。这个表达有点长，但是你可以用它来替换 void
with this bigger expression.
。
But it's two things.
但这包含两部分。
int, called argc by convention, and a string,
int，按照惯例称为 argc，以及一个字符串，
but not a string, actually an array of strings called argv.
但实际上不是字符串，而是一个称为 argv 的字符串数组。
And these terms are a little arcane, but argc means
这些术语有点晦涩，但 argc 代表
argument count-- how many words did the human type at the prompt?
参数数量——用户在提示符中输入了多少个词？
Argv stands for argument vector, which is generally
Argv 代表参数向量，它通常
another term for an array--
是数组的另一个术语——
you've heard it perhaps from mathematics.
你可能在数学中听说过。
It's like a list of values, or in this case, a list of command line arguments.
它就像一个值列表，或者在本例中，是一个命令行参数列表。
So C is special.
所以 C 语言很特殊。
If you declare main as not taking void inside of parentheses, but rather,
如果你声明 main 在括号中不接受 void，而是
an int and an array of strings, C will figure out
一个 int 和一个字符串数组，C 语言会弄清楚
whatever the human typed at the prompt and hand it to you
用户在提示符中输入的内容，并将它传递给你
as an array and the length thereof.
作为数组以及它的长度。
So if I want to leverage this, I can start
所以如果我想利用这一点，我可以开始
to implement some programs of my own that actually incorporate command line
实现一些我自己的程序，这些程序实际上包含命令行
arguments.
参数。
For instance, let me go back in a moment here to VS Code.
例如，让我回到 VS Code 这里。
Let me create a program, for instance, called greet.c
让我创建一个程序，例如，名为 greet.c
that's just going to greet the user in a few different ways.
它将以几种不同的方式向用户问候。
So let me first do it the old way. cs50.h.
所以我先用旧方法来做。cs50.h。
Let me include stdio.h.
让我包含 stdio.h。
Let me do int main void still.
让我仍然使用 int main void。
So the old way.
所以这是旧方法。
And if I want to greet myself or Carter or Yulie or anyone else,
如果我想向我自己、Carter、Yulie 或其他任何人问候，
I could do, old fashioned now, get the answer from the user, get_string.
我可以像现在这样，用老方法从用户那里获得答案，使用 get_string。
Let's prompt for "What's your name?" question mark,
让我们提示“你的名字是什么？”问号，
just like we did in Scratch.
就像我们在Scratch中所做的那样。
And then do printf, "Hello," comma, %s backslash n, answer.
然后执行printf，“你好，”逗号，％s反斜杠n，答案。
So we've done this many times now this week and last.
所以我们这周和上周已经做了很多次了。
This is the old school way now of getting command line--
现在这是从命令行获取用户输入的传统方式——
of getting user input by prompting them for it.
通过提示用户来获取用户输入。
So if I do make greet /greet, there's no command line arguments at the prompt,
所以如果我执行make greet /greet，提示符处没有命令行参数，
I'm literally just running the program's name.
我只是在运行程序的名字。
If I hit Enter, though, now get_string kicks in, asks me for my name,
但是，如果我按回车键，get_string就会启动，询问我的名字，
and the program then greets me.
然后程序向我问好。
But I can do--
但我可以——
otherwise, I could do something like this instead.
否则，我可以尝试执行类似的操作。
First, answer's a little generic, so let's first change
首先，答案有点泛泛，所以让我们先更改
this back to name and back to name, but that's a minor improvement there
将其改回name并改回name，但这只是那里的小幅改进
just stylistically.
仅从样式上来说。
Let's, though, introduce now a command line argument
但是，让我们现在引入一个命令行参数
so that I can just greet myself by running the program, hitting Enter,
这样我就可以通过运行程序、按下回车键来向自己问好，
and being done, no more get_string.
并且完成操作，不再需要get_string。
So I'm going to go ahead and change void to int argc, string
所以我会继续将void更改为int argc，string
argv with square brackets.
带方括号的argv。
string means-- the square brackets means it's an array;
string表示——方括号表示它是一个数组；
string means it's an array of strings; and argc, again,
string表示它是一个字符串数组；并且argc再次，
is just an integer of the number of words typed.
只是一个输入单词数量的整数。
Now I'm going to somewhat dangerously going to do this.
我现在要进行一些危险的操作。
I'm going to get rid of my use of get_string altogether,
我将完全删除get_string的用法，
and I'm going to change this line to be not name, which no longer exists,
并且我将把这行代码更改为不再存在的name，
but I'm going to go into this array called argv
但是我会进入这个叫做argv的数组
and I'm going to go into location 1.
并且我会进入位置1。
So I'm doing this on faith.
所以我相信这一点。
I haven't explained what I'm doing yet, but I'm going to do make greet ./greet,
我还没有解释我要做什么，但我将执行make greet ./greet，
and now I'm going to type my name at the command line just like with rm,
现在我要在命令行中输入我的名字，就像使用rm一样，
with clang, with cd.
使用clang，使用cd。
With any of the commands you've written with multiple words,
对于你用多个单词编写的任何命令，
I'm going to greet literally David.
我会向David问好。
So I hit Enter, and voila, I've somehow gotten access
所以，我按回车键，瞧，我不知何故获得了访问
to what I typed at the prompt by accessing this special parameter called
通过访问这个名为
argv.
argv的特殊参数。
Technically you could call it anything you want, but the convention is
从技术上讲，你可以随意称呼它，但惯例是
argv and argc from right to left here.
从这里向右到左依次为argv和argc。
Just a guess, then.
仅仅猜测一下。
What if I change this to print out bracket 0 and recompile the code?
如果我将它更改为打印出方括号0并重新编译代码呢？
And I run ./greet David?
然后我运行./greet David？
What might it say instinctively?
它可能会本能地说些什么？
Any hunches?
有什么预感吗？
Yeah.
是的。
So it's going to say hello, ./greet.
所以它会说你好，./greet。
So it turns out, you get one for free.
所以，你免费得到一个。
Whatever the name of your program is always
无论你程序的名字是什么，它总是
accessible in argv at location 0.
可以在argv的位置0访问。
That's just because.
这只是因为。
It's a handy feature.
这是一个方便的功能。
In case there's an error or you need to tell the user how to use the program,
如果出现错误或需要告诉用户如何使用程序，
you know what the command is that they ran, but at location 1,
你知道他们运行的是什么命令，但在位置 1，
maybe 2, maybe 3 are the additional words
可能还有 2、3 个额外的单词
that the human might have typed in.
是用户可能输入的。
Well, let's do something a little smarter than this.
好吧，让我们做点比这更聪明的事。
Let me go back to version 1.
让我回到版本 1。
Let me recompile it, make greet.
让我重新编译它，生成 greet。
Let me rerun ./greet David, and this seems to work fine.
让我重新运行 ./greet David，这似乎工作正常。
What if I get a little curious and print out location 2?
如果我有点好奇，并打印出位置 2 呢？
Let me recompile the code, make greet ./greet David, Enter, OK, there's null.
让我重新编译代码，生成 greet，./greet David，Enter，OK，出现了 null。
And I mentioned we'd see N-U-L-L, and here's one incarnation thereof,
我提到我们会看到 N-U-L-L，这里就是其中一个体现，
but this is clearly wrong.
但这显然是错误的。
So I probably don't want to even let the user do this because I
所以，我可能甚至不想让用户这样做，因为我
don't want them to see bogus output.
不想让他们看到错误的输出。
Like this is arguably the a bug in the code
就像这可以说是代码中的一个 bug
that it even bothered to show this by default. So what could I do instead?
它甚至默认显示了这一点。那么我该怎么办呢？
Well, what if I do this?
好吧，如果我这样做呢？
If argc equals equals 2, then go ahead and comfortably
如果 argc 等于 2，那么继续并轻松地
say printf "hello," argv, bracket, 1.
说 printf "hello," argv，方括号，1。
Else, if the human did not give exactly two arguments at the prompt,
否则，如果用户在提示符处没有给出恰好两个参数，
let's just print out some default value like "hello, world"
让我们只打印出一些默认值，例如 "hello, world"
like from last week.
就像上周一样。
In other words now I'm doing this error checking with a conditional,
换句话说，我现在正在用条件语句进行错误检查，
making sure with this Boolean expression only
确保只有使用这个布尔表达式
if argc equals equals 2, and therefore has two words in argv
如果 argc 等于 2，因此 argv 中有两个单词
do you want to proceed.
你想继续吗？
And so now if I do make greet again, ./greet David, this now works.
所以，如果我再次生成 greet，./greet David，它现在可以工作了。
But if I don't cooperate and I just run greet, what should it say?
但如果我不配合，只运行 greet，它应该说什么呢？
Just hello, world.
就说 hello, world。
If I run David Malan as two words, what should it say?
如果我将 David Malan 作为两个单词运行，它应该说什么呢？
hello, world, because that's not exactly equal to 2.
hello, world，因为这并不完全等于 2。
Again, the first word in argv is always the program's name.
再说一次，argv 中的第一个词总是程序名。
The second word is whatever the human, then, has typed.
第二个词就是用户当时输入的任何内容。
Now if we don't even know in advance how many words they're going to be,
现在，如果我们事先甚至不知道会有多少个单词，
we can combine today's ideas.
我们可以将今天的想法结合起来。
This is going to look a little weird, but it's the same thing as before.
这看起来会有点奇怪，但它和以前是一样的。
for int i gets 0, i is less than--
对于 int i 获取 0，i 小于--
how about argc i++?
argc i++ 怎么样？
And then inside of this loop, I can print out %s, maybe backslash n, comma,
然后在这个循环内部，我可以打印出 %s，可能是反斜杠 n，逗号，
and then print out argv, bracket, i.
然后打印出 argv，方括号，i。
So I can have a loop that iterates argc number of times,
所以，我可以创建一个循环，循环 argc 次，
once for every word at the prompt.
每次循环都对应一个提示符处的单词。
I can print out argv, bracket, i, which is the i-th word in that array
我可以打印出 argv，方括号，i，它是该数组中的第 i 个词
from left to right.
从左到右。
And so if I now run make greet and I do ./greet alone,
所以，如果我现在运行 make greet，并且我单独运行 ./greet，
I just see the program's name.
我只是看到了程序的名字。
If I do ./greet David, I see, those two, one after the other.
如果我运行 `./greet David`，你会看到这两个词，一个接一个地显示。
If I do David Malan, I get those three words.
如果我运行 `David Malan`，我会得到这三个单词。
If I keep going, I'll get more and more words.
如果我继续下去，我会得到越来越多的单词。
So using just the length of the array and the name of the array,
所以，仅使用数组的长度和数组的名称，
I can actually do quite a bit there.
我实际上可以做很多事情。
Now there's actually some fun things you can do with this,
现在，你实际上可以用这个做一些有趣的事情，
and this is sort of beside the point, but there's
这有点偏题，但它存在于
this thing in the world called ASCII art, which
世界上一个叫做 ASCII 艺术的东西，它
is making pictures and beautiful things just using ASCII or maybe
是用 ASCII 或现在的 Unicode 字符来制作图片和美丽的事物，但它不使用表情符号。
nowadays Unicode characters, but without using emoji.
现在 Unicode 字符，但没有使用 emoji。
Like emoji kind of make this a little too easy.
就像表情符号让这个变得太容易了。
But if all you have are traditional largely English letters
但是，如果你只有传统的英语字母
and punctuation, you can actually do some interesting things.
和标点符号，你实际上可以做一些有趣的事情。
On Linux systems-- for instance, if I go back to VS Code here,
在 Linux 系统上——例如，如果我回到 VS Code 这里，
let me increase the size of my terminal window here.
让我增加一下终端窗口的大小。
And it turns out that we've pre-installed-- really,
事实证明，我们已经预安装了——确实，
for no compelling reason, but just for fun, a program called cowsay,
出于没有强有力的理由，只是为了好玩，一个叫做 `cowsay` 的程序，
which has a cow say something.
它让一头牛说一些话。
So if I want to have a cow say "moo" in ASCII art, I can do this,
所以，如果我想让一头牛用 ASCII 艺术说 “moo”，我可以这样做，
and you get an adorable cow saying something like "moo" on the screen.
你会看到一头可爱的牛在屏幕上说着像 “moo” 之类的话。
But moo is a command line argument that is clearly
但是 `moo` 是一个命令行参数，很明显
modifying the output of this program because I could also
修改了这个程序的输出，因为我也可以
change it to say hello, comma, world, and now the cow
把它改成说 “hello, world”，现在这头牛
is going to say that instead.
会说这句话了。
So it takes multiple command line arguments, if you will.
所以，它接受多个命令行参数，如果你愿意的话。
But it also takes what are called flags or switches whereby any command line
但它也接受所谓的标志或开关，任何以短横线开头的命令行
argument that starts with a dash is usually like a special configuration
参数通常就像一个特殊的配置
option that you would only know exists by reading the documentation
选项，你只有通过阅读文档才能知道它的存在
or seeing a demonstration.
或观看演示。
And if I have my syntax right, if I do cowsay -f, and maybe I'll do--
如果我的语法正确，如果我运行 `cowsay -f`，也许我会做——
let's see.
让我们看看。
Instead of this cow say, how about I'll do -f for file,
而不是这只牛，我试试用 `-f` 代表文件，
and I'm going to change it into duck mode.
我要把它改成鸭子模式。
And I'm going to have this version of the ASCII art say quack.
我让这个版本的 ASCII 艺术说 "quack"。
So it's a tiny little duck there, but it's saying quack.
这是一个小小的鸭子，但它在说 "quack"。
And you can kind of waste a lot of time doing this.
你可以花很多时间做这个。
I can do cowsay -f dragon and say something like, RAWR,
我可以运行 `cowsay -f dragon` 并说一些像 “RAWR” 之类的话，
and this is just amazing.
这太棒了。
Again, not really academically compelling,
再次强调，这在学术上并不引人注目，
but it does demonstrate, again, command line arguments, which are everywhere,
但它再次证明了命令行参数，它们无处不在，
and you've indeed been using them already.
而你确实已经在使用它们了。
But there's one other feature we wanted to introduce you
但我们想向你介绍另一个功能，
to today, which will be a useful building block, which will also
在今天，它将是一个有用的构建块，它也将
reveal one other thing about the code that we've been writing.
揭示关于我们一直在编写的代码的另一件事。
It turns out that all of the programs we've been writing thus far, eventually
事实证明，到目前为止，我们编写的所有程序最终
obviously exit because you see your prompt again
都会退出，因为您会再次看到您的提示
unless you have an infinite loop such that it never ends.
除非您有一个无限循环，这样它永远不会结束。
But eventually they exit.
但最终它们都会退出。
And secretly, every program we've written thus far actually
而且实际上，到目前为止，我们编写的每个程序
has what's called an exit status.
都有一个所谓的退出状态。
It's like a special return value from the program
它就像程序的一个特殊返回值
itself that by default is always 0.
本身，默认情况下始终为 0。
0 as a number in the world generally means everything's OK.
在世界上，0 作为一个数字通常意味着一切正常。
The flip side of that is because the world tends to use integers
另一方面，这是因为世界倾向于使用整数
and you've got four billion possibilities,
而你有 40 亿种可能性，
like every other number in the world when it comes to our program's exit
就像世界上所有其他数字一样，当谈到我们程序的退出时
status is bad.
状态就不好。
If it's 1, it's probably bad.
如果它是 1，它可能就不好了。
If it's negative 1, it's bad.
如果它是负 1，它就不好。
And in fact, you've probably seen this in the real world.
事实上，您可能在现实世界中见过这种情况。
If you've ever had like a random error message on the screen--
如果您曾经在屏幕上看到过随机错误消息——
here's a screenshot of Zoom, for instance.
例如，这里是一张 Zoom 的截图。
And that screenshot, somewhat confusingly or unknowingly,
而且那张截图，有点令人困惑或不知情，
has an error code like 1132, that probably
有一个错误代码，比如 1132，这可能
means that the Zoom software that some other humans wrote incorrectly somehow
意味着 Zoom 软件，其他一些人类错误地编写了它，以某种方式
had an error and it did not exit with status 0, it exited with status 1132.
出现了错误，它没有以状态 0 退出，而是以状态 1132 退出。
And somewhere at Zoom, there's probably a file
在 Zoom 的某个地方，可能有一个文件
or a book that tells the programmers what this error code actually means.
或一本书告诉程序员这个错误代码的实际含义。
This is not useful for you and me.
这对您和我来说没有用。
There's some programmer at Zoom who would probably be like,
Zoom 的某个程序员可能会说，
oh, I know what I did or my colleague did wrong in this case.
哦，我知道我或我的同事在这种情况下做错了什么。
You've seen this elsewhere even though this is not quite the same thing,
您在其他地方见过这种情况，即使它并不完全相同，
but we'll talk about this in a few weeks.
但我们将在几周后讨论这个问题。
If you've ever seen 404, like numbers are everywhere, and on the web,
如果您曾经见过 404，就像数字无处不在，在网上，
404 means like file not found.
404 代表文件未找到。
It means you made a typo, the web server deleted a file, or something like that,
这意味着您输入错误，Web 服务器删除了文件，或者类似的事情，
but this is just to say numbers are so often used to signify or represent
但这只是为了说数字经常被用来表示或代表
errors.
错误。
Even though that's not an exit status, per se,
即使它本身不是退出状态，
that's an HTTP status code, which we'll soon see.
那是 HTTP 状态码，我们很快就会看到。
But you have access to exit statuses as it relates
但您已经可以访问退出状态，因为它与
to command line software already.
命令行软件相关。
Up until now, this is how we've been writing main, now
到目前为止，这就是我们一直编写 main 的方式，现在
with command line arguments, but we've also
使用命令行参数，但我们也
been writing main with an int return value.
一直在使用 int 返回值编写 main。
And you've never used this-- we didn't talk about this last week.
而且您从未使用过它——我们上周没有谈论过这个。
I just ask that you trust me and just keep copying and pasting this.
我只是要求您相信我，并继续复制和粘贴这个。
But that int means that even your programs
但是 int 意味着即使您的程序
can return values which can be useful even if you don't use command line
可以返回值，即使您不使用命令行，这些返回值也很有用
arguments and we just go back to the original version like void.
参数，我们只是回到原始版本，比如 void。
So for instance, if I go ahead and open up, for instance, VS Code again,
例如，如果我继续打开 VS Code，
I'll get rid of the dragon.
我会去掉这条龙。
And let's do one other program here called status just
让我们在这里做另一个程序，叫做 status，
to play around with the idea of these so-called exit statuses.
来试着玩玩这些所谓的退出状态。
Let me just demonstrate the idea with an include cs50.h, include
让我用 include cs50.h 来演示这个概念，
stdio.h, int main, and here I'll do int argc, string argv.
stdio.h，int main，在这里我会写 int argc，string argv。
And then inside of main, let's do a similar program
然后在 main 内部，让我们做一个类似的程序，
to before like the hello, world.
和之前的 hello world 一样。
So printf "hello," comma, %s backslash n.
所以 printf "hello," 逗号，%s 反斜杠 n。
Then let's print out argv 1.
然后让我们打印出 argv 1。
But I only want to execute that line if the human gave me a command line
但我只想在用户给了我一个命令行的时候执行那行代码。
argument.
参数。
Otherwise I don't want to even say some default like hello, world.
否则，我甚至不想说一些默认值，比如 hello world。
I just want to abort early and just exit the program, no output whatsoever.
我只想尽早终止并退出程序，没有任何输出。
So I could do this.
所以我可以这样做。
If argc does not equal 2--
如果 argc 不等于 2 - -
and it's a single equals, but it's a bang, an exclamation point,
它是一个单一的等于号，但它是一个感叹号，
means not equal.
表示不等于。
So this is the opposite of equals equals.
所以这是等于等于的反面。
Then previously I would have just printed hello, world,
然后我之前会直接打印 hello world，
but now I want to print out an error message
但现在我想打印一个错误信息，
like, "Missing command-line argument" just to explain to the user
比如 "缺少命令行参数"，只是为了向用户解释
why the program is about to terminate, and then I can return 1.
为什么程序要终止，然后我可以返回 1。
It's kind of arbitrary.
这有点随意。
I could also return 1132, but why start there?
我也可以返回 1132，但为什么要从那里开始？
This is the only possible error that could go wrong in my program.
这是我的程序中唯一可能出错的地方。
So I'm going to start at 1.
所以我将从 1 开始。
Zoom clearly has 1,000-plus possible things that can go wrong
Zoom 显然有 1000 多种可能出错的地方
in their source code, which is why the number got as big as 1132,
在他们的源代码中，这就是数字为什么变得如此大的原因，
but I'm just going to arbitrarily, but conventionally return 1.
但我只是随意地，但传统上返回 1。
But if everything is OK and I do-- it is not the case that argc does not equal 2
但如果一切正常，而且我确实 - - argc 不等于 2 并非如此
and I actually get to line 11, I'm going to return 0 because 0, again, I claim,
而我实际上到了第 11 行，我会返回 0，因为 0，我再说一次，
signifies success.
表示成功。
And all of this time, every program we've written-- you've written
而且一直以来，我们编写的每个程序 - - 你编写的每个程序
has secretly exited with 0 by default. But now
默认情况下，它都悄悄地退出了，返回 0。但现在
that our programs are getting more sophisticated,
我们的程序越来越复杂了，
when something goes wrong, it turns out it's
当发生错误时，事实证明，
useful to have the power to just return some other value even
能够返回其他值是有用的，即使
though the user is not going to see it.
用户不会看到它。
Even though the Zoom user shouldn't see it, it's still there.
即使 Zoom 用户不应该看到它，它仍然在那里。
It's diagnostically useful to you, or in the case of a class,
这对你有诊断意义，或者在课堂上，
to your TF or TA or CA.
对你指导老师、助教或助教来说。
So if I do make status now to compile this program and run ./status and type
所以如果我现在用 make status 来编译这个程序，然后运行 ./status 并且输入
my first name I think this is a success.
我的名字，我认为这是成功的。
It should say hello, David and secretly exit with 0.
它应该说 hello，David，并秘密地退出，返回 0。
If you really want to see the 0, there's this arcane command you can type.
如果你真的想看到 0，有一个神秘的命令你可以输入。
You can literally type at your prompt echo $?.
你可以直接在你的提示符中输入 echo $?。
It's weird symbology, but it's what the humans chose decades ago.
这是一个奇怪的符号，但这是人类几十年前选择使用的。
This will just show you what did the most recently-run program secretly exit
这只会显示最近运行的程序秘密退出的状态。
with.
状态。
So if I do this in VS Code, I can do exit $?, Enter,
所以如果我在 VS Code 中这样做，我可以输入 exit $?，然后回车，
and there's that secret 0.
就会显示那个秘密的 0。
I could have been doing this week and last week, it's
我可能这周和上周都在这样做，这
just not that interesting.
没什么意思。
But it is interesting, or at least marginally so, if I rerun status
但如果我重新运行 status，这很有趣，或者至少有点意思，
and maybe I don't provide a command line argument or I provide too many.
并且也许我没有提供命令行参数，或者我提供了太多。
So argc does not equal 2.
所以 argc 不等于 2。
And I hit Enter, I get yelled at with the error message,
然后我按回车，我收到了错误消息，
but I can see the secret status code, which is, indeed, 1.
但我可以看到秘密的状态码，它确实是 1。
And so now if you're ever in the habit in either a class like this
所以现在如果你在像这样的课程中，或者在现实世界中，你自动测试你的代码，
or in the real world where you're automatically testing your code,
在现实世界中你自动测试你的代码，
be it with check50 or in the real world, things called
无论是用 check50 还是在现实世界中，称为
unit tests and other third-party software,
单元测试和其他第三方软件，
those tests can actually detect these status code-- exit statuses
这些测试实际上可以检测这些状态码 - 退出状态
and know that your code succeed or fail, 0 or 1.
并且知道你的代码成功还是失败，0 或 1。
And if there's different types of failures it can detect--
如果存在不同类型的错误，它可以检测到 -
status 2, status 3, status 1132, it's just one other tool in your toolkit.
状态 2，状态 3，状态 1132，它只是你的工具包中的另一个工具。
But all of that is terribly low level, and really,
但所有这些都非常底层，实际上，
the goal of this week-- and really, today, and really, code more generally,
本周的目标 - 实际上，今天，以及更广泛地来说，代码
is to solve problems.
是为了解决问题。
So let's consider an increasingly important one, which
所以让我们考虑一个越来越重要的问题，即
is the ability to send information securely,
安全发送信息的能力，
whether it is in file format, wirelessly, or any other.
无论是文件格式、无线还是其他方式。
Cryptography is the art and the science of encrypting.
密码学是加密的艺术和科学。
Scrambling information.
对信息进行混淆。
So that even if I write a secret message to you
所以即使我写了一封秘密信息给你
and I send it through this open audience with so many nosey eyes
并且我通过这个开放的公众发送它，那里有那么多窥探的眼睛
who could look at the message, if I've encrypted this message, none of them
谁都可能看到这条消息，如果我对这条消息进行了加密，他们中的任何人都
should be able to read it, only you, whoever you are,
无法阅读它，只有你，无论你是谁，
to whom I intended that message.
我打算把这条信息发给你。
In the world of cryptography, then encryption
在密码学领域，加密
means scrambling the information so that only you and the recipient
意味着对信息进行混淆，这样只有你和接收者
can receive it.
可以接收它。
So if we consider our black box like in week 0 and 1,
所以如果我们考虑像第 0 周和第 1 周的黑盒一样，
here is the problem to be solved.
这里就是需要解决的问题。
And let me propose a couple of pieces of vocabulary.
让我提几个词汇。
Plaintext is any message written in English or any human language
明文是任何用英语或任何人类语言写成的
that you want to send and write yourself.
你想发送并自己写的消息。
Ciphertext is what you want to convert it
密文是你想要转换它的内容
to before you just hand it off to a bunch of random strangers
在你把它交给一群随机的陌生人之前
in the audience or a bunch of servers on the internet,
在观众席上，或者互联网上的服务器，
any one of whom could look at your message.
他们中的任何一个人都可能看到你的消息。
So in the black box is what we're going to call
所以在这个黑盒子里，我们将称之为
a cipher, an algorithm for encrypting or scrambling information
一种密码，一种用于加密或混淆信息的算法
in a reversible way.
以可逆的方式。
It doesn't suffice to just scramble the information randomly,
仅仅随机地混淆信息是不够的，
otherwise the recipient can't do anything with it.
否则接收者就无法对其进行任何操作。
It's an algorithm, a cipher that encrypts it in such a way
它是一种算法，一种以这样一种方式对其进行加密的密码
that someone else can decrypt it.
其他人可以对其进行解密。
And here's a common way.
这里有一个常见的方法。
Most ciphers take as input not only the plaintext message in English
大多数密码不仅以英文形式的明文消息作为输入
or whatever else, but also a key.
或者其他任何东西，而且还需要一个密钥。
And it's metaphorically like a key to open a lock,
从比喻意义上来说，它就像一把打开锁的钥匙，
but it's technically generally a number, like a really big number made up
但在技术上，它通常是一个数字，就像一个由
of lots of bits.
许多位组成的非常大的数字。
And not even 32, not even 64, sometimes 1,024 bits, which is crazy
甚至不是32位，甚至不是64位，有时是1024位，这太疯狂了
unpronounceable large, but the probability
难以发音的巨大，但可能性
that someone is going to guess your key is just so, so small
有人猜到你的密钥的可能性非常、非常小
that for all intents and purposes, you are, in fact, secure.
因此，从所有意图和目的来看，你实际上是安全的。
So what's an example of this, for instance?
那么，举个例子，这是什么？
Suppose the secret message I want to send is innocuously just "HI!"
假设我想要发送的秘密消息只是无害的“HI！”。
Well, it'd be pretty stupid to write "HI!" on a piece of paper,
嗯，在纸上写下“HI！”是很愚蠢的，
hand it to someone in the audience, and expect
把它递给观众中的某个人，并期望
it to get all the way to the back without someone like glancing at it
它能一路传到后面，而不被人看到
and obviously seeing and reading the plaintext.
并显然看到并读出明文。
So what if I, though, agree with someone in back, for instance,
所以如果我和后面的人达成一致，例如，
that our secret is going to be 1?
我们的秘密将是1？
And we have to agree upon that secret in advance,
我们必须提前商定好这个秘密，
but 1 just means that is my key.
但1只是意味着这是我的密钥。
And let me propose that according to one popular cipher,
让我提议，根据一种流行的密码，
if I want to send "HI!", change the H to an I and the I to a J-- that is,
如果我想发送“HI！”，将H改为I，将I改为J，也就是说，
increment effectively every letter of the alphabet by one,
将字母表中的每个字母都增加1，
and if you get to a Z, wrap back around to A, for instance.
如果你到了Z，就绕回到A，例如。
So shift the alphabet by one place in this case
所以在这个例子中将字母表向后移一位
and send this message now instead.
然后现在发送这条消息。
So is that secure?
那么这样安全吗？
Well, if one of you kind of nosily looks at this sheet of paper,
嗯，如果你有人好奇地看看这张纸，
you won't see "HI!"
你不会看到“HI！”
You will see some information leak in this algorithm.
你将会看到这个算法中泄露了一些信息。
You'll see an exclamation point, so I'm enthusiastically saying something,
你会看到一个感叹号，所以我热情地说了一些东西，
but you won't know what the message is unless you decrypt it.
但你不会知道这条消息是什么，除非你进行解密。
Now that said, is this very secure, really, in practice?
也就是说，这在实践中真的非常安全吗？
I mean, not really.
我的意思是，不全是。
Like, if you know I'm just using a key and I'm using the English alphabet,
比如，如果你知道我只是在用一个密钥，并且在用英语字母表，
you could probably brute force your way to a solution
你可能会强行找出解决方法
by just trying 1, trying 2, trying 3, trying 25,
通过尝试1，尝试2，尝试3，尝试25，
go through all the possibilities tediously,
枯燥地尝试所有可能性，
but eventually it's probably going to pop out.
但最终它可能会被找到。
This is actually known, though, as the Caesar cipher.
不过，这实际上被称为凯撒密码。
And back in the day, before anyone else knew about or had invented encryption,
在很久以前，在其他人知道或发明加密之前，
Caesar, Julius Caesar, was known to use a cipher like this
凯撒大帝，也就是尤利乌斯·凯撒，以使用这种密码而闻名。
using a key of three, literally.
他使用了一个密钥，一个数字3。
And I guess it works OK if you're literally the first human in the world
我想，如果你真的是世界上第一个想到这个主意的人，那它应该还可以。
by lore to have thought of this idea, but of course, anyone who intercepts it
根据传说，但当然，任何截获它的人
could attack it nonetheless and figure things out a bit mathematically.
都可以破解它，并用数学方法进行解密。
13 is more common.
13 比较常见。
This is called ROT13 on the internet for rotate the letters of the alphabet 13.
这在网络上被称为 ROT13，代表将字母表中的字母旋转 13 位。
That changes "HI!" to "UV!"
它会将 "HI！" 变成 "UV！"
You might think what's better than 13?
你可能会想，什么比 13 更好呢？
Well, let's double the security.
嗯，让我们将安全性翻倍。
ROT26.
ROT26。
Why is this stupid?
为什么这是愚蠢的？
I mean, there's like 26 letters in the alphabet, so like A becomes A. So
我的意思是，字母表里有 26 个字母，所以 A 就变成了 A。因此，
that doesn't really help-- oh, wait.
这实际上没什么用处——哦，等等。
Oh, I'm pointing at something that's not on the screen, dammit.
哦，我在指向屏幕上没有的东西，该死。
Suppose the message is more lovingly, "I LOVE YOU," instead of just "HI!"
假设这条消息更甜蜜，是 "I LOVE YOU"，而不是仅仅 "HI！"
Same exact approach, whether or not there's punctuation, "I LOVE YOU,"
同样的方法，无论是否有标点符号，"I LOVE YOU"，
with an input of 13 might now become this.
输入 13 后，它可能会变成这样。
And now it's getting a little less obvious what the ciphertext actually
现在，密文实际上代表什么就不那么明显了。
represents.
代表什么。
And now, what's twice as secure is 13?
现在，什么比 13 安全两倍呢？
Well, 26 is surely better, but of course, if you rotate 26 places,
嗯，26 肯定更好，但当然，如果你旋转 26 个位置，
that, of course, just gives you the same thing.
那当然，你得到的还是相同的东西。
So there's a limit to this, but again, that just
所以，这有一定的局限性，但再次强调，这只是
speaks to the cipher being used, which is very simple.
说明所使用的密码非常简单。
There is much, much better, more sophisticated mathematical ciphers
有许多更好、更复杂的数学密码
that are used.
被使用。
We're just starting with something simple here.
我们只是从一个简单的例子开始。
As for decryption, if I'm using a key of 1, how do I reverse the process?
至于解密，如果我使用密钥 1，我如何逆转这个过程？
Yeah, so I just minus 1.
是的，我只需要减去 1。
So B becomes A, C becomes B, A becomes Z. And if it's 13,
所以 B 变成 A，C 变成 B，A 变成 Z。如果密钥是 13，
I subtract 13 instead or whatever the key is, so long as sender
我则减去 13，或者减去任何密钥的值，只要发送者
and receiver actually know it.
和接收者知道它就行了。
So in this case here, this is actually the message with which we began class.
因此，在这种情况下，这实际上是我们开始上课时所使用的消息。
If we have this message here and I used a key of 1 to encrypt it,
如果我们有这条消息，我用密钥 1 对它进行加密，
well, decrypting, it might involve doing something like this.
那么，解密可能需要做这样的事情。
Here's those same letters on the screen, and I think in a moment
这些相同的字母在屏幕上，我想过一会儿
before we adjourn, I'll mention too that we
在我们结束之前，我还想提一下，我们
might have encrypted a message in eight characters
可能用八个字符加密了一条消息。
this whole day, so if any of you took the time
在今天一整天，所以如果你有人花时间
and procrastinated and figured out what the light bulb spelled
拖延时间，并弄清楚灯泡拼写的是什么，
and they didn't seem to spell anything in English,
而且它们似乎没有拼出任何英语单词，
well, here now is the solution for cracking it.
那么，现在是破解它的方法。
This, if I subtract 1, becomes what?
如果我减去 1，它会变成什么？
U becomes T. And this is obviously-- see where we're going with this?
U 变成 T。很明显——你们明白我要说什么了吧？
And if we keep going, subtracting 1-- so indeed, we're at the end of class
如果我们继续减1，我们确实已经到了课程的结尾
now because this was CS50.
因为这是CS50
And the last thing we have to say is we have hundreds of ducks waiting for you
最后我们要说的是，我们有数百只鸭子在外面等着你
outside.
在外面
So on the way out, grab your own rubber duck.
所以出去的时候，抓一只你自己的橡皮鸭
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]